<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the report, concerning the present state of the differences in doctrinals, between some dissenting ministers in London, in reply to a book, enbtitled, A faithful rebuke of that report</title>
            <author>Lobb, Stephen, d. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215527</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827381</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827381</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31799</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48858)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31799)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1891:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the report, concerning the present state of the differences in doctrinals, between some dissenting ministers in London, in reply to a book, enbtitled, A faithful rebuke of that report</title>
                  <author>Lobb, Stephen, d. 1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Nath. Hiller, at the Prince's Arms in Leaden-Hall-Street, over against St. Mary Axe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: S.L., i.e. Stephen Lobb.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lobb, Stephen, d. 1699. --  Report of the present state of the differences in doctrinals, between some dissenting ministers in London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31799:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF THE REPORT, CONCERNING The <hi>Preſent State</hi> of the Differences in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinals, between ſome Diſſenting Miniſters in <hi>London;</hi> in <hi>REPLY</hi> to a Book, ENTITULED, A <hi>Faithful Rebuke</hi> of that <hi>Report.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>If I Build again the things which I Deſtroyed, I make my ſelf a Tranſgreſſor. <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal. 2.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>The Wiſdom that is from above is firſt <hi>Pure,</hi> then Peaceable, Gentle, and eaſie to be Entreated. <bibl>
                     <hi>Jam. 3.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The beſt way of Revenging an Injury is, not to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate or reſemble him that did it.</hi> Marc. Antonin. Lib. 6. § 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Hiller,</hi> at the <hi>Prince</hi>'s <hi>Arms</hi> in <hi>Leaden-Hall-Street,</hi> over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt St. <hi>Mary Axe,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:31799:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31799:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHEN the <hi>Report</hi> was Publiſhed, I being in the <hi>Countrey,</hi> on my Return, ſeveral made Enquiry touching my <hi>Thoughts</hi> of it; to whom my Anſwer was; That whoever was the <hi>Author,</hi> I <hi>knew</hi> the <hi>Matters of Fact,</hi> therein contained, to be <hi>True;</hi> and <hi>Believed</hi> the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, Explained and Aſſerted in the <hi>Healing Paper,</hi> and pleaded for in the <hi>Report</hi> to be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Gods Word; and that I ſhould be willing, if at any time called thereunto, to do my moſt for their Defence.</p>
            <p>Some <hi>Weeks</hi> after the <hi>Report</hi> had been Abroad, a <hi>Brother,</hi> who once, according to the <hi>Talent,</hi> wherein he excell'd, wrote in <hi>Vindication</hi> of the <hi>Common Faith,</hi> ſent forth a <hi>Rebuke</hi> to the <hi>Report;</hi> wherein both for <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> he has expreſſed himſelf quite otherwiſe than formerly he had Written, or his <hi>Trueſt</hi> Friends at this time expected; and has really
<pb facs="tcp:31799:3"/> given the Proteſtant Religion, in the Article of Chriſts <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> a moſt ſenſible Wound.</p>
            <p>Theſe Controverſies, I doubt not, upon an Apprehenſion, that none but the Enemy to Religion will be hereby the Gainer, are very grievous to many <hi>ſincere Chriſtians;</hi> who, when they ſhall conſider, how much the <hi>Truth,</hi> by this <hi>Colliſion,</hi> will be cleared; the moſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Doctrines of our Holy Religion, be more throughly underſtood; more Firmly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, as well as more Irrefragably Defended againſt the Oppoſition made unto it; will Admire the Divine Wiſdom, and Adore the Riches of Glorious Grace, in bringing ſo much Good out of theſe Miſchievous Diviſions, which have been, and are amongſt us.</p>
            <p>As for my own part, notwithſtanding the hard Cenſures of my <hi>Reverend Brother,</hi> I cannot forbare telling thee, That I deſire with my whole Soul to bleſs and praiſe the Lord, for the inſight he has given me into the Myſteries of <hi>Chriſts Goſpel,</hi> ſince this Controverſie hath been ſtated, and that I do <hi>now</hi> plainly ſee, how the very <hi>Truths,</hi> we were, through an unjuſtifyable <hi>Supineneſs,</hi> in danger of looſing, will, hereby be the more <hi>clearly Diſcovered</hi> and <hi>effectually Secured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſcourſes from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> even when about the moſt Evangelical Parts of Chriſtianity,
<pb facs="tcp:31799:3"/> having been of late Years, rather adjuſted to move the Affections than inlighten the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are but a <hi>ſlender Fence unto Truth;</hi> And an <hi>Obſervance,</hi> how they, who are ſound in the Faith, through a Zeal for <hi>Populacy,</hi> have neglected that Cloſe Study, which is neceſſary to a through underſtanding the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant</hi> Doctrines now under debate, hath emboldened the Adverſary to Oppugn them, and with the greater Vigour to attempt the expoſing the preſent <hi>Miniſtry</hi> amongſt us; and, to ſpeak freely, one Reaſon why our Brethren are ſo much confounded with the Noiſe of <hi>Common Terms and Phraſes,</hi> at this time Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted and ſo caſily Impoſed on, is their Diſuſe of ſuch Studies.</p>
            <p>But, it's hoped that theſe Conteſts will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke our Brethren to make more diligent Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries into the <hi>Doctrines of Satisfaction and Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> as it has already rouſed up ſome Great Men to reſolve on a Defence of the very Points, now exagitated amongſt us. For, as I have heard thus much of <hi>one</hi> very Learned Perſon; ſo I did the laſt Night receive the enſuing <hi>Letter</hi> from another; in which, you'l obſerve enough to convince you it is from one of the firſt Rate among the Learned, whoſe <hi>Sagacity,</hi> and Sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is Conſpicuous, and his Reſentments Deep.</p>
            <p>And, as the <hi>Truth,</hi> by theſe Methods will be abundantly cleared, ſo the <hi>ſureſt Foundation</hi> for
<pb facs="tcp:31799:4"/> a ſolid and laſting Union will be laid: For, whatever my Cenſorius Brother ſuggeſts to the contrary, 'tis the reſolution of the <hi>Congregational Brethren</hi> to do their moſt for PEACE, which they are ſure can never be laſting, if at the <hi>Expence</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> but let our <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren joyn with us in the Defence of ſome <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Truths now in danger, they will find us to go ſo far as 'tis poſſible, with a good <hi>Conſcience</hi> for <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> with them.</p>
            <p>That theſe Great Bleſſings may be obtain'd, is the fervent Prayer, and ſhall be the conſtant En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novem.</hi> 4. 1697.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>S. L.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>The <hi>Letter</hi> I mention, I will here inſert exactly as it came to my hands.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Nath. Hiller,</hi> at the <hi>Princes Arms</hi> in <hi>Leaden-hall-ſtreet,</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Mary Axe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Divine Inſtitution of Congregational Churches, <hi>Miniſtry and Ordinances,</hi> [As has been Profeſſed by thoſe of that <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion</hi>] Aſſerted and Proved from the Word of GOD. By <hi>Iſaac Chauncy,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>A Diſcuſſion of the Lawfulneſs of a Paſtors Acting as an <hi>Officer</hi> in other Churches beſides <hi>that</hi> which he is ſpecially Called to take the Overſight of. By the late Reverend Mr. <hi>Nath. Mather.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:31799:4"/>
            <head>To my Reverend, and much Eſteemed Friend Mr. <hi>Stephen Lobb.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Could heartily have wiſhed, that there had been no Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion adminiſtred for thoſe Accuſations, wherewith the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Congregational</hi> Divines have of late mutually charged one another. And though I do ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believe, that the <hi>Latter</hi> are as remote from all Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs to <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> as moſt of the <hi>Former</hi> are from being Tainted with <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> or the having Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the <hi>Dogmata</hi> of <hi>Socinus;</hi> yet ſome <hi>Crude</hi> Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of each Party, whoſe good Opinion of themſelves, doth far exceed their Knowledge in thoſe Controverſies, have had the misfortune to ſpeak leſs accurately, than the avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the being thought Infected with thoſe <hi>Heterodoxies,</hi> would have exacted of them. But, as for your <hi>Rebuker</hi> I will venture to ſay, that he hath not only Departed from the Received Opinions of moſt <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Divines, but that he hath Treſpaſs'd againſt all the Rules of good Breeding and Modeſty in his <hi>Pedantick,</hi> as well as Inſolent way of Writing. For, tho' I have not the vanity to pretend the being very Converſant in the <hi>Socinian</hi> and <hi>Arminian</hi> Controverſies; yet I dare affirm that the <hi>phraſes,</hi> which he aſſumes the liberty to Ridicule, as well as to Oppoſe, are thoſe that they of the greateſt character for Learning, who have Written either againſt the <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> or them of the <hi>Racovian</hi> Belief, have both uſed, and judged neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be adopted into their Debates, not only as a Fence about the Received Faith, and a Barrier againſt Irrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon common Chriſtianity, but as ſuch without which the Doctrines of <hi>Chriſts Satisfaction,</hi> and of our <hi>Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:31799:5"/> could neither be Orthodoxly nor Intelligibly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And were it not, that I intend to <hi>Imbarque in this Diſpute,</hi> in caſe it be further ſupported on his part, I could at preſent eaſily expoſe the Ignorance of your <hi>Rebuker,</hi> both in <hi>Claſſical</hi> and in <hi>Theological</hi> Authors, which whenſoever I do, you may aſſure your ſelf it ſhall not be in the <hi>Harle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin</hi> and <hi>Scarramuchio</hi> ſtile. Nor do I think your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor will much raiſe his Reputation, by his ſetting up for an Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Droll,</hi> ſeeing beſides the Indecency of it, he will by few be thought the more <hi>Witty</hi> for acting the <hi>Buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foon.</hi> For a ſmall meaſure of <hi>Intellectuals,</hi> if accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a great degree of <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> will qualifie any man to <hi>Burleſque</hi> all that is Sacred, and thereby to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance him among ſuch as are truly ſerious to the Title of Blaſphemous and Atheiſtical. And you may eaſily ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, how not only your Gentlemen of the <hi>Dry-Club</hi> (whoſe <hi>Libertiniſm</hi> was too long countenanced as well as connived at by ſome amongſt you) but your Partizans a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Revealed Religion, will hug themſelves upon the Preſident ſet them by this <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> in his Treating the moſt important Articles of the Chriſtian Faith with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt as well as a Jocularneſs, which either a Wiſe or Sober Man would not allow himſelf to uſe, even in relation to the Dreams and Romances of <hi>Mahomet.</hi> And to deal with you without reſerve, I will not be poſitive, in conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what his Opinion is in theſe Controverſies, tho' I fully underſtand the Language wherein he expreſſeth it, ſeeing I have an <hi>Exemplar</hi> before me of his ſincerity, in an <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue</hi> upon an Addreſs in which his meaning hath ſince appeared <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be Contradictions to what he ſaid. But I will add this in Extenuation of the Authors guilt, that he uſeth ſometimes to be Delirous, and that then both his <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> and Diſtemper lead him to be Divertive and <hi>Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> whereas when his <hi>Lucida</hi> returns, he leaves the <hi>Stage</hi> and puts off his <hi>Buskins,</hi> and reaſſumes the Gravity of a <hi>Theologue,</hi> and exchangeth the Language of the <hi>Theatre</hi> for that of the Pulpit.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir Adieu.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:31799:5"/>
            <head>A REPLY TO A Faithful Rebuke.</head>
            <p>IN my Endeavours to Clear the Report of the <hi>Preſent</hi> State of the Differences, in Doctrinals, between ſome Diſſenting Miniſters, in <hi>London,</hi> from the Charge of <hi>Falſhood;</hi> and Vindicate the <hi>Congregational</hi> Brethren from the Accuſation of being <hi>Antinomian;</hi> I will paſs over the Delicate Language, with which the <hi>Rebuker</hi> hath <hi>Adorn'd</hi> his Diſcourſes, as what is becoming neither the <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and <hi>Sacred</hi> Matters treated on, nor a <hi>Divine,</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or a <hi>Gentleman;</hi> Wondring, that the Checks of his Friends, and the Senſe of the like Contempt and Neglect, with which ſome years ago, his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Accoſted him, when he had a Better Cauſe to Defend, have had no more Influence on him: Eſpecially conſidering, that He is now Drawing ſo very near to that Age, which few Attain unto. But being of Opinion, that what this Reverend Brother hath herein done, is as much the Effort of another Man's Heats as of his own <hi>Diſturbed Thoughts,</hi> I wou'd Hope, that on a ſerious Review, when he ſhall Reflect, not only on his way of Writing; but on the <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Severity</hi> of thoſe Accuſations,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31799:6"/> which He hath, contrary to Truth, and without the leaſt Ground, loaded his <hi>Congregational Brethren</hi> with, he will ſee cauſe to <hi>Bewail</hi> what now He ſeems to <hi>Triumph</hi> in. I ſay, paſſing by theſe things, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe may rather Provoke than Enlighten; I will Confine my ſelf to what he hath Objected againſt the <hi>Reporter</hi> and his <hi>Brethren,</hi> which may be Reduced to <hi>Matters of Fact, Doctrines of Faith,</hi> and <hi>Cha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge of Antinomianiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I. Of <hi>Matters of Fact.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="rebuke">
                  <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="margSglQuotes">
                        <hi>THE Reporter hath miſerably Impoſed upon you in</hi> Matter of Fact, <hi>and — 1. One</hi> Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimen <hi>of his Honeſty, you ſhall meet with at the Entrance of his Paper — And thus in a Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous Stile, He Breaks into the Buſineſs</hi> after Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry attempts made by the <hi>Induſtrious Pa<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ficators, <hi>an</hi>
                        </hi> Inſtrument was pi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch'd upon, which gave ſatisfaction to the moſt Learned of both Parties: This Paper was ſent by ſix, or ſeven of the Biggeſt Name among them, who do, or at leaſt have gone under the Denomination of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>esbyterians,</hi> unto ſome <hi>Congregational</hi> Brethren, and gladly Embraced by them, <hi>p. 12.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>This is one part of the <hi>Charge</hi> of <hi>Falſhood</hi> againſt the <hi>Report,</hi> and yet there is not One Word mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Place, but what is <hi>True.</hi> For, (1.) After ſundry Attempts, an <hi>Inſtrument</hi> was Pitch'd upon, which you have in the cloſe of the Report. (2.) This was ſent unto the <hi>Congregational</hi> Brethren, by ſix or ſeven of the Biggeſt name among the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians,</hi> of which number Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi> was one, as the Brethren to whom it was ſent can, and they by whom
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:31799:6"/> it was ſent muſt Teſtifie. (3.) That it was ſent by ſome of the Biggeſt Name, is manifeſt, for the Hands of Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> and Mr. <hi>Howe</hi> are to the Letter, by which it was tranſmitted to the Congregational. (4.) That this Paper was gladly received by the <hi>Congregational;</hi> their own Subſcription doth Evince. (5.) That it gave ſatisfaction to the moſt Learned of both Parties, it is but to read over the Names of them who ſubſcribed it, and it will be found moſt True. (6.) That Mr. <hi>Mather</hi>'s, and Mr. <hi>Cole</hi>'s hands were not ſet to this Paper, was not, becauſe they Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved not of the Doctrines therein contained, for they both in the Hearing of many declared their Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, tho' for ſome other Reaſons declined Subſcription.</p>
                  <p>Where then is the <hi>Falſhood?</hi> No where but in my Brothers own Imaginations; who adds,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="rebuke">
                  <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Now Sir do you not Judge, that this Inſtrument — had Redintegrated the violated Union — That all Diſtances were removed — That they were all now got together again at <hi>Little St. Hillens?</hi> I aſſure you Sir, not a <hi>word of this was true.</hi> p. 13.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>No Sir, we had no reaſon to Judge thus, but the quite contrary, for there was not a word of this in the <hi>Report,</hi> where it's expreſly affirmed, (1.) <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That when matters were brought to this Head [as above] nothing but a Re-union, and a general Amneſty was in <hi>Proſpect.</hi> It was you ſee but in <hi>Proſpect,</hi>
                     </hi> not come to an Accompliſhment; And, 'tis added, (2.) <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That this Re-union had enſued, had it no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> been for two or <hi>three Oppoſers,</hi>
                     </hi> ſo that, unleſs the Oppoſition made unto the <hi>Healing Inſtrument;</hi> and the <hi>laying it by,</hi> doth ſignifie, that this Inſtrument had Redintegrated the violated Union, and brought all of 'em together again to <hi>Little St. Hellens,</hi> there is not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31799:7"/> there cannot be the leaſt Pretence for the charge of <hi>Falſhood.</hi> And whether theſe Expreſſions ſignifie what is moſt contrary to their genuine meaning, I ſubmit it to my Brother's <hi>more ſober</hi> Thoughts, and in the mean time will take it for granted, That there is nothing <hi>Falſe</hi> in this part of the <hi>Report,</hi> and paſs on to his <hi>ſecond Inſtance.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="rebuke">
                  <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi rend="margSglQuotes">2. A ſecond Inſtance of the <hi>Reporters</hi> regard to <hi>Truth,</hi> where you will eaſily obſerve how by a <hi>Wretched Sen<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>chdoche,</hi> he has given you a part for the whole of a <hi>Juſt Narrative.</hi> p. 14.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Reporter</hi> never Pretended to give a <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> of the <hi>whole:</hi> He knew that the doing ſo would rather widen than cloſe the wound; and therefore, it being his Deſign, whilſt he gave an account of what was done towards the making up the Breach, and where the laſt Stop was, to Soften and Prepare the Minds of the Brethren <hi>for Peace,</hi> He Induſtriouſly wav'd, as any one might perceive, the giving a <hi>Full Narrative</hi> of the <hi>whole:</hi> and in the Title Page, He Declared, That his Report was of the <hi>Preſent State,</hi> and therefore, not of what had paſſed ſome years ago. How then can any, conſiſtently with Truth, ſay, that by a <hi>Wretched Senechdoche,</hi> He hath given you a part for the whole of a <hi>Juſt Narrative?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. A Deſire to <hi>Accommodate matters</hi> ſo far as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, upon the <hi>Bottom</hi> of Truth, lyeth ſo much upon his Heart, that he doth <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> fixedly Reſolve a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt what is likely to Exaſperate. And therefore tho' this Brother hath given ſuch a <hi>Partial</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntrue</hi> Hiſtory of the whole, Relating to the Diviſion, as cannot be Detected without Publiſhing what we ought (I think) mournfully to cover. He Obligeth me at leaſt for the Preſent, to conceal ſuch Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, as much as ſincere Affection to the Truths of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31799:7"/> Chriſt's <hi>Goſpel</hi> will allow; which I am the rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to do, becauſe I find, that when the Report did ſo <hi>calmly</hi> give but a few Intimations about what had been done for Peace, what Advances had been made towards it by divers of the moſt Eminent of each Party, where the ſtop was, and what would Heal, they have put my Brother in to ſuch a Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Thought, as moves ſome to Fear, that a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough ſearch into this Hiſtory, will diſcover ſuch Miſtakes, and give him ſuch a Diſturbance, as to make him wholly Unfit for that good work, for which God hath given him an Excellent Talent, and to which, with a ſincere Reſpect to him and his further Uſefulneſs, I do Heartily Wiſh he would hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Confine himſelf.</p>
                  <p>Having thus Cleared the <hi>Report</hi> from the Charge of <hi>Falſhood,</hi> as to <hi>matter of Fact,</hi> I will make what convenient haſt I can, to conſider what he hath Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered about <hi>Doctrinals.</hi> And to ſet what Relates hereunto, in the cleareſt Light, I muſt beg my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Patience to Obſerve, what is neceſſary to be ſuggeſted on this Occaſion. For, it muſt be Incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated. 1. That we have no Controverſie with any Aſſembly of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Miniſters,</hi> as <hi>ſuch;</hi> not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we know of no ſuch meeting that hath been of late months at <hi>Little St. Hellens;</hi> but becauſe, when there were ſuch <hi>Meetings,</hi> they did not ſet their hands unto the Offenſive Book, and never Expreſſed any other way their Approbation of it.</p>
                  <p>That the meeting of Miniſters at <hi>Little St Hellens,</hi> is not compoſed of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Brethren,</hi> is manifeſt, in that the <hi>Congregational,</hi> who are an eſſential Part of the <hi>Union,</hi> have not (if we may believe my Brother) met with them. For he aſſures us, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That they <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually with-drew from their Aſſemblies,</hi> and Common-Meetings; and not only ſo, but ſet up another Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite-Meeting in a Neighbouring Place, at the very
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31799:8"/> Hour, and on the ſame day that the United Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren Aſſembled at Dr. <hi>Anneſleys; Some few</hi> of them would now and then drop in, when they had occaſion to ſerve themſelves of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly there was one or two to <hi>ſpie out their Liberty.</hi> Fa. Reb. p. 21.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now what manner of Union can there be between two Parties, when there is but one Party to make it up? But,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The generality of thoſe Brethren, who were Paſtors of Churches, and did ſet their Names unto the Teſtimonial before the <hi>Offenſive Book,</hi> did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by rather intend to expreſs their Juſt Abhorrence of <hi>Antinomian</hi> Dotages, than an Approval of the Book: for divers of them never Read the Book; nor can they bear, that the ſetting their hands unto the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation praefixed unto it, ſhould be Interpreted, as if it had been unto the <hi>Book,</hi> but only unto the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>Truths</hi> and <hi>Errors</hi> therein mentioned, and not unto the <hi>Preface, Explications,</hi> or <hi>Proofs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the true Reaſon, which influenced ſeveral of them, who meet at <hi>Little St. Hellens</hi> to Reject the <hi>first Paper</hi> was an Apprehenſion, that the Teſtimony, it gave againſt <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> was not ſo full as they could wiſh and thought needful (tho' it was as <hi>full</hi> as 'tis <hi>now,</hi> in the <hi>third</hi> Paper.) Not that they diſlik'd the Renunciation of <hi>Arminian,</hi> or <hi>Socinian</hi> Errours.</p>
                  <p>However, it muſt be acknowledged to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſingular, if not unparallel in them, who Reject the <hi>firſt Paper,</hi> that, notwithſtanding the Complaints of our Offened Brethren, the Nature of the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Charged on the Offenſive-Book; and the many miſchievous and fatal Conſequences, that have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the Setting their Hand unto the Teſtimonial before it, they have not hitherto, that I can hear, Condeſcended ſo far, as to Examine, whether their Names have not given Countenance to ſuch Notions,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31799:8"/> as are contrary to the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and the Faith Profeſſed by Proteſtants at Home and Abroad.</p>
                  <p>But, ſeeing what is thus ſurprizing flows from an <hi>Exceſs</hi> of <hi>Charity</hi> in them, to the Author of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Book, it's now hoped, that the bold ſtroke, which the <hi>Faithful Rebuke</hi> hath given to the Doctrine of <hi>Chriſts Satisfaction,</hi> will awaken the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Brethren to declare their Orthodoxy by their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying againſt what doth, in it, deviate from the Truth.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That the Controverſie is, in good earneſt, between the <hi>Congregational,</hi> and the Body of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Brethren on the one Part; and a <hi>few,</hi> who are with Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> on the other. The Reaſons which move me to Judge thus are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. The generality of the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> Brethren in this City, do ſtill firmly adhere unto the <hi>Aſſemblies Confeſſion, Larger</hi> and <hi>Shorter Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm;</hi> from which, in the Controverted Points, ſome apprehend Mr. <hi>W's<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> tho' he hath ſubſcribed them, doth diſſent and cannot chooſe, whilſt they have ſo many powerful Arguments for that Apprehenſion. Beſides, if there had not been a real Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and them, how could Mr. <hi>J. W.</hi> and his Friends boaſt of a Brother's coming over unto them in the Point of <hi>Juſtification?</hi> 2. No one hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten much in the praiſe of Mr. <hi>Ws</hi> his Notions, but Mr. <hi>Toland;</hi> whoſe Opinions are well known both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> and this Brother, whom I am ſorry to ſee Liſted in defence of the ſame Cauſe. What the Reverend Mr. <hi>Lorimer</hi> hath written, as it is after another manner than what my <hi>Rebuker</hi> hath done; ſo the moſt in him in theſe Matters is his miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Charity</hi> to Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> For he is a Man, that neither thinks the Phraſes of <hi>Chriſts ſuſtaining the Perſon of Sinners,</hi> and of a <hi>Commutation of Perſons between Chriſt, and us,</hi> to be either <hi>New</hi> or of a <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſound.</hi> Nor doth he deny, that our Lord Jeſus
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31799:9"/> did, as <hi>our ſurety,</hi> come under the <hi>Bond</hi> and <hi>Curſe</hi> of the <hi>Moral Law.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. As for the Doctrine of Juſtification, Mr. <hi>Ws,</hi> if he will be true to his own avowed Principles, muſt come over to Mr. <hi>Humphrey,</hi> in the <hi>denial</hi> of the <hi>imputed Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, in any other ſenſe, <hi>than in its Effects.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis true, Mr: <hi>Ws</hi> doth grant, that Chriſt by his Righteouſneſs, did not only purchaſe a <hi>Conditional Grant,</hi> of thoſe Effects, which he had merited by his Righteouſneſs; But, beſides <hi>theſe Effects made ours,</hi> the <hi>very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to</hi> true Believers. <hi>Goſpel Truth Stated,</hi> p. 39. However, if we compare this paſſage with what is more lately and fully explain'd in his <hi>Man made Righteous,</hi> p. 77, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you will ſoon unravel the whole Myſtery, and ſee, that whilſt he is labouring to hide himſelf, for a while, in a Cloud of Words, be means nothing at all by this Grant. For he is moſt explicite in affirming, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, as it was the Performance of the Conditions of our Salvation, is <hi>mediately</hi> imputed to the Believer. Chriſts very Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the Conditions is (ſaith he) <hi>Imputed mediately</hi> in this <hi>manner.</hi> If one give me my Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, which he voluntarily purchaſed for me at a dear rate, he <hi>mediately</hi> gives me what he paid for my Ranſom, tho' <hi>immediately</hi> I receive my Liberty and a Right thereto.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now what is this more than an <hi>imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs in the Effects?</hi> Becauſe the Effects of Chriſts death, ſuch as a <hi>Right to Pardon,</hi> &amp;c. is given to the True Believer, therefore it may be ſaid, that Chriſts Righteouſneſs, the procuring Cauſe, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto him. As the money, which one gives for anothers Liberty, may be ſaid to be given to that other to whom Liberty is given, which is only in the effects of that Money; ſo Chriſts Righteouſneſs is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31799:9"/> imputed, in that the effects of it are given unto us: that is to ſay, Chriſts Righteouſneſs is imputed to us <hi>mediately;</hi> It is imputed to us <hi>mediante effectu,</hi> or in its effects. If he can make any thing more of it, let him.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, ſo long as he, againſt the Common Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Proteſtants, denies a <hi>Commutation,</hi> or <hi>Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us;</hi> or, <hi>that Chriſt ſuſtained the Perſon of ſinners;</hi> or, <hi>as our Surety came under the Bond and Obligations of the violated Law of works,</hi> to anſwer thoſe Obligations for us: it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible there ſhould be, on his Principles, any other imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs, but what is in <hi>its effects,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Humphrey,</hi> clearly underſtanding, does honeſtly Aſſert, and that he muſt do the ſame, or relinquiſh his Principles may be more diſtinctly proved at any time, that he will, tho' let him be but ſincere and confeſs it, I ſhall be moſt willing, with my Reverend Brethren, to conſider how far we are to extend our <hi>Communion,</hi> or Charity towards ſuch, wherein he will find me Charitable enough.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The Breach being on this account begun, it is now widened by a Rejecting the Aſſertion of a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a <hi>Commutation</hi> of Perſons between Chriſt and us, for the due explaining and defending the Doctrine of Chriſts ſatisfaction, and our Juſtification; together with a Laying by the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of the <hi>Phraſes of Chriſts ſuſtaining the Perſon of Sinners, of a Change of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons between Chriſt and us; of Chriſts being our <hi>Surety,</hi> to anſwer for us the Obligations of the Violated Law of Works;</hi> and the like. And made more <hi>dangerous,</hi> ſince theſe <hi>Phraſes</hi> have been ſo very much Ridiculed by this Brother.</p>
                  <p>But there being ſo much <hi>wonder</hi> made at an inſiſting on the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of theſe <hi>Phraſes,</hi> I will, for the ſake of thoſe Brethren, who, either by diſuſe have forgotten; or, by reaſon of a too early and conſtant Application unto
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31799:10"/> practical Preaching, never throughly underſtood this neceſſary Doctrine of Chriſts Satisfaction; I will, I ſay, ſhow how <hi>uſeful</hi> theſe Phraſes are to <hi>explain</hi> this glorious and bleſſed Truth.</p>
                  <p>There are, in the Holy Scriptures, ſeveral Texts which diſcover and prove the Doctrine of Chriſts Satisfaction.</p>
                  <p>About the Genuine Senſe of theſe Texts, the chief Controverſie between the Reformed on the one hand, and the <hi>Arminian,</hi> and <hi>Socinian,</hi> on the other, doth Lye.</p>
                  <p>The Controverted Texts are ſuch as ſpeak of Chriſts <hi>dying for our ſins,</hi> and <hi>for us;</hi> of his being <hi>our Surety,</hi> and a <hi>Sacrifice for us;</hi> and the like, that relate to theſe Matters.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>different</hi> Senſes, which the Orthdox, and their <hi>Adverſaries</hi> have of theſe Texts, I will diſtinctly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When it's ſaid in Scripture, that Chriſt was <hi>wounded</hi> and <hi>bruiſed</hi> for our <hi>Tranſgreſſions; ſuffered</hi> and <hi>dyed for our Sins. Socinus</hi> and his Followers affirm, that the Expreſſion <hi>[for our ſins]</hi> ſignifies only a <hi>Final Cauſe,</hi> as if no more was meant than that <hi>Chriſt dyed for our good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Orthodox expreſly Aſſerts, that <hi>[For our ſins]</hi> in theſe Texts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> imports an <hi>impulſive meritorious Cauſe;</hi> and <hi>Grotius</hi> proves againſt <hi>Socinus,</hi> that theſe words, <hi>Chriſt ſuffered for our ſins,</hi> cannot be underſtood of a <hi>Final,</hi> but of <hi>Meritorious Cauſe.</hi> And, if our <hi>ſins</hi> be the <hi>Meritorious Cauſe</hi> of Chriſts Sufferings, it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily follows, that Chriſts ſufferings were a <hi>Proper Puniſhment</hi> for them, and muſt be ſatisfactory to Gods Juſtice, which <hi>Grotius,</hi> and the Right Reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> have unanſwerably Proved.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. When, in Scripture it is affirmed, that <hi>Chriſt ſuffered, and dyed <hi>For us,</hi>
                     </hi> the <hi>Socinians,</hi> who Labour to reduce all to his ſuffering for <hi>our good only,</hi> are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31799:10"/> poſitive, that the ſignification of the <hi>Propoſition [For]</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, that Chriſt dyed <hi>noſtro bono, <hi>for our good.</hi>
                     </hi> He ſuffered <hi>for our ſins,</hi> that is, ſay they, he ſuffered for our good; He dyed <hi>for us,</hi> that is, ſay they, he <hi>dyed</hi> only <hi>for our good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>On the contrary, the Orthodox aver, that the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>For,</hi> when it's ſaid, Chriſt dyed <hi>for us,</hi> ſignifies a <hi>Commutation,</hi> or <hi>Change of perſons between Chriſt and us;</hi> which is aptly expreſſed by that other Phraſe, <hi>[in our Place and Stead]</hi> that is, Chriſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered not only for our good; but, that God might be glorified in our Redemption, Chriſt ſuffered in our <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Stead;</hi> Chriſt in his ſufferings, did <hi>ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere vicem, ſeu Perſunam noſtram.</hi> He was put into our <hi>Place, State</hi> and Condition, that having the Guilt of our ſins laid upon him, he might, according to the <hi>Rule of Juſtice,</hi> ſuffer a Proper Puniſhment for our ſins, and ſo make Satisfaction to Gods Juſtice for us.</p>
                  <p>When it's ſaid, Chriſt came into our <hi>Place, State</hi> and <hi>Condition,</hi> the meaning is, he came under the <hi>Bonds</hi> and <hi>Obligations</hi> of the violated Law of Works, lay under the Guilt and Puniſhment of ſin on our behalfs, that we, by laying hold on Chriſt by Faith, might be delivered.</p>
                  <p>The Phraſes then of a <hi>Change of Perſons between Chriſt, and us, of Chriſts taking on him the Perſon of Sinners, ſuffering in their Perſon, Rooms</hi> and <hi>Stead,</hi> are moſt apt to convey unto our <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings</hi> the true, the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and <hi>Genuine</hi> Senſe of theſe Texts, <hi>Christ dyed for <hi>our ſins,</hi> and for us,</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi>Socinian Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation,</hi> that is to bring all to Chriſts <hi>ſuffering</hi> for <hi>our good only;</hi> which they do, that they may the better ſubvert the Doctrine of a <hi>Real, Proper and full Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faction</hi> to <hi>Gods Justice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Term <hi>Surety,</hi> when ſpoken of Chriſt in Scripture, relates to us as we are <hi>Sinners,</hi> endebted
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31799:11"/> to the <hi>Law,</hi> and Juſtice of God, and imports a <hi>Change of Perſon between Chriſt, and us; Chriſts ſustaining our Perſon, coming into the Bond,</hi> we had forfeited, and <hi>in our Place and Stead, anſwering for us the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Violated Law of Works.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Chriſts being made <hi>a Sacrifice for us,</hi> doth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſame, for that Chriſt might be a <hi>Proper Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> for us; 'twas neceſſary that he ſhould be <hi>ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted into our Place and Stead,</hi> as the Biſhop of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester,</hi> as well as <hi>Grotius,</hi> have fully proved.</p>
                  <p>'Tis true, <hi>Epiſcopius</hi> and his Followers, pretend a Zeal for Chriſts being a <hi>Proper Expiatory Sacrifice,</hi> but then they declare that <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when ſacrificed for us, did not ſuffer a <hi>Proper Puniſhment</hi> for our ſins: But the <hi>Orthodox</hi> have cleared it, beyond all doubt, that Chriſt, as our Sacrifice was ſubſtituted into our <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Stead;</hi> that this <hi>Subſtitution</hi> cannot be without a <hi>Commutation</hi> of <hi>Perſons between him and us;</hi> that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Chriſts ſufferings, when he was ſacrificed for us, became a <hi>Proper Puniſhment</hi> for our ſins.</p>
                  <p>The Uſe then of theſe Phraſes <hi>[of a Commutation of Perſons between Chriſt, and us; of Chriſts ſuſtaining the Perſon of Sinners; of his ſuffering in our Place, Stead and Perſon; of his coming under the Bonds and Obligations of the Violated Law of Works; of his anſwering for us theſe Obligations,]</hi> are uſed by the Orthodox, as moſt apt to explain the Doctrine of Chriſts <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and diſtinguiſh it from the <hi>Socinian</hi> Hereſie.</p>
                  <p>They are the <hi>Phraſes</hi> pitched upon by the Godly Learned, to deliver unto us the ſound meaning of thoſe Scriptures, which ſpeaks of Chriſts <hi>ſuffering for our ſins; dying for us;</hi> being our <hi>Surety,</hi> and made a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for us.</p>
                  <p>But, if you will Reduce all to Chriſt's ſufferings in our <hi>Place,</hi> and <hi>Stead;</hi> and by <hi>theſe Expreſſions,</hi> avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly Declare, that <hi>it's Impoſſible for <hi>that Phraſe,</hi>
                     </hi> to ſignifie any more than <hi>for our good,</hi> and to turn <hi>noſtro
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31799:11"/> Loco,</hi> into <hi>noſtro bono,</hi> you give up the Doctrine of Chriſt's Satisfaction, and Sacrifize the Truth to the Luſts of its greateſt Enemies, for Chriſt's ſuffering <hi>only for our Good,</hi> reſpects only <hi>Man;</hi> and the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of <hi>Chriſt's making Satisfaction</hi> doth primarily reſpect <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs of</hi> his <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> which is not included in his ſuffering only <hi>noſtro bono;</hi> for which reaſon if Chriſt ſuffered <hi>only for our Good,</hi> He did not by his ſufferings make ſatisfaction unto <hi>God's Juſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe things, (which will be diſtinctly handled in my vindicating the <hi>Report</hi> from <hi>Falſhood</hi> in <hi>Doctrinals</hi>) do ſufficiently ſhew how neceſſary the Uſe of theſe <hi>Phraſes</hi> is, how Dangerous to recede from them, and how liable to ſuſpicion ſuch Brethren are, who do not only Oppoſe, but with Scorn and Contempt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject them.</p>
                  <p>It now remains, that I proceed to Examine <hi>what it is,</hi> that my Reverend Brother chargeth the <hi>Report</hi> with, in matters <hi>Doctrinal.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II. Of <hi>Doctrinala.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the <hi>Report</hi> we may obſerve an Intimation given of ſundry Points, which were in the <hi>Firſt Paper,</hi> but left out of the Third, and the leaving 'em out of the <hi>Third</hi> inſiſted on as what encreaſed the <hi>Offence</hi> of our <hi>Grieved Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>An</hi> Expunging <hi>that <hi>Paragraph</hi> which in the <hi>Firſt Paper,</hi> did Aſſert the Neceſſity of a <hi>Change of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, between Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Vs,</hi> in order to a due Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining, and Defending the Doctrine of Chriſt's Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and our Juſtification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>A Rejecting the Phraſe of</hi> Chriſt's ſuſtaining the Perſon <hi>of</hi> Sinners.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:31799:12"/>III. <hi>The Denying a</hi> Change <hi>of</hi> Perſons <hi>between</hi> Chriſt <hi>and</hi> Us.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>An Impoſing a</hi> Socinian <hi>ſenſe on the Phraſe of</hi> Chriſt's ſuffering in our Place <hi>and</hi> Stead.</p>
               <p n="5">V. <hi>A Turning</hi> Chriſt's Undertaking <hi>to Anſwer <hi>for us</hi> the <hi>Obligations</hi> of the Violated Law of Works,</hi> into <hi>Chriſt's Anſwering for our Violation of the Law of Works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. <hi>Why ſo many Orthodox <hi>Terms</hi> and <hi>Phraſes,</hi>
                  </hi> which <hi>were in the</hi> Firſt <hi>Paper are left out of the</hi> Third?</p>
               <p>And ſeeing it is boldly ſaid, That our Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie with them is not about what is owned, or ſo much as Countenanced in any Publick Confeſſions, I will under this Head of <hi>Doctrinals</hi> make Anſwer to the Enquiry.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. <hi>In what</hi> Confeſſions <hi>are</hi> the Terms, <hi>or</hi> Phraſes <hi>ſo much Contended for to be found?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before I diſcourſe on any of theſe points, 'twill be requiſite, that I ſet before you the Reaſon, which my Brother gives for their rejecting thoſe <hi>Paſſages, Terms</hi> and <hi>Phraſes,</hi> that were in the <hi>Firſt Paper.</hi> You ſhall have it in his own words.</p>
               <div type="rebuke">
                  <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Brethren did Unanimouſly agree to <hi>Grant</hi> as much as the <hi>ſound Senſe <hi>could Bear;</hi>
                        </hi> and modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to wave, and paſs by <hi>the other,</hi> which was <hi>liable</hi> to be Interpreted to a <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>ſound</hi> of <hi>Malignity</hi> to the <hi>whole</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> p. 30.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p>This paſſage of my Reverend Brother doth make it manifeſt, That the <hi>Paragraphs, Terms,</hi> and <hi>Phraſes,</hi> which were in the <hi>firſt</hi> Paper, and were waved and paſſed by in the Compoſure of the Third, are look'd upon by my Brother, and as he will have us believe,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31799:12"/> by all the Miniſters, who meet at <hi>Little St. Helens,</hi> and had a Head, a Hand, and a Heart in Compoſing the <hi>Third,</hi> could not bear a ſound ſenſe, but were liable to be Interpreted to a <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and <hi>ſound</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity</hi> to the <hi>whole</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> That is to ſay, The Phraſe of <hi>Chriſt's putting on the Perſon of Sinners;</hi> of his <hi>Anſwering for us the <hi>Obligations</hi>
                     </hi> of <hi>the Violated Law of Works,</hi> the <hi>Term, Surety,</hi> and the Aſſertion of the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of a Commutation, or <hi>Change of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> between <hi>Chriſt and Us,</hi> in order to <hi>Explain,</hi> and <hi>Defend</hi> Chriſt's Satisfaction, cannot in their Opinion bear a <hi>ſound ſenſe,</hi> but are liable to be Interpreted to a <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and <hi>ſound</hi> of <hi>Malignity</hi> to the <hi>whole</hi> of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>This is the ſenſe of my Reverend Brother, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which I will only ſay, that tho' I think my ſelf bound in <hi>Civility</hi> to believe what he ſaith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yet I dare not be ſo ſevere as to conclude, that all my <hi>Presbyterian Brethren</hi> who meet at <hi>Little St. Hellens</hi> are in theſe Points of his Mind. However I deſire my Reader to have Recourſe unto this Paſſage, when He conſiders what I offer under the <hi>Particulars</hi> Propoſed to be Examined. To the Firſt,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I. An Expunging that <hi>Paragraph, which in the</hi> firſt Paper <hi>did Aſſert the</hi> Neceſſity <hi>of</hi> a Change <hi>of</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons between Chriſt and Us, <hi>in order to a Due</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining <hi>and</hi> Defending <hi>the Doctrine of Chriſt's Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction,</hi> and our <hi>Juſtification.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>That a <hi>Change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us</hi> is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>to a due</hi> Explication <hi>and</hi> Defence of Chriſt's S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>tion <hi>and our</hi> Juſtification, is ſo very manifeſt, that were nor but ſurprize us, to Hear from a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who pre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> to Believe both, that it is not ſo.</p>
                  <p>What more Evident, than that if the Lord Chriſt hath not made Satisfaction to God's Juſtice <hi>for us,</hi>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:31799:13"/> there is nothing Left for the Relief of a <hi>Convinced</hi> Sinner, or for Healing a Wounded Spirit: for there is no Room, no Place for our being Juſtified in the Court of Heaven. If no Satisfaction, there can be no Juſtifying Righteouſneſs found for us, to appear before the Bar of God in. 'Tis Chriſt's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs alone, that can paſs the Examen in the Great Day of the Lord; and without <hi>that</hi> no Soul Living can be Juſtified.</p>
                  <p>But, if Chriſt Endured not <hi>the Puniſhment due</hi> to us for ſin, by Anſwering for us the <hi>Obligations</hi> of the Violated Law of Works, there can be no <hi>Proper Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi> made to the Juſtice of God for Us, for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction taken ſtrictly and in a proper ſenſe is <hi>ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Debiti,</hi> a Suffering the <hi>Puniſhment due for our Sin.</hi> That the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of our Sins could not be born by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, unleſs there were a <hi>Commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Perſons</hi> between <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Us,</hi> whereby the Lord Jeſus came under the Bonds and Engagements of the Violated Law of Works, that we might be Delivered, is as Evident.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things are ſo plain, that whoever throughly Underſtands this Doctrine, whether the <hi>Orthodox, Socinian,</hi> or <hi>Arminian,</hi> they make no doubt of it, and therefore ſuch as oppoſe the Doctrine of a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Satisfaction,</hi> deny a Change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us, and thereby turn Chriſt's Sufferings from being <hi>Properly</hi> a Puniſhment to be only <hi>vicarious,</hi> that is, <hi>vice poenae,</hi> Grievous, and Painful Afflictions inſtead of a proper Puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>Whether what I here Aſſert be not the Truth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the Holy Scriptures, I appeal to all ſound Divines, whether in the Church of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> or the Reformed abroad.</p>
                  <p>However, if we may Believe my Brother, the <hi>Aſſertion</hi> of the <hi>Neceſſity of a Commutation of Perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Us,</hi> in order to a due Explaining
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31799:13"/> and Defending Chriſt's Satisfaction and our Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>cannot bear</hi> a <hi>Sound ſenſe,</hi> but is <hi>liable to be Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted</hi> to a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of <hi>Malignity</hi> to the <hi>whole of the Goſpel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If this be not matter of Juſt Grief to the Godly Learned amongſt us, what can be ſo? Here is an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing to the uttermoſt Contempt a Truth of very great Importance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>II.</hi> The Phraſe of <hi>Chriſt's ſuſtaining the Perſon</hi> of Sinners is Rejected.</head>
                  <p>That they Reject this Phraſe, of <hi>Chriſt's Suſtaining the Perſon of Sinners,</hi> is ſo manifeſt, that my Brother doth not only prove the Charge to be true, but Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth himſelf againſt the <hi>Vſe</hi> of this Phraſe, with Vehemence and Heat. Take his own words.</p>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">For <hi>Chriſt</hi> to take upon <hi>him the Perſon of ſinners,</hi> as the phraſe is <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Uncouth,</hi> ſo it is to me <hi>Unintelligible,</hi> till they who have invented it ſhall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret it, <hi>p.</hi> 10. — This <hi>New</hi> phraſe, <hi>Chriſt took upon him the Perſon of ſinners,</hi> is a phraſe to <hi>Puzzle</hi> and <hi>Confound</hi> mens Underſtandings, <hi>p.</hi> 11. — Now ſucceeds the <hi>Coining Age,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> have <hi>ſtamped,</hi> and <hi>Counterfeited</hi> ſome <hi>New <hi>Phraſes, Terms,</hi>
                           </hi> and <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Chriſt's taking on him the Perſon of Sinners.</hi> p. 32.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. This is no new <hi>Phraſe,</hi> but Uſed and Contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for by the Orthodox againſt the <hi>Arminians</hi> many years ago. If you conſult the Learned <hi>Peter du Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> his <hi>Anatomy</hi> of <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> you'l find, that near fourſcore years ago, he charged the <hi>Arminians</hi> with denying, that Chriſt <hi>ſuſtained the Perſon of the Elect when on the Croſs.</hi> cap. 27. § 6. And, in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>chapter,</hi> § 30. he thus expreſſeth himſelf,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31799:14"/> 
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">When theſe <hi>Sectaries</hi> deny, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> did, when on the Croſs, <hi>ſuſtain the Perſon of the Elect,</hi> they do plainly contradict what is Affirm'd by Chriſt in <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.11. The good Shepherd lays down his Life <hi>for</hi> his Sheep, and thoſe other places in <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.13. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Joannes Arnoldus Corvinus</hi> in his <hi>Cenſure</hi> on the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy,</hi> freely declares in the Name of the <hi>Arminians</hi> they do deny, <hi>that Chriſt ſuſtained the Perſon of the Elect,</hi> when <hi>on the Croſs.</hi> cap. 27. §. 6.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Learned <hi>Du Moulin</hi> was not ſingular in his Opinion, for what he aſſerted on this Occaſion was the Faith of the Reformed, which I will evince, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning with the mention of ſome Learned Divines amongſt our ſelves in this Iſland. And it's worthy Remark, that the Reverend Dr. <hi>Bates,</hi> who is known to be no <hi>Antinomian,</hi> doth affirm in his <hi>Harmony,</hi> p 240. <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That, as in <hi>Civil</hi> caſes, where one becomes <hi>Surety</hi> for another, He is <hi>Obliged</hi> to pay the <hi>Debt,</hi> for in the <hi>Eſtimate</hi> of the Law, they are but <hi>One Perſon, Heb.</hi> 7.22. So the Lord Jeſus entring into this Relation, <hi>ſuſtained the Perſon of ſinners,</hi> and became <hi>Iudicially <hi>One with them;</hi>
                           </hi> and according to the Order of Juſtice was liable to their Puniſhment.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>What the Doctor hath here obſerved, gives Light touching the Genuine Import of the Phraſe of <hi>Chriſt's taking on him the Perſon of ſinners,</hi> as it is included in Chriſt's <hi>Sure<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iſhip.</hi> For, when it's ſaid, Chriſt is our <hi>Surety,</hi> if it be meant of his Paying our Debts to the Law, and Juſtice of God, as it is by the Orthodox, the Term <hi>Surety</hi> muſt neceſſarily imply Chriſt's <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>r Perſon,</hi> it being the part of a Surety to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ake on him the Perſon of a Debtor, to Repreſent him, and ſtand <hi>ſo</hi> in his <hi>Place</hi> and ſtead as to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame Bond, and under the ſame Obligations the Debtor ſtood.</p>
                     <p>Thus much is the Import of the Term, <hi>Surety,</hi>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:31799:14"/> and ſignification of <hi>Chriſt's ſuſtaining</hi> the <hi>Perſon of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> that is, The Lord Chriſt came into the Bond, we Forfeited, lies under the Obligations of the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Law of Works, and in our <hi>Perſon,</hi> Repreſenting Us, He Paid the Debt we Contracted, by ſuffering the Puniſhment we Deſerved.</p>
                     <p>Tho' Chriſt had not any <hi>Demerit</hi> of his own upon him, yet as the learned Biſhop <hi>Reynolds</hi> has it, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">He had the Guilt of Sin ſo far upon him, as it Notes the Obligation and Subjection unto Puniſhment, as he was <hi>our Surety,</hi> and ſo in <hi>ſenſu forenſi,</hi> in the <hi>ſight of Gods Court of Juſtice, One with us,</hi> who had deſerved the Puniſhment imputed to him, on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. <hi>p.</hi> 439.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chriſt, as our <hi>Surety,</hi> ſuffered in our <hi>Perſon, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting us,</hi> and as the great <hi>Placeus,</hi> in the <hi>Salmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Theſes de Juſtificat.</hi> ſect. 29. Obſerves, what <hi>Chriſt</hi> as our <hi>Surety,</hi> in our Perſon or Name ſuffered may be very truly imputed unto us. <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Who can, ſaith he, deny the Imputation of that Satisfaction unto us, which was made by our <hi>Surety,</hi> in our Name?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the ſame purpoſe the learned Mr. <hi>Rutherford,</hi> who was not only an Enemy to <hi>Antinomian</hi> Hereſies, but One, who did Unanſwerably Confute them, this worthy Perſon, ſo juſtly celebrated, not only throughout <hi>Scotland,</hi> but by the learned in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and abroad for his Excelling Learning, Piety, and ſound Judgment, makes it his Province to prove againſt the <hi>Arminians,</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> that Chriſt in ſuffering <hi>ſuſtained the Perſon of the</hi> Elect, and that the Orthodox ſignification of the phraſe in our <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Stead</hi> is, in our <hi>Name</hi> or <hi>Perſon;</hi> of which more hereafter in due ſeaſon, but in this place I will only Remark, how he preſſeth, that Chriſt's <hi>Suretiſhip</hi> can import no leſs than his <hi>ſuſtaining the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of them for whom he ſuffered. His words are,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31799:15"/> 
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">He, who being under the Law, paid that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Debt of Satisfaction, which the Elect <hi>in</hi> their <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons ſhould have paid, He <hi>ſuſtained the Perſon of the Elect,</hi> in his ſuffering. But Chriſt being made <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the Law, paid that Law-Debt of Satisfaction which the Elect in their Perſons ſhould have paid, <hi>Ergo.</hi> The Propoſition is out of doubt.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> He, who ſaith expreſly, that what is here affirmed by my Rebuking Brother to be <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nintelligible,</hi> fit to <hi>Puzzle</hi> and <hi>Confound</hi> mens Underſtandings, is ſo <hi>eaſie</hi> to be <hi>Underſtood,</hi> that there is no place left for doubt, for, as He adds in the next page. <hi rend="margSglQuotes">
                           <hi>None who Dyeth as a Surety,</hi> or <hi>pays as a Surety,</hi> but He <hi>bears the Perſon of ſuch as He Pays</hi> for.</hi> Theſe things are Aſſerted by him, in his <hi>Treatiſe of the Covenant of Grace. Part</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 252, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>I will add one Teſtimony more, and that is what I find in the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> of Mr. <hi>Nowell,</hi> received with the greateſt Honour, above theſe Hundred years, in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> where you have theſe words; <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Chriſt <hi>for us</hi> ſuffered, and went through <hi>Horrible Fears,</hi> and moſt <hi>bitter Griefs</hi> of mind, to <hi>ſatisfie</hi> God's Juſt <hi>Judgment</hi> in all things, and to Appeaſe his Wrath. For to <hi>Sinners, whoſe <hi>Perſon Chriſt did here Bear,</hi>
                           </hi> not only the Sorrows and Pains of preſent Death are due, but alſo Death to Come and Everlaſting.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But theſe Authorities being only in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, can only prove, that the Phraſe of <hi>Chriſt's bearing the Perſon of ſinners</hi> is <hi>not ſo New,</hi> as my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affirms, I will go on to enquire, <hi>whether this <hi>odd</hi> Phraſe</hi> (to uſe my Brothers own words) <hi>durſt ſhew its Face</hi> in <hi>Latin?</hi> For my Brother ſaith it durſt not.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Seeing the great Struggle hath been, not about the ſatisfaction of Chriſt, as the Report Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents it, but about ſome <hi>odd Phraſes,</hi> and Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31799:15"/> in which 'tis cloathed, eſpecially theſe of <hi>Chriſt's ſuffering in the Perſon of ſinners</hi> — whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if this be a ſound, and ſafe way of Expreſſing that great Doctrine, it will not endure to ſhew its <hi>Naked Face</hi> in ſome other of the <hi>learned Languages?</hi> And if you pleaſe make an Experiment, how well it will look in <hi>Latin?</hi> — Now what is <hi>ſuſtinere Perſonam alterius?</hi> — Whatever Excuſe they can have for the <hi>Engliſh phraſe,</hi> I know not, it's pretty hard to Damn all the World for an <hi>Angliciſm,</hi> p. 53.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. What my good Brother means by theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on the phraſes of <hi>Chriſt's ſuſtaining</hi> and <hi>ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in the Perſon of ſinners, leſs than that, in his Opinion, they were never uſed by any Author, who wrote in <hi>Latin,</hi> and that this learned Language wants apt words to expreſs them by, I cannot comprehend. But,</p>
                     <p n="2">2. This being the manifeſt ſenſe of my reverend Brother, I ſhall be neceſſitated to Try his <hi>Skill,</hi> or <hi>Integrity,</hi> or <hi>both;</hi> For, nothing more Obvious than that they, who have wrote in <hi>Latin,</hi> on this Subject, have Uſed theſe phraſes, and that <hi>Cicero</hi> himſelf hath found out apt words to render the <hi>Bearing the Perſon of another</hi> into good <hi>Latin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. The <hi>Authorities</hi> I deſign to preſs ſhall be of ſuch Great Men, as are moſt diſtant in their Judgment, from <hi>Antinomian</hi> Notions, and paſſing by the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans,</hi> viz. <hi>Calovius, Dorſheus, Scherzerus, Quenſtedius,</hi> and many other ſuch, who are in this <hi>Article</hi> very ſound, I will Confine my ſelf to the <hi>Reformed. Eſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> in his Defence of <hi>Grotius de Satisfactione,</hi> lib. 1. ſect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. cap. 5. part 1. p. 128. hath it thus, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That <hi>Chriſtus <hi>Perſonam noſtram</hi> ſuſtinens, &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining our Perſon,</hi> there was a <hi>Commutation</hi> of his Death for ours, that we might attain unto Life.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:31799:16"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hoornbeck,</hi> who underſtood this Controverſie as well as any one, lays it down as a <hi>General Rule,</hi> by which we are to guide our ſelves, in the management of it, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That <hi>Chriſtus eorum Perſonam ſuſtinuit,</hi> Chriſt <hi>ſuſtained the Perſon</hi> of them, for whom he made Satisfaction by his death, was in their <hi>Place,</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and took on him to bear their Guilt on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>Miſcel. Sac. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 396.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Nor can there be any thing more Remarkable upon this Occaſion than what <hi>Rivet</hi> Replies to <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s Anſwer to the Common Argument of Proteſtants, for our being Juſtified by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt; in which place, after he had urged a great deal in detecting <hi>Bellarmine's Sophiſtications,</hi> he adds, That Chriſt is to be conſidered, firſt as in himſelf, and then with reſpect <hi>to us,</hi> whoſe <hi>Perſon he ſuſtains;</hi> that Chriſt conſidered in himſelf is <hi>Just, Holy,</hi> without <hi>Spot,</hi> and ſeparate from Sinners, but in reſpect <hi>to us,</hi> he is ſaid to be <hi>made ſin:</hi> He is our Surety, and ſo a <hi>Debtor. Rivet. Cathol. Orthod. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Tract.</hi> 8. <hi>Querſt.</hi> 2. <hi>num.</hi> 35.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cloppenburch</hi> is as poſitive; for, in his Enarrat. in 53. <hi>Iſa.</hi> ſaith he, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">When it's affirmed, that our ſins are imputed unto Chriſt, we muſt underſtand it, that he is truly made ſin, tho' not in <hi>himſelf,</hi> yet <hi>in our Perſon</hi> he may be reckoned and eſteemed as the Debtor: for, by reaſon of his <hi>Suretiſhip,</hi> he is <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially</hi> eſteemed One Perſon with us. pag. 79.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Witſius,</hi> to whom Dr. <hi>Chauncey</hi> and Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> have appealed in this Controverſie, declares it as his Judgment, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That Chriſt was ſo ſubſtituted for the Elect, and ſo <hi>ſuſtained their Perſon,</hi> that there is a Permutation or Change of Perſons. Animad. Iren. Cap.</hi> 2. § 8. and elſewhere, <hi>Christ did not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertake, or make Satisfaction for any, but them, whoſe Perſon he ſustained.</hi> De Oecon. Faed. lib. 2. cap. 9. § 1.</p>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:31799:16"/>
                     <p>To theſe I will only add <hi>Voetius,</hi> who having Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That Chriſt, as our <hi>Surety, ſustained the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all them that ſhall be ſaved by him,</hi> and ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled all that Righteouſneſs of the Law, which they could not do, tells us, 'That the <hi>Remonstrants,</hi> who are juſtly ſuſpected for Leaning too much towards the <hi>Socinians,</hi> do hold no other <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and <hi>Merit,</hi> than ſuch an appeaſing God, the offended Party, as that, by which he is ſo far ſatisfied as to be willing to Receive Offenders into favour; and by which Chriſt has acquir'd for the Father, a Right of Entring into a New Covenant with Men, from whence (adds he) it follows, That Chriſt was not truly <hi>our Surety,</hi> that <hi>he ſuffered not</hi> in our <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Stead;</hi> that he did not in a proper Senſe Purchaſe and Procure any thing for us; nor did he, when on the Croſs, <hi>ſustain the Perſon of the Elect. Select. Diſput. Theol. p.</hi> 2. de Merito Chriſti; pag. 133, 134. <hi>Calvin</hi> alſo uſes it on <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe few Inſtances are enough to convince an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byaſſed Mind, that the Phraſe of <hi>Christs ſuſtaining our Perſon,</hi> hath been commonly uſed, both by the Reformed at Home and Abroad; that it hath been inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted on as neceſſary to ſecure the Doctrine of Chriſts Satisfaction from <hi>Arminian</hi> and <hi>Socinian</hi> Incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that it has dared to ſhow its <hi>Face</hi> in <hi>Latin.</hi> But my Brother's further Enquiry is, <hi>Doth it appear in good Latin?</hi> To which I anſwer.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. This Phraſe, <hi>ſustinere Perſonam alterius,</hi> is <hi>Cicero</hi> all over, for (ſaith he <hi>de Orat.) Tres Perſonas unus ſustineo, meam, Adverſarij &amp; Judicis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Matter is ſo very plain, that how excuſable ſoever my Brothers Inſtructor may be in making ſuch Miſtakes, my Brother himſelf, who is ſo good a <hi>Latiniſt,</hi> diſcovering ſo much <hi>Unacquaintedneſs,</hi> not only <hi>with Divinity,</hi> but with that Learned Language, in which, if in any thing, excepting <hi>Wit,</hi> he muſt be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31799:17"/> eſteemed to excel, cannot be entirely excuſed. For what more evident, than that, if <hi>Cicero</hi> may be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded as a Competent Judge in this Caſe, <hi>ſuſtinere Perſonam alterius,</hi> is ſuch good <hi>Latin,</hi> that it need not be afraid to Look my Brother in the face. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,</p>
                     <p n="6">6. This Brother will have it, that the Phraſe of <hi>Chriſts Sustaining our Perſon,</hi> is <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nintelligible,</hi> fit to <hi>Puzzle</hi> and <hi>Confound Mens <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> uncapable of a ſound Senſe, and liable to be interpreted to a Senſe and Sound of Malignity to the whole of the Goſpel, as if all that have uſed it, ſuch as Dr. <hi>Bates, Rutherford, Calvin,</hi> and the Generation of the Orthodox had deſigned to confound the World by the Uſe of barbarous and pernicious Phraſes, and had been guilty of the unrighteous Charge, with which the <hi>Engliſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> have burdened them, when they Reproach them for amuſing Mankind with the <hi>Jargon</hi> of <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nintelligible Terms and Phraſes.</hi> And as if ſuch an Accuſation had been too mean, my Brother runs higher. For</p>
                     <p n="7">7. He expoſes the Phraſe of <hi>Chriſts ſuſtaining the Perſon of Sinners,</hi> to the greateſt Contempt and Scorn, as if it Repreſented the bleſſed Redeemer in the moſt glorious undertaking of falen Mans Recovery, to be <hi>Hiſtrionical.</hi> His Words are,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>We are told of Chriſts <hi>ſuſtaining the Perſon of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners:</hi> — What can this <hi>Expreſſion ſignifie,</hi> but that Chriſt wore the <hi>Mask,</hi> the <hi>Vizer,</hi> the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe</hi> of Sinners? That he was <hi>Perſonatus Hiſtrio?</hi> Like a S<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ge Player, that puts on the Perſon of a King, wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> indeed he is but ſome <hi>Sorry Fellow.</hi>— pag. 53.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. That the Phraſe of Chriſts <hi>ſuſtaining the Perſon of Sinners,</hi> ſhould be ſo vilely miſ-repreſented by any
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:31799:17"/> one of them, who meet at <hi>Little St. Hellens,</hi> is equal Matter of Aſtoniſhment and Humiliation. And to be Juſt unto Truth, I muſt turn unto the Reverend Brethren, who ordinarily Aſſemble at that Place for their Judgment in this caſe, whether the <hi>Phraſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſts ſuſtaining <hi>the Perſon of ſinners, can ſignifie nothing but his wearing the</hi> Mask,</hi> the <hi>Vizer,</hi> the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe <hi>of Sinners, as if he had been a ſorry Stage Player?</hi>
                        </hi> This is the Caſe that deſerves, yea, that calls for your determination; for my Brothers words are, <hi>What can theſe Expreſſions ſignifie, but that Chriſt wore the Mask,</hi> &amp;c. Sirs, the Eyes of a whole Nation are upon you, and the Eyes of the Reformed Churches Abroad, will be upon you, to ſee whether you will give Countenance to ſuch an Abuſe of Truth, and its Renowned Defenders. But to Return to my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Why, cannot this Phraſe ſignifie nothing elſe? If he had but gained a little ſmattering in the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> he would have ſeen that it could have born another meaning. There he might have Learned, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That there is a <hi>Moral Perſon</hi> diſtinct both from a <hi>Phyſical,</hi> and <hi>Ficta Perſona;</hi> That a Moral Perſon is one placed in the <hi>State</hi> and Office of them, whoſe <hi>Perſon he ſuſtains;</hi> That One ſingle Man being put into the different States and Conditions of many, puts on their Perſon; That a peculiar Species of Political Perſons may be called <hi>Repreſentative,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they repreſent the <hi>Perſons</hi> they bear; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Ambaſſadors, Vice-Roys, Syntdicks,</hi> and the like. And in the more inferior Station, the <hi>Tutor</hi> ſuſtains the <hi>Perſon of the Pupil,</hi> the <hi>Guardian</hi> of the <hi>Minor,</hi> and yet none of theſe are <hi>Stage-Players;</hi> for to a <hi>Repreſentative Perſon,</hi> ſomewhat more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs than meer <hi>Repreſentation,</hi> they are ſuch as do ſomewhat for the Advantage of them, whoſe <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> they ſuſtain; That theſe <hi>True Moral Perſons</hi> are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31799:18"/> diſtinct from them, who are but <hi>Fictae</hi> as <hi>Stage-Players</hi> are: That the <hi>Fictae Perſonae,</hi> or <hi>Stage Players,</hi> are but the <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrae,</hi> or Shadows of the True. That the Eſſence of theſe <hi>Fictae Perſonae,</hi> conſiſts only in Repreſentation of the <hi>Habit,</hi> the Geſture, and the like of another. And as <hi>Pufendorf</hi> further declares, <hi>Veras Perſonas morales, <hi>quas pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducit Impoſitio, haudquidquam ita eſt Libera, quin ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi</hi> Qualitates <hi>debeat</hi> praeſupponere, <hi>quae</hi> aptae <hi>ſint, ut</hi> ſolidus aliquis <hi>effectus in vitâ humanâ inde Eveniat. Et illas, qui circa Conſtituendas Perſonas negle xerint per vecordem Petulantiam mortalibus inſultare eſt Cenſendus. Pufend. de Jure Nat. &amp; Gent. Lib.</hi>
                           </hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Edit.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 15.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That this good Brother therefore, whilſt ſo Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with what is ſo much known to every body, who underſtands this Controverſie about <hi>Chriſts Satisfaction,</hi> and his <hi>Suretyſhip,</hi> ſhould ſo far forget himſelf as to write after the rate he hath done, may very well be a Caution to others to take heed, how they go beyond their laſt, or, how they ſuffer themſelves to be hurryed on a Controverſie before their Heats are over, and they have got time to deliberate, and digeſt what they write about. Had my Reverend Brother been more cool, had he got more time to conſider, and weigh well what he did, he could never have been thus impoſed upon to wound his own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation as he hath done, in the uſe he hath made of <hi>Milton: Milton,</hi> tho' he ſaith, <hi>Salmaſium riſum pene Legentibus <hi>Multiplici Barbariſmo</hi> concitaſſe,</hi> could not charge <hi>Salmaſius,</hi> with more Inſtances of Barbariſm, than my Brother is fallen into miſtakes in the uſe he makes of <hi>Milton.</hi> For,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Salmaſius</hi> Writes not of a <hi>Moral Repreſentative Perſon,</hi> but of the <hi>Natural Perſon</hi> of the King; there was, ſaith he, a Paricide Committed on the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the King, that is, on his Natural, his own proper Perſon.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:31799:18"/>2. When <hi>Milton</hi> Banters <hi>Salmaſius</hi> with a <hi>Pſeudo-Philip,</hi> he mentions not a word of a <hi>Moral Perſon</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>her; but ſpeaks only of a meer <hi>Ficta Perſona,</hi> as if <hi>Salmaſius,</hi> by <hi>Perſona,</hi> had meant a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> under the <hi>Vizer,</hi> or <hi>Mask</hi> of a King.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The Reaſon, why <hi>Milton</hi> was ſo ſevere upon <hi>Salmaſius,</hi> was not ſo much becauſe <hi>Salmaſius</hi> uſed the Word <hi>Perſona,</hi> as becauſe he miſlook the <hi>Abla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> for the <hi>Accuſative</hi> Caſe, and wrote <hi>in Perſona,</hi> when it ſhould have been <hi>in Perſonam Regis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But, tho' <hi>Salmaſius</hi> gave a full Anſwer to every thing, that <hi>Milton,</hi> on this occaſion, Played upon him for, Inſtancing in ſeveral <hi>Roman</hi> Writers, who have taken the word <hi>Perſona</hi> in a proper Senſe, and have uſed the <hi>Ablative Caſe,</hi> as he has done; yet, it not being to my preſent Purpoſe, I ſhall only deſire to know of my Brother. What Alliance <hi>Christs ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Perſon of Sinners has,</hi> either with the <hi>Natural Perſon</hi> of a King; or of any other Man; or with a meer <hi>Ficta Perſona?</hi> For both theſe are very diſtinct from a <hi>Moral,</hi> or <hi>Legal Perſon;</hi> and, it is in this <hi>Moral</hi> or <hi>Legal</hi> Senſe, that the word <hi>[Perſon]</hi> is taken, when it's affirm'd, that <hi>Chriſt ſuſtained the Perſon of Sinners,</hi> and it ſignifieth the ſame with Chriſts being their <hi>Publick Repreſentative.</hi> He was <hi>Publica Perſona mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis <hi>Repreſentativa.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>We will therefore, before we diſmiſs this <hi>Phraſe,</hi> conſult the Reverend Mr. <hi>Alſop,</hi> for I know my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath a great conceit of him; who, in his <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſozzo, p.</hi> 689. ſaith, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Repreſentative</hi> of all his <hi>Spiritual Seed;</hi> and in <hi>p.</hi> 693. All the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Seed</hi> and <hi>Poſterity</hi> of Chriſt, are by Vertue of a <hi>New</hi> Law-conſtitution, made Righteous by the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of their <hi>Spiritual Head,</hi> and <hi>Repreſentative:</hi> To whom I'le add what the Reverend Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> ſaith of it, which is, <hi>that Chriſt was to be our <hi>Repreſentative,</hi> and therefore ſuch a Conjunction between him, and us, muſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31799:19"/> be, that God might eſteem all his People to ſuffer in him;</hi> which is no more than what is affirmed in the Cloſe of the firſt <hi>Homily</hi> of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> when it's ſaid, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That Chriſt is now the Righteouſneſs of all them that truly do believe in him. He for them paid their Ranſom by his death; He, for them, fulfilled the Law in his Life: So that <hi>now in him, and by him, every True Chriſtian may be called a <hi>Fulfiller of the Law:</hi>
                           </hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But if Chriſt <hi>Repreſented Sinners</hi> in his Death, he muſt be found in their <hi>Quality,</hi> ſuffering <hi>as a Sinner;</hi> that is, as Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi> has it, in his <hi>Anti-Sozzo,</hi> p. 184. <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That Chriſts Soul was made an Offering for ſin, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10. Nay, <hi>he was made <hi>Sin</hi> for us, tho' he know no ſin, that we might be made the Righteouſneſs of God in him,</hi> 2 Cor. 21. And <hi>Appearing</hi> in <hi>this Quality; <hi>Death,</hi>
                           </hi> the Officer of Gods Violated Law, might <hi>Juſtly Arreſt</hi> him, and the Father be pleaſed to bruiſe him. For as elſewhere, the ſame Author, he was a <hi>Sinner,</hi> that is, by <hi>Imputation,</hi> pag. 574. Chriſt could no otherwiſe be a <hi>Sinner,</hi> but by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, nor we otherwiſe Righteous than by <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus, the Lord Chriſt Suffering and Obeying in the <hi>Perſon of Sinners,</hi> as their <hi>Publick Repreſentative,</hi> it is to all intents and purpoſes as effectual, as if they had done it themſelves <hi>Perſonae morales <hi>Repreſentativae,</hi> quae <hi>Perſonam ali<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>um Reſerant</hi>—hujus vice ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotia expediunt, eodom cum effectu, acſi ab <hi>illo</hi> ipſo eſſent Confectae.</hi> Puſend. ubi. ſup. II.</p>
                     <p>What hath been urged on this Head, makes it Apparent, that the Phraſe of <hi>Chriſts ſustaining the Perſon of Sinners,</hi> in his Death and Obedience, is very Intelligible and Aptly uſed by the Orthodox; ſuch as Dr. <hi>Bates, Rutherford, Scherzerus, Quenstedius, Nowel, Eſſenius, Voetius, Rivetus,</hi> and many others; ay, the very ſame thing is uſed by the Reverend Mr. <hi>Alſop,</hi>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:31799:19"/> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> inſiſting ſo very much on Chriſts being a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" extent="5 letters">
                              <desc>•••••</desc>
                           </gap>ntative,</hi> who is one that <hi>ſuſtain the Perſon of them <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Repreſents:</hi> However, it's rejected and expoſed to ſcorn and contempt, by <hi>this Brother,</hi> who thereby doth, in this inſtance, prove the Reports to be <hi>True;</hi> For, it being affirmed in the <hi>Report,</hi> that this Phraſe of <hi>Chriſts ſustaining our Perſon,</hi> is Rejected by them; you ſee it to be ſo, and the Reaſon aſſigned is, becauſe it <hi>could not bear a ſound ſenſe,</hi> but is <hi>lyable to be Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a ſenſe of Malignity to the whole of the Goſpel.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>III.</hi> A Commutation or Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us, is Denyed.</head>
                  <p>The Paper ſent by ſome <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Brethren unto the Congregational, intimating, that the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Goſpel Truth Stated,</hi> had denyed <hi>a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or Change of Perſons between Christ and us;</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Brethren, who meet at <hi>Little St. Hellens,</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their Oppoſite Senſe thus, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">It is manifeſt, that when Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> uſeth the Phraſe <hi>[of no Change of Perſons between Christ and us]</hi> it could not be intended, as a denyal of <hi>a Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us,</hi> in the general Senſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But what thinks my Reverend Brother of this? It appears clear enough to me, that he is of Opinion, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Ws. <hi>doth deny a Change of Perſons between Christ and us, in every Senſe.</hi> And yet on the other hand, he ſeems to argue, as if Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> held a Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us, in ſome Senſe, which is Evident from what he ſaith of a <hi>Change</hi> and no Change; [tho' he had little Reaſon to ſpeak of <hi>no Change,</hi> ſeeing he is the man that is given ſo much to <hi>Change</hi>] and his falling ſo ſeverely upon the <hi>Reporter,</hi> for ſuggeſting, that Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> Denyed <hi>a Change of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons between Chriſt and us, in every Senſe?</hi> For he very triumphantly tells us,</p>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:31799:20"/>
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> did not deny a Change of Perſon, <hi>ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter, ſed ſecundum quid;</hi> not univerſally, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictively; for the moſt univerſal Terms are not always <hi>univerſally</hi> to be underſtood. pag. 38.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. This Paragraph of my Reverend Brother, in Connection with what precedes, and follows it, doth, I confeſs, look as if he held, that Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us, in the general ſenſe: And for once we will ſuppoſe it, and ſee how agreeable this Notion is with his way of arguing on this occaſion, which is thus,</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> did not deny a <hi>Change of Perſon ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſed ſecundum quid,</hi> not <hi>univerſally</hi> but <hi>restrictively.</hi> Well then; on this ſuppoſal, what follows? Becauſe Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> did nor deny a <hi>Change of Perſon, ſimpliciter,</hi> and <hi>univerſally,</hi> therefore muſt he be for a Change of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons between Chriſt and us, <hi>ſecundum quid,</hi> &amp; <hi>restrictive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly?</hi> Yes; It muſt be ſo. How then ſhall we Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate this Notion with what is in pag. 9. in which place he thus expreſſeth himſelf; <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Where lies the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, that becauſe there was a <hi>Change of Christs Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for ſinners,</hi> there muſt be a <hi>Change of Perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and ſinners?</hi>
                        </hi> This Paſſage makes it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that in the Judgment of my Brother, theſe two Phraſes <hi>[A Change of Chriſts Perſon for ſinners;]</hi> and <hi>[a Change of Perſon between Chriſt and ſinners]</hi> are ſo very different, and in their Meaning ſo Remote from each other, that from the Aſſerting the one, the other cannot be neceſſarily inferred. How then can, ſay I, theſe two Paſſages be Conciliated? Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> muſt hold a <hi>Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us, ſecundum quid,</hi> becauſe he doth not <hi>ſimply and univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny a Change of Christs Perſon;</hi> and yet there lyes no neceſſity, that becauſe there is a <hi>Change of Christs Perſon for us,</hi> there <hi>must be a Change of Perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:31799:20"/> Christ and Us?</hi> How ſhall we ſet theſe things together? Or, find in our Brothers Arguings a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Brethren at <hi>Little St. Hellens?</hi> It muſt be thus or not at all, that I can ſee. Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> doth not deny a <hi>change of Christ's Perſon</hi> Simply and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally, therefore in ſome reſpect he muſt be for a <hi>change of Perſon between Chriſt and Us.</hi> That is to ſay, tho' a Man may hold a <hi>change of Christ's Perſon,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out holding a <hi>change of Perſons between Christ</hi> and Us, in any ſenſe; yet Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> muſt be for a <hi>change of Perſons between Christ and Us,</hi> in ſome ſenſe, becauſe he doth not deny a <hi>change of Christ's Perſon ſimply,</hi> and <hi>in every ſenſe.</hi> He muſt own that the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> was a good man, in ſome reſpect, becauſe he doth not ſay, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was Evil in every reſpect. The Connection between a <hi>change of Christ's Perſon,</hi> and a <hi>change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us,</hi> is, in the Judgment of my Brother, no other than what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Piety of the one Apoſtle, and the Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the other. But,</p>
                     <p n="3">3. My Brother is in good earneſt, only for a <hi>change of Chriſt's Perſon,</hi> without a <hi>change of Perſons between Chriſt and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> as I will ſoon prove, ſo that all this noiſe about a <hi>change of Chriſt's Perſon ſecundum quid,</hi> and <hi>Reſtrictively,</hi> is nothing to the purpoſe. The queſtion is not, <hi>whether there be a change of Chriſt's Perſon for Sinners?</hi> No <hi>Socinian</hi> will deny thus much. But, <hi>whether there be a change of Perſons between Chriſt and Sinners?</hi> The Brethren at St. <hi>Hellens</hi> ſay, There is a <hi>change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us;</hi> at leaſt in the general ſenſe, and they thought, that Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> held ſo too. But, if we may Judge of Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> by his Defender, its notorious, that Mr. <hi>Ws. doth not hold a change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us,</hi> in any ſenſe. That this phraſe is of a late contrivance, and muſt have a <hi>Blaſphemous</hi> ſenſe, as I will ſhew from my Brothers own words.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:31799:21"/>
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">The Controverſie lieth in ſome School Terms, or <hi>Jargons</hi> of Art, of a very late Contrivance, ſuch as a <hi>change of Perſons between Chriſt and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi> p. 30.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. This contemptuous Treatment, with which my Brother entertains this phraſe, (which as it has been long ago uſed by the Church of God; ſo is it moſt apt to expreſs that great Truth, delivered in the Holy Scriptures, where it's ſaid, <hi>Chriſt died for us</hi>) can indicate nothing leſs than that He <hi>Believes not</hi> a <hi>change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. He ſaith, that it is a phraſe of a <hi>very late contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance,</hi> and a <hi>School</hi> Term, whereas the learned Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> hath prov'd it to have been uſed by the <hi>Fathers,</hi> ſuch as St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome, Gregory Nyſſen,</hi> and <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> long before the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> had their riſe. <hi>Owen</hi> of <hi>Juſtif.</hi> p. 41, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Witſius</hi> proves it too.</p>
                     <p>My Brother goeth on to aſſure us, that this phraſe, of a <hi>change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us,</hi> muſt have a <hi>Blaſphemous ſenſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Let us Examine the phraſe: <hi>A change of perſons between Chriſt and Us;</hi> If I underſtood <hi>Grammar,</hi> the <hi>ſenſe muſt be,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt was changed <hi>for</hi> us;</hi> and we <hi>for <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
                           </hi> the <hi>change</hi> muſt <hi>be mutual,</hi> and <hi>Interchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</hi> But though Chriſt <hi>Redeemed us;</hi> we never Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed Chriſt: Chriſt ſtood in our place, as our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, we never ſtood in his place, nor were his Redeemers: He Died <hi>for us,</hi> for our ſins; we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>never Died <hi>for <hi>him,</hi>
                           </hi> for his ſins. <hi>p.</hi> 9.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. That my reverend Brother hath delivered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in a point of this Importance ſo haſtily, doth greatly leſſen him in the Eſteem of ſome of his trueſt Friends. For he is poſitive, that the phraſe of <hi>a change
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:31799:21"/> of Perſons between Chriſt and Us, <hi>muſt ſignifie,</hi>
                        </hi> that we Died for <hi>Chriſt's ſins,</hi> to Redeem him; Now, ſeeing this <hi>muſt <hi>be</hi>
                        </hi> the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the phraſe, I deſire to know, whether we did, in any ſenſe, <hi>General,</hi> or <hi>Special,</hi> Die for Chriſt's Sins? If this <hi>must be</hi> the ſenſe of the phraſe; except my Brother believes, that in ſome <hi>ſenſe,</hi> we did Die to Redeem Chriſt, he can't hold a change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us, in any ſenſe, and whatever my reverend Brethren in <hi>Little St. Hellens</hi> did <hi>charitably</hi> hope, it's now manifeſt from this <hi>Rebuker,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> by the phraſe [of <hi>no change of Perſons between Christ and Us</hi>] did intend the denial of a change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us in the <hi>General</hi> ſenſe. Yea farther,</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That ſeeing my reverend Brethren at <hi>St. Hellens</hi> are for a <hi>change of Perſons between Christ and Us,</hi> they muſt, in the Opinion of the Rebuker, hold, that We Died for Chriſt's Sins, and Redeemed him, which is <hi>Blaſphemy.</hi> I wiſh my Brother would think a little on what he Aſſerts, when he ſo boldly avers, that the ſenſe <hi>of a change of Perſons</hi> between Chriſt and Us, <hi>muſt be,</hi> that we were <hi>Chang'd for him,</hi> ſo as <hi>to Die for his Sins:</hi> Never did a <hi>Socinus,</hi> a <hi>Crellius,</hi> or any raſh <hi>Engliſh Unitarian</hi> charge this phraſe, and the generality of the Reformed, with more than Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy. But,</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Where is the man, that ever gave ſuch a ſenſe of this phraſe? The learned <hi>Witſius</hi> is perſuaded, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That never any one, who underſtood Divinity, no, not a Man in <hi>his Wits,</hi> did ever Dream of ſuch a Permutation of Perſons, as that, which places the Saviour amongſt <hi>the ſaved. Iren. Animad. cap.</hi> 2. §. 8.</hi> And ſure I am, that <hi>Crellius,</hi> tho' he faſtned a wrong ſenſe upon the word <hi>Surrogation,</hi> 'twas not ſuch a <hi>Blaſphemous</hi> one. For, when he ſaith, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">There is not a <hi>proper Surrogation</hi> in <hi>Chriſt's Dying for us,</hi> It is (ſaith he) becauſe a <hi>proper Surrogation</hi> muſt be ſuch a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:31799:22"/> 
                           <hi>Commutation of Perſons,</hi> that the ſubſtituted perſon is, <hi>in all reſpects,</hi> to be in the ſame <hi>place,</hi> and <hi>ſtate,</hi> wherein the other was, and if it refers to <hi>Sufferings,</hi> then it is when one <hi>ſuffers the very ſame,</hi> which the other was to ſuffer, he being immediately delivered by the others ſuffering.</hi> But in anſwer unto <hi>Crellius</hi> it's cleared, That to endure the ſame Puniſhment <hi>in all reſpects,</hi> is not neceſſary to a <hi>proper Surrogation.</hi> 
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That, if <hi>David,</hi> (as the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> has it) had obtain'd his wiſh, that he had Died for his Son <hi>Abſolom,</hi> it had not been neceſſary in order to his Sons Eſcape, that he had <hi>hanged by the Hair of his Head,</hi> as <hi>his Son;</hi> but his <hi>Death,</hi> tho' in other <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances,</hi> had been ſufficient. And therefore, when the Lawyers ſay, <hi>ſubrogatum ſapit naturam ejus, in cujus Locum ſubrogatur: Coverruvias</hi> tells us, it is to be underſtood <hi>ſecundum primordia<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>em</hi> natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, <hi>non ſecundum accidentalem;</hi> from whence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that <hi>all <hi>circumſtances</hi>
                           </hi> are not neceſſary to be the ſame in <hi>Surrogation,</hi> but that the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>the Puniſhment remain.</hi>
                        </hi> Diſcourſ. of Chriſt's ſuff. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 324. But where is the man, who at any time <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied that a <hi>Commutation of Perſons between Chriſt a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> Us,</hi> muſt ſignifie, that as Chriſt ſuffered for us, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> we ſuffered for Chriſt. There is a Commutation between a Surety and the Debtor, which is when the Surety, ſuſtaining the Perſon of the Debtor, pays his Debts for him; but muſt this phraſe of a change of Perſons between the Surety and the Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ſignifie, that the Debtor pays the Debts of his Surety? Is it not ſufficient, that it ſignifieth, that on the Sureties coming into the ſame Bonds with the Debtor, and Paying the Debt he owed, the Debtor be thereby delivered? The ſame may be truly ſaid of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for he being our Surety, took on him our Perſon, ſo that there was a change of Perſons between him and us, He paid the Debt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:31799:22"/> we owed, that we might be delivered. Not that we Paid any Debts for Chriſt, for he owed none. But the <hi>Term Surety</hi> is alſo rejected, as what can't bear a ſound ſenſe; which may further aſſure us, That a Change <hi>of Perſon between Chriſt and Us,</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied in the general ſenſe. Once more,</p>
                     <p n="4">4. As the phraſe of a <hi>change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us</hi> is entirely denied, in like manner a New Phraſe of a <hi>Change of Chriſts Perſon</hi> is invented, and put into its place, Tho' what to make of it my Brother is at a loſs; and when He goes about to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain it, he is miſerably confounded.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">This phraſe, the <hi>Change of the Perſon of Chriſt,</hi> may have, and truly has an Honeſt, and ſound ſenſe, in which it may be of ſome good Uſe to Explain the Doctrines of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and <hi>Juſtification;</hi> and it is that which the <hi>R. R. the Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> with <hi>Grotius</hi> againſt <hi>Crellius</hi> do put upon it, <hi>Reaſ. of Chriſt's Suffer. Edit.</hi> 1. p. 144. viz. The <hi>Substitution of One Perſon in the room of another,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 44.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. There is, ſaith he, an Honeſt ſenſe of this phraſe, [the <hi>change of Chriſts Perſon</hi>] hath, and it is that, which the R. R. the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> with <hi>Grotius</hi> againſt <hi>Crellius</hi> put upon it. He ſhould have ſaid what <hi>Grotius,</hi> with the Biſhop of <hi>Worcester</hi> againſt <hi>Crellius</hi> put upon it; for, tho' <hi>Crellius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> wrote againſt <hi>Grotius,</hi> and the Biſhop againſt <hi>Crellius,</hi> yet <hi>Grotius</hi> never wrote againſt <hi>Crellius.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. What ſenſe did theſe great Men put upon this phraſe, of a <hi>change of Chriſts perſon?</hi> I can't conceive how they ſhould put any ſenſe upon it, for, 'twas not known, when they wrote on Chriſt's Satisfaction; nor ever invented till the Gentleman, who engaged my Brother to enter upon this ſorrowful Undertaking, ſtarted it. And to ſpeak the Truth, 'tis a phraſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:31799:23"/> adjuſted to expreſs no more than what the <hi>Socinians</hi> do conſtantly grant; for they ſay it again and again, that Chriſt, tho' he ſuffered not the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> due to us for ſin, yet he endured Grievous and Dolorous Pains, which is aptly enough expreſſed, when it's ſaid there was a <hi>change of Chriſt's Perſon for us,</hi> for he was, ſay theſe Hereticks, <hi>Changed <hi>from Eaſe to Pain for our Good.</hi>
                        </hi> However,</p>
                     <p n="3">3. My Brother will have it, that the Biſhop hath put a ſound ſenſe upon this phraſe, <hi>viz. It is the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of one Perſon into the room of another.</hi> Doth the Biſhop give this Interpretation of the phraſe of a change of Chriſt's Perſon? Or, doth he not rather think, that there can be no Subſtitution of one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon into the room of another, without a <hi>change of Perſon</hi> between <hi>that One, and the other?</hi> Thus much undoubtedly he holds. But to Inſinuate, that this great Man and <hi>Grotius</hi> are for a change of Chriſt's Perſon, without a change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us, and make that <hi>change of Chriſt's Perſon</hi> to ſignifie a <hi>Subſtitution</hi> of Chriſt in our room, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent 'em to be ſuch <hi>Self-contradictors,</hi> as indeed, my Brother and his Principal are. A <hi>change of Chriſt's</hi> Perſon, without a change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us, muſt be a <hi>Change</hi> without a <hi>Subſtitution,</hi> for a Subſtitution there cannot be without a change of <hi>Perſons</hi> between one, and another. To affirm that Chriſt was Subſtituted into our Place and Room, and at the ſame time to deny a Commutation of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons between Chriſt and Us, is to Say, and Unſay.</p>
                     <p>That I may therefore clear the Truth in this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and Vindicate theſe learned Men from the charge of denying a <hi>change of Perſons between Chriſt and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> and of affirming a <hi>Subſtitution of Chriſt into</hi> our room, I will give you their own words on this Subject, and add to them what the great <hi>Turretine</hi> ſaith of the phraſe of a <hi>change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:31799:23"/>1. That <hi>Grotius</hi> is for a Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us, I mean ſuch a Change of Perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the one and the other, as is more than only a <hi>Change</hi> of a <hi>Perſon.</hi> For, 1. <hi>Grotius</hi> his word is <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation,</hi> which imports, that what is changed hath an eſſential reſpect to the Change of another, whether it be meant of <hi>Things</hi> or <hi>Perſons,</hi> the Commutation muſt ſignifie more than the Change either of one thing, or of one Perſon, it muſt be between Thing and Thing; or between Perſon and Perſon; Or, as <hi>Crellius</hi> ſaith, between a Thing and a Perſon: Tho' there may be a Change of one thing only, or of one Perſon; yet, a <hi>Commutation</hi> of <hi>one</hi> thing; or of <hi>one</hi> Perſon only is an Implication. 2. The Change, <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſpeaks of, is ſuch a Change, as is <hi>per ſucceſſionem,</hi> where one goeth out of the place and another comes into it, which cannot poſſibly be, if the Change be only of one. <hi rend="margSglQuotes">As often (ſaith <hi>Grotius</hi>) as the Praepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>[For]</hi> is applied to <hi>Perſons,</hi> it ſignifieth the <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of one into the room and place of another by Succeſſion.</hi> Thus <hi>Archelaus</hi> is ſaid to Reign <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>[For Herod]</hi> That is, He Succeeded <hi>Herod</hi> in the Throne. — <hi>Socinus,</hi> when preſſed, dares not deny, that <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>[For many]</hi> doth ſignifie a <hi>Commutation.</hi> — We were <hi>Debitores mortis,</hi> from this <hi>debt</hi> we were diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by <hi>Chriſts</hi> giving ſomewhat, to give ſomewhat, that <hi>by it,</hi> we may be diſcharged, is to <hi>Pay</hi> or <hi>Satisfie.</hi>
                        </hi> This <hi>Phraſe</hi> therefore, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>[To give for many]</hi> doth always ſignifie a <hi>True Commutation;</hi> not a <hi>Metaphorical One,</hi> as <hi>Socinus</hi> without any Preſident affirms. — <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>For,</hi> doth neceſſarily denote a <hi>Commutation. <hi>Grot. de Satiſ. Cap.</hi>
                        </hi> 9.</p>
                     <p>Here's not a word of the <hi>Change of one Perſon</hi> only; it being a <hi>Commutation,</hi> which is a <hi>Change between one Perſon and another,</hi> that <hi>Grotius</hi> ſpeaks of, where he, who owed nothing, is come into the place of the Debtor, and paying the debt, the Debtor is diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:31799:24"/> and thereby brought into a ſtate of Liberty and Freedom. Here is, I ſay, a <hi>Commutation,</hi> or <hi>Change of Perſons,</hi> which in ſome reſpect is <hi>mutual,</hi> but not in all reſpects ſo; It is, as the Learned Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> has it, a <hi>Commutation, or Change of Perſons</hi> between Chriſt and us, as to <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> whence Chriſt is made <hi>our ſin,</hi> and they, who believe, are made the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Right Reverend the Biſhop of <hi>Worcester,</hi> who, in his Defence of <hi>Grotius,</hi> againſt <hi>Crellius,</hi> hath very Clearly ſtated the Controverſie between the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox and the <hi>Socinians,</hi> and given the true ſenſe of <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius:</hi> is very particular and diſtinct in his Aſſerting and Explaining the Doctrine of a <hi>Commutation of Perſons between Chriſt and us,</hi> in theſe words, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">In the matter of Redemption, or where <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> is uſed, <hi>Crellius</hi> will by no means yield, that there was a <hi>Commutation of Perſons between Chriſt and us;</hi> but all the <hi>Commutation</hi> he will allow here, is only a <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> between a <hi>Thing</hi> or a <hi>Price</hi> and a <hi>Perſon;</hi> which he therefore aſſerts, <hi>that ſo there may <hi>be no neceſſity</hi>
                           </hi> of Chriſts <hi>undergoing</hi> the <hi>Puniſhment <hi>of ſin,</hi>
                           </hi> in <hi>order to Redemption,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Price</hi> that is paid, is not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to undergo the <hi>Condition</hi> of the <hi>Perſon Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by it;</hi> which will evidently appear to have no force at all, in caſe we can prove, that a <hi>Proper Redemption</hi> may be obtained by the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of <hi>one</hi> in the <hi>room of another;</hi> for that <hi>Puniſhment</hi> then comes to be the <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, or <hi>Price</hi> of Redemption, and he that pays this, muſt be ſuppoſed to undergo <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> for it: ſo that the <hi>Commutation</hi> being <hi>between the one and the other,</hi> Redeemed by it, here is a <hi>Proper Commutation of Perſons</hi> implied in the <hi>Payment of the price.</hi> Diſc. <hi>of Chriſts ſuffer. Ed.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 325.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In theſe words the Learned Biſhop is very full in aſſerting a <hi>Proper Commutation <hi>of Perſons between
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:31799:24"/> Chriſt and us;</hi>
                        </hi> That whereas <hi>Crellius</hi> denied a <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Perſons</hi> that there might <hi>be no neceſſity</hi> of Chriſts undergoing the Puniſhment of ſin, in order to Redemption, the Biſhop doth with clearneſs detect his ſubtilty; and Learnedly Confute him, making it to appear, that thoſe places of Scripture, where <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> are joyned together, do prove a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation,</hi> not of a price for a Perſon, but of <hi>one Perſon for another;</hi> or which is the ſame, a <hi>ſubstitution of one Perſon in the room of another;</hi> for, theſe Phraſes, <hi>[a Commutation of one Perſon for another]</hi> and <hi>[a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of one Perſon into the room of another]</hi> as the Biſhop and all others, acquainted with this Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, apprehend, do ſignifie ſo much the ſame thing, that whoever yields the one, can't in reaſon deny the other.</p>
                     <p>The Biſhop, diſcourſing of <hi>Expiatory Sacrifices,</hi> clears it, that the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves underſtood <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Capar,</hi> to import ſuch an Expiation as is made by the <hi>ſubſtitution of one in the Place of another,</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us, that <hi>Buxturf</hi> has collected many Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherein <hi>Capara</hi> is taken by the <hi>Rabinical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> for ſuch an <hi>Expiation,</hi> whereby one was to undergo a <hi>Puniſhment</hi> in the place of another; And (ſaith the Biſhop) <hi rend="margSglQuotes">I inſiſt on theſe things, only to let us underſtand, that the <hi>Jews</hi> never underſtood <hi>Capar</hi> in the ſenſe our Adverſaries contend for, when applyed to an <hi>Expiatory Sacrifice,</hi> but as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying a <hi>Commutation</hi> and a <hi>Subſtitution <hi>of one in the place of another,</hi>
                           </hi> ſo as by the puniſhment of <hi>that,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> in whoſe room <hi>he</hi> ſuffers, may obtain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance.</hi> Of <hi>Chriſts Suffer.</hi> p. 359, 360. Here you ſee a <hi>Commutation</hi> and a <hi>Subſtitution</hi> do go together, and as the Biſhop adds, <hi>Which is the ſenſe we plead for.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The thing is ſo very clear, that my Brother could never have miſ-repreſented theſe Great Men thus, nor indeed have himſelf fallen into this miſtake, if he had not uſed the word, without framing in his
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:31799:25"/> Mind an Idea of its Import. If he had taken the Phraſe of a <hi>Subſtitution of one Perſon into the Room of another,</hi> in the Common Senſe of the Words, he could not but obſerve, a <hi>Commutation, or Change of Perſons between the one and the other,</hi> and that if the Change had been but of <hi>one,</hi> of the Subſtituted Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon only, there could be no room for him to be placed in, that is, there could be no <hi>Subſtitution.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In a word, from what I have inſiſted on it's mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that the Learned Biſhop is moſt expreſs in aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a <hi>Proper Commutation, or Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us:</hi> So that my Reverend Brother, when he ſuggeſts the contrary, doth really miſ-repreſent and abuſe the Biſhop. But</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The Learned <hi>Turretine,</hi> who is acknowledged by all to have written of Chriſts Satisfaction with as much clearneſs, and ſtrength as moſt Men, is very large in his Defence of a <hi>Commutation, or Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us,</hi> againſt <hi>Socinus</hi> and <hi>Crel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> 
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">For (ſaith he) ſeeing our Salvation may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered under a fourfold Reſpect; (1.) With reſpect to <hi>God, Judging.</hi> (2.) As to <hi>Chriſt, Redeeming,</hi> and ſo there is a <hi>Permutation,</hi> becauſe Chriſt is made <hi>ſin,</hi> and a Curſe for us, that we might be the bleſſed of God in him. De Satiſ. par.</hi> 1. <hi>Diſp.</hi> 3. § 29. And in the following <hi>Diſputation,</hi> § 5. <hi rend="margSglQuotes">When it's ſaid <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Chriſt gave himſelf a Ranſom for many,</hi> the praepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Communiſſimè, &amp; maximè propriè ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutionem, &amp; Commutationem deſignat;</hi>
                        </hi> this praepoſition <hi>[For]</hi> doth moſt frequently and properly denote a <hi>Subſtitution</hi> and <hi>Commutation:</hi> And this Great Man adds, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">
                           <hi>Crellius</hi> againſt <hi>Grotius,</hi> inſinuates, that we are deceived in thinking, that there is a <hi>Commutation between Chriſt and us,</hi> in the controverted Places, as if, when we were to give our ſouls, Chriſt <hi>in our Place gave his Soul,</hi> the Commutation is only between a <hi>Thing</hi> and a <hi>Perſon;</hi> between a Price, that is, the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:31799:25"/> Soul and Life <hi>of Chriſt, and us,</hi> as Captives and Slaves, but who did ever ſay, that <hi>Chriſts blood m<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> ſubrogated for us, and came into our Place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi>
                        </hi> To th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> of <hi>Crellius, Turretine</hi> thus anſwers, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That whilſt he endeavours to deceive others, he himſelf is moſt ſhamefully deluded, for theſe are not <hi>our words ſed ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba Scripturae,</hi> but it is the Scripture, <hi>quae <hi>Commutatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem illam inter Chriſtum</hi> &amp; <hi>nos</hi> ſtatuit, dum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſè dicit Chriſtum ſeipſum dediſſe pro multis,</hi> which <hi>direct</hi> to this <hi>Commutation, <hi>or Change between Chriſt and us;</hi>
                           </hi> when it's ſaid ſo expreſly, that <hi>Chriſt gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for many,</hi> Mat. 20.28, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This <hi>Phraſe of a Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us,</hi> is, in the Judgment of the Learned <hi>Turretine,</hi> a <hi>Scripture Phraſe,</hi> intended by Chriſt himſelf when it's ſaid, <hi>He gave himſelf [For] many.</hi> I might give a large Catalogue of other Authorities, but, that this is the Doctrine, commonly received by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> is ſo manifeſt, that whoever hath any tollerable Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with their Writings, cannot but be convinced of the Truth of what I do herein affirm, much more ſhould he, who has received a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from all the <hi>Systematical Divines</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> the <hi>Voluminous Tigur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines</hi> and <hi>Bulky Low-Dutch,</hi> and with thoſe few that are left in <hi>England,</hi> be ſufficienty inſtructed in the Knowledge of ſuch a Plain and Common Truth.</p>
                     <p>Theſe things then have been cleared that my <hi>Rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> doth untruly repreſent the <hi>Phraſe of a Change of Perſons between Christ and us,</hi> to be a <hi>Jargon</hi> of Art; of a <hi>very late Contrivance;</hi> that can't bear a ſound ſenſe, but muſt ſignifie <hi>Blasphemy;</hi> That he, or his <hi>guide,</hi> has invented a <hi>New Phraſe of a Change of Chriſts Perſon;</hi> that he has Unrighteouſly Charged <hi>Grotius</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> for uſing it, that the ſenſe he feigns them to put upon it is inconſiſtent with his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying</hi> a Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:31799:26"/> And, do he what he can, he muſt ſplit either on a <hi>Contradiction;</hi> or on <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> or both.</p>
                     <p>Thus you ſee whither my Brothers <hi>Heats,</hi> or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe has hurryed him.</p>
                     <p>But it's urged, that tho' a <hi>Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us,</hi> is denyed; yet ſo long as it's owned, that the Lord Chriſt <hi>ſuffered in our Place and Stead,</hi> the <hi>Truth is ſecured.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">I would a thouſand times ſooner chuſe to adhere to this Phraſe, Chriſt ſuffered, and dyed in our <hi>Stead</hi> and <hi>Place [Loco noſtro, vice noſtrâ]</hi> than to that other; In the ſufferings of Chriſt, there was a <hi>Change</hi> of <hi>Perſons</hi> between <hi>Chriſt and us;</hi> for the former has had its ſignification ſtrongly fixed, and ſettled by long Uſage, and Praeſcription: Whereas this latter is but of Yeſterday, and ſcarce two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, no, not the Inventors agreed amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, what ſenſe to ſtamp upon it. Again, the plaineſt Chriſtians have a tolerable underſtanding of the former, whereas the other does but <hi>Amuſe</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found</hi> them. p. 37.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. If Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> had taken this Phraſe <hi>[in our place and ſtead]</hi> in it's Antient and Genuine Senſe, it would have argued, that he was ſound in the Faith, and that his rejecting the Phraſe of a <hi>Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us,</hi> would have been only an evincement of his want of Learning, and that he underſtood not the Controverſie he wrote of.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That, if this had been the Caſe, the Reverend Brethren, at <hi>Little St. Hellens,</hi> would have been in the Right, when they ſaid, Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> cannot be underſtood to deny a Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us, in the <hi>general</hi> ſenſe becauſe he uſes the Phraſe of Chriſts ſuffering in our place and ſtead, which doth ſignifie a <hi>Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us.</hi> But</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:31799:26"/>3. He who wrote the <hi>Report,</hi> had, it's like, ſome Reaſons, moving him to ſuſpect Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> that as he did (whether in ignorance or knowingly, I ſay not) concur with <hi>Socinus</hi> and <hi>Crellius,</hi> in denying a <hi>Proper Commutation, or Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us;</hi> ſo he did with ſome high <hi>Arminians,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> impoſe a wrong ſenſe on the <hi>Phraſe of</hi> Chriſts ſuffering <hi>in our Place and Stead,</hi> who intend by it <hi>no more</hi> than that Chriſt ſuffered <hi>for our good,</hi> in which ſenſe it doth not, I confeſs, imply a Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us; nor can the Uſe of it be ſufficient to prove, that he who doth expreſly deny a Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us, doth hold a Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us, which was the thing the Reporter preſſed. And now the Rebuker has made manifeſt.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. That the Phraſe of Chriſts ſuffering <hi>in our place and ſtead,</hi> is not taken by them in the ſenſe of the Reformed, for as it's ſet up in contradiſtinction to a Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us, ſo it's made to ſignifie <hi>no more</hi> than <hi>for our good,</hi> for which reaſon the next Charge is,</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>IV.</hi> That an Heterodox Senſe is Impoſed on the Phraſe of <hi>Chriſts ſuffering in our Place and Stead.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="margSglQuotes">There are, ſaith <hi>Turretine,</hi> ſeveral Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in which 'tis aſſerted, <hi>That Chriſt dyed <hi>for us,</hi> Rom.</hi> 8.32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6, 8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.28. Theſe and many other ſuch Texts, do either bear but a <hi>Frigid,</hi> and <hi>Jejune ſenſe; or muſt neceſſarily import ſuch a ſurrogation,</hi> as ſignifieth, that Chriſt did undergo the moſt curſed Death, not only <hi>bono, &amp; Commodo noſtro,</hi> for <hi>our good and profit,</hi> But moreover, <hi>vice ac Loco noſtro,</hi> in <hi>our place and ſtead.</hi> De Satiſ. par. 1. Diſput. 4. Theſ. 2.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> in the Second Part of his <hi>Preſervative</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:31799:27"/> againſt <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> having aſſerted, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour by dying and ſhedding his blood, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went that puniſhment, and ſubmitted to that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, which our ſins had otherwiſe rendred us, inevitably obnoxious to; and this being in it ſelf a <hi>Sufficient Compenſation</hi> made to the Juſtice of God, for the Affronts and Injuries offered to his Authority by the violation of his Laws; and likewiſe being accepted of by him as ſuch: It muſt <hi>from hence neceſſarily and naturally</hi> be effectual to procure for us <hi>Pardon,</hi> and Impunity.</hi> The Dr. having aſſerted thus much, he adds, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">
                        <hi>Now this being a matter of great Conſequence, upon which the <hi>whole ſtreſs</hi>
                        </hi> of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie between us, and our Adverſaries <hi>Leans</hi> and <hi>Reſts,</hi> I ſhall a little further enlarge upon it, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make out theſe <hi>two Things,</hi> 1. That <hi>Chriſt dyed for our ſakes,</hi> and that not only as it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies for our <hi>Benefit</hi> and <hi>Advantage,</hi> but <hi>in our room</hi> and <hi>ſtead,</hi> p. 94.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What the Dr. hath in this place declared, is nothing elſe than what the Orthodox univerſally do, in their Oppugning the <hi>Socinian</hi> Hereſie, in this great Point; For they all hold, that as the Phraſe, in <hi>our room and stead,</hi> ſignifyeth <hi>ſomewhat more</hi> than <hi>for our good,</hi> ſo it points us to <hi>that</hi> upon which the whole ſtreſs of the Controverſie between us and them doth Lean.</p>
                  <p>But what is this <hi>ſomewhat more?</hi> I anſwer,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Turretine,</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſts Suffering <hi>vice nostrâ,</hi> in our place and ſtead, explains it thus, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Chriſt, as <hi>our Surety</hi> ſuffered what we had deſerved, that by making a full ſatisfaction to Divine Juſtice, we might be delivered from eternal Death, and being delivered, might moreover, be made partakers of eternal Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To ſuffer, you ſee, <hi>vice noſtrâ,</hi> in <hi>our stead,</hi> is in the Judgment of this great Man, to ſuffer as our <hi>Surety,</hi> and who knoweth not, that a <hi>Surety</hi> is ſubſtituted
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:31799:27"/> into the room of the Debtor; that between the one and the other there is a <hi>Commutation,</hi> or <hi>Change of Perſons,</hi> beſides, <hi>ſuſtinere vicem <hi>noſtram</hi>
                     </hi> is the ſame with <hi>ſuſtinere perſonam noſtram;</hi> to ſuffer <hi>in our ſtead</hi> the ſame with ſuffering in <hi>our Perſon.</hi> Further,</p>
                  <p>This phraſe <hi>[vice noſtrâ, in our Stead]</hi> is uſed to interpret that other phraſe, <hi>[For us]</hi> what is done <hi>for us,</hi> is done in <hi>our ſtead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When it's ſaid in Scripture, that Chriſt ſuffered <hi>[for us,]</hi> the meaning is that Chriſt ſuffered [in <hi>our ſtead,</hi>] and that <hi>[For us]</hi> doth denote a <hi>Commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us, I have already ſhewn out of <hi>Grotius,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and <hi>Turretine</hi> about the Import of the <hi>Praepoſition</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>[For.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But in Scripture it's alſo ſaid, that Chriſt Died for <hi>our ſins;</hi> and for <hi>ſinners,</hi> and the Controverſie between <hi>Us,</hi> and the <hi>Socinians,</hi> is, whether <hi>[for our ſins]</hi> muſt be conſidered as Importing a <hi>Final,</hi> or the <hi>Impulſive and Meritorious Cauſe,</hi> of Chriſt's ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings? Now Dr. <hi>Edwards</hi> gives the ſenſe of the Orthodox, when He affirms that all thoſe phraſes of Dying <hi>for ſins,</hi> and <hi>ſinners,</hi> plainly denote to us, that ſin in thoſe places, is not to be conſidered as the <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> but as the <hi>Impulſive Meritorious Cauſe;</hi> But the <hi>Socinians</hi> will have it, that <hi>[for us]</hi> and [for <hi>our ſins</hi>] denote only a <hi>Final Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>ſignifie</hi> no more than for <hi>our good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>However my reverend Brother, for reaſons beſt <hi>known unto himſelf,</hi> is expreſs, that the phraſe of Chriſt's ſuffering in our <hi>Stead, doth ſignifie no more than for our</hi> Good, Ay, that it's <hi>Impoſſible</hi> it ſhould ſignifie <hi>any more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">He that by Chriſt's ſuffering in our <hi>ſtead,</hi> intends He ſuffered <hi>for our good</hi> ſpeaks the <hi>Truth.</hi> p. 37.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">But the Caviller proceeds; in our place and ſtead
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:31799:28"/> (with ſome) ſignifie <hi>no more than for our good</hi> why <hi>'tis Impoſſible they ſhould.</hi> p. 35.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p>What <hi>Engliſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian</hi> can more poſitively de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that it is <hi>Impoſſible</hi> for the phraſe <hi>[in our Place, and Stead]</hi> to ſignifie <hi>any more,</hi> than <hi>for our good</hi> than my Brother has done? And if it can ſignifie no more than for <hi>our good,</hi> wherein can he, who is of this Opinion, diſtinguiſh himſelf from a <hi>Socinian,</hi> when he denies a change of Perſons to <hi>be between Chriſt and Us,</hi> by ſaying, that Chriſt Died in our <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Stead?</hi> For, whilſt he ſaith Chriſt ſuffered in <hi>our Stead,</hi> according to this declaration, he muſt mean no more than that Chriſt ſuffered <hi>for our good,</hi> which may be without His making ſatisfaction to God's Juſtice for us. Alas Sirs! If you will allow us no ſenſe of the phraſe of a <hi>change of Perſons between Chriſt and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> but that we Died for Chriſt's ſins, this is <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> when yet, if there be not a change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us, there cannot be a <hi>Subſtitution</hi> of Chriſt's Perſon into our room, and conſequently Chriſt did not, and could not ſuffer in our <hi>place</hi> and <hi>ſtead,</hi> which is, He did not, he could not make ſatisfaction, a <hi>Real, Proper,</hi> and <hi>Full</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction unto God's Juſtice for us.</p>
                     <p>Here is the very natural and irrefragable Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence which flows from my Brother's denying, a <hi>change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us.</hi> For (I ſay) if Chriſt ſuffered not in <hi>our ſtead,</hi> He could not make <hi>Satisfaction for us,</hi> as all will grant. If there was not a <hi>Subſtitution</hi> of Chriſt into our place, He <hi>ſuffered not in our place,</hi> and if there was not a <hi>change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us,</hi> there could not be a <hi>Subſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt into</hi> our place.</p>
                     <p>But you'l ſay, that this is a remote, Conſequence, which ought not to be charged on my Brother; well then, we will let it for once paſs ſo; and ſee
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:31799:28"/> whether He is for Chriſt's ſuffering <hi>in our ſtead,</hi> here our Enquiry is not about the <hi>word,</hi> without a <hi>mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> nor with a <hi>wrong Senſe.</hi> But, whether as it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies ſomewhat more than <hi>for our good;</hi> it may be ſaid, that Chriſt ſuffered in <hi>our ſtead?</hi> To which my Brother doth directly anſwer, That when it's ſaid Chriſt ſuffered in our ſtead, it's <hi>Impoſſible</hi> it ſhould ſignifie any <hi>more than for our Good:</hi> So clear it is, that how honeſtly ſoever my Brother may mean, his <hi>Words</hi> do in this place Expreſs a Denial of Chriſt's Satisfaction; as openly as the Engliſh <hi>Unitarians</hi> have ventured to do; And yet he doth ſay, that the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians,</hi> when they uſe this phraſe, do it <hi>Knaviſhly.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">I had rather have the <hi>Socinians</hi> ſpeak honeſtly, tho' with a <hi>Knaviſh</hi> meaning, than mean, and ſpeak, both like <hi>Knaves</hi> — If the <hi>Socinians</hi> will put an <hi>Unſound</hi> ſenſe upon <hi>ſound</hi> words, will you quit the ſound phraſe, becauſe they put a <hi>wretched Senſe</hi> on't? p. 35.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. I am willing to think my Brothers <hi>Wit</hi> hath prov'd a Snare to him in this place. For, if he be in good earneſt in any ſenſe, tho' but comparatively, for honeſt words with a <hi>Knaviſh</hi> meaning, 'twill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſome to ſuſpect, that whilſt he ſeems ſo zealous for the honeſt phraſe of Chriſt's <hi>ſuffering in our ſtead,</hi> he hath pitch'd upon the <hi>Socinian,</hi> which he calls the <hi>Knaviſh,</hi> meaning deliberately, and of choice; And that of Inclination and Deſign he doth too often ſo ſpeak, and ſo write.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Whatever my Brother intends, it's manifeſt, that whilſt he calls the <hi>Socinian</hi> ſenſe <hi>Unſound, Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>Knaviſh,</hi> He gives the very ſenſe of this phraſe, which the <hi>Socinians,</hi> who uſe it, do give; and by it means (if we may judge his meaning by his <hi>words</hi>) no more than what <hi>Socinus, Crellius,</hi> and that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:31799:29"/> 
                        <hi>Fraternity,</hi> do conſiſtently with their Denial of Chriſt's Satisfaction, conſtantly grant. But muſt we quit a ſound phraſe, when ever an Unſound ſenſe is put upon it?</p>
                     <p n="3">3. There is no need of quitting the phraſe. An <hi>Orthodox</hi> Explanation will be ſufficient to Obviate what miſchiefs are likely to ariſe from their wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Interpretations; which is the true reaſon, why I am ſo much concern'd in this affair, and preſs ſo much for the Uſe of theſe Orthodox Terms and Phraſes in their ſound ſenſe. For,</p>
                     <p n="4">4 It hath been the Practice of ſome to reject the <hi>Uſe</hi> of ſuch phraſes, as have been pitch'd upon by the Godly Learned, and are moſt apt to expreſs the Truth in the Controverted Points; and when for their Intereſt to continue their Uſe, then inſiduouſly to foiſt in a wretched ſenſe on them; chiefly for this reaſon, that they may make the <hi>Sufferings</hi> of Chriſt to be but an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Dominion;</hi> and not <hi>properly Poenal;</hi> they, as well as all others knowing that if Chriſt's Sufferings be not properly a Puniſhment, they cannot be <hi>ſatisfactory</hi> to <hi>God's Juſtice</hi> for our ſins; and if Chriſt did not ſo ſuffer in our Place and Stead, as [in <hi>our Place</hi> and <hi>Stead</hi>] ſignifie ſomewhat more than for our good, His ſufferings were not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Poenal. And, agreeably hereunto, my Brother as he Rejects the phraſes of Chriſt's <hi>ſuſtaining the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſinners; of a change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us,</hi> and puts an <hi>Unſound</hi> ſenſe on <hi>Chriſt's ſuffering</hi> in <hi>our Place</hi> and <hi>Stead;</hi> ſo that word, which was in the <hi>firſt Paper,</hi> to make it evident, that we eſteemed Chriſt's Sufferings to be a <hi>proper Puniſhment</hi> is rejected, as what can't in my Brothers Opinion bear a ſound ſenſe, which brings me to the fifth charge.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>V.</hi> Chriſt's Undertaking to Anſwer for ſinners, the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations <hi>of</hi>
                     </hi> the Violated Law of Works, <hi>is turn'd
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:31799:29"/> into</hi> Chriſt's Anſwering for our Violation of the Law of Works. <hi>To this my Brother Replies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">What is the <hi>Nice</hi> difference then between Chriſt's <hi>Anſwering <hi>for our</hi> Violation of the</hi> Law; and <hi>Anſwering <hi>for us</hi> the Violation?</hi> Or, what the <hi>Critical</hi> difference between Chriſt's anſwering <hi>for them</hi> the Violation; and Anſwering <hi>for their</hi> Violation of the Law of Works: He that Anſwers <hi>for me</hi> the Violation of the Law, Anſwers <hi>for my</hi> Violation of the Law. p. 47.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. That Chriſt ſuffered <hi>for our ſins,</hi> that is, <hi>for our</hi> Violation of the Law, the <hi>Socinians</hi> always acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but then they are ſo honeſt as to tell us, that the Praepoſition <hi>[For]</hi> in this Inſtance denotes only a <hi>Final cauſe,</hi> and that the meaning of the <hi>phraſe</hi> of Chriſt's ſuffering for our Violations of the Law is the ſame with that other of Chriſt's ſuffering <hi>for our good;</hi> for which reaſon the yielding no more than that Chriſt ſuffered for our Violation of the Law of Works, cannot be a Bar againſt <hi>Socinian</hi> Encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor a ſufficient ſecurity to the Truth of <hi>Chriſt's Satisfaction.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. My Brother doth in this place make a ſad noiſe about Anſwering for our Violation of the Law of Works, making cloſe Enquiry, where the <hi>Nice</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between <hi>for our,</hi> and <hi>for us;</hi> and the <hi>Critical</hi> difference between <hi>for them,</hi> and <hi>for their</hi> cloſing his Enquiry with a but this it is to be <hi>Hypercriticks in Theology,</hi> when it's often ridiculous <hi>in Phylology,</hi> whereas a Grain of Common Senſe would have help'd him to underſtand, that here is not one word in all his <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>Critical</hi> Diſquiſitions to the purpoſe, and that it was not about the difference between <hi>for ours,</hi> and <hi>for us,</hi> for <hi>them</hi> and for <hi>theirs,</hi> but that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:31799:30"/> the ſtreſt of what ſhe Reporter ſuggeſted on this occaſion leans on the word <hi>[Obligation.]</hi> In the firſt Paper it was, that the Lord Chriſt did Anſwer for us the <hi>Obligations</hi> of the <hi>Violated Law of Works,</hi> and it muſt be obſerv'd, that by this phraſe an Effectual <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> was laid in againſt the moſt Rotten part of the <hi>Socinian</hi> Hereſie againſt, <hi>Chriſt's Satisfaction.</hi> And the Enquiry, if ſo the purpoſe, ſhould have been, what the Nice Difference between anſwering for us the <hi>Obligations</hi> of the Violated Law of Works; and Anſwering <hi>for our Violation of the Law of Works?</hi> To which I anſwer;</p>
                     <p n="3">3. There is a very great Difference, as great as is between a <hi>Goſpel Truth,</hi> and a <hi>Socinian Errour,</hi> in an <hi>Important Article</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To clear the Truth in this Point, I will refer you to the learned Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> who truly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the ſenſe of the <hi>Socinians</hi> thus. <hi rend="margSglQuotes">They aſſert, <hi>That God took occaſion by the ſins of Men to exerciſe an Act of Dominion upon Chriſt in his</hi> ſufferings, and <hi>that the</hi> ſufferings of <hi>Chriſt were intended for the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the ſins of men;</hi> but they utterly deny, <hi>that the ſufferings of Chriſt were to be conſidered, as a</hi> Puniſhment <hi>for ſin,</hi> or <hi>that Chriſt did ſuffer in our place and ſtead,</hi> nay they contend with great ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency, <hi>that it is wholly inconſiſtent with the Juſtice of God to make one mans ſins, the Meritorious Cauſe of anothers Puniſhment; eſpecially One wholly Innocent, and ſo that the Guilty ſhall be Freed on the account of his ſufferings.</hi> Thus I have endeavoured to give the <hi>true ſtate</hi> of the Controverſie, with all Clearneſs and Brevity. And the ſubſtance of it will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to theſe two Heads.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus this learned Biſhop. The firſt Head of the two, being moſtly to my purpoſe, I'll only mention it and ſomewhat ſaid of it. It is this, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Whether the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt in general are to be conſidered as
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:31799:30"/> a <hi>Puniſhment of Sin,</hi> or as a meer act of <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion?</hi> for that it muſt be one or the other of theſe two, cannot be denied by our Adverſaries; for the Inflicting thoſe Sufferings upon Chriſt, muſt either proceed from an <hi>Anteceding Meritorious Cauſe,</hi> or not. If they do, they are then <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> if not, they are meer Exerciſes of Power and Dominion; whatever Ends they are Intended for and whatever Recompence be made for them. Of Chriſt Suff.</hi> p. 267.</p>
                     <p>Here then lies the Heart of the Controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and them, whether <hi>our ſins be an Impulſive Meritorious Cauſe of Chriſt's ſufferings;</hi> and <hi>Christ's ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings a proper Puniſhment for our ſins?</hi> If our ſins be the <hi>Meritorious</hi> Cauſe of Chriſt's ſufferings, it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily follows, that Chriſt bore the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of our ſins in a <hi>proper</hi> ſenſe.</p>
                     <p>An Impulſive Cauſe, in a remote ſenſe, as though our ſins <hi>were a meer</hi> Occaſion of Chriſt's Dying <hi>Crel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> granted. But as the Biſhop obſerves, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">We Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not an Impulſive Cauſe in ſo remote a ſenſe, — but we contend for a <hi>nearer</hi> and more proper ſenſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Death of Chriſt was <hi>primarily</hi> intended for the Expiation of our ſins, with a reſpect to <hi>God.</hi> and not to Us, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our ſins as an <hi>Impulſive Cauſe</hi> are to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as they are ſo diſpleaſing to God, that it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Vindication of God's Honour, and the deterring the World from ſin, that no leſs a ſacrifice of Attonement ſhould be offered than the Blood of the Son of God. <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> ibid.</hi> p. 269.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And as they own a ſort of no Anteceding Impulſive Cauſe, which is but the meer Occaſion of Chriſt's ſuffering ſo they'l call Chriſt's ſufferings a <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> but then they take Puniſhment only in an improper ſenſe, <hi>Paenam improprie dictam fatamur.</hi> So <hi>Crellius,</hi> For, ſaith He, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">What Chriſt ſuffered hath ſo near
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:31799:31"/> a Cognation and Alliance with <hi>true Puniſhment,</hi> that the word <hi>Puniſhment;</hi> and thoſe other <hi>phraſes</hi> uſed in deſcribing proper Puniſhments, may for the greater Elegancy be taken into our Diſcourſes about Chriſt's Paſſion. The Agreement there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt's ſufferings and a proper Puniſhment is very conſiderable. Firſt in their <hi>matter,</hi> for both are afflictive, then in the <hi>Impulſive Procatartic</hi> cauſe: which is <hi>ſin</hi> in the ſenſe the Biſhop obſerved, and at laſt in the <hi>Effect,</hi> and <hi>End,</hi> which is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move guilt, and bring men off from their ſins, tho' in the manner there is ſome difference. But then the great Difference is as to the <hi>Formal Reaſon</hi> of <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> which not being found in Chriſt's ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings they can't be properly a Puniſhment. Crel. Reſponſ. ad Grot. de ſatisf. ad cap.</hi> 1.</p>
                     <p>Thus, what Approaches ſoever they ſeem to make towards the Truth, they utterly deny that ſin is in a proper ſenſe the Meritorious Cauſe of Chriſt's ſufferings; Or, that Chriſt's ſufferings are a proper Puniſhment.</p>
                     <p>There are amongſt the <hi>Arminians</hi> alſo, ſome who agree too much with the <hi>Socinians</hi> in denying Chriſt's ſufferings to be properly a Puniſhment, they holding them to be rather <hi>Dolorous</hi> than <hi>Poenal,</hi> who are juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Socinianizing-Arminians;</hi> ſuch as <hi>Epiſcopius, Carcellaeus,</hi> and <hi>Limborch,</hi> who do their utmoſt to corrupt the Doctrine of Chriſt's <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> They own that Chriſt was <hi>Puniſhed Loco noſtro,</hi> in our Place and Stead, and yet deny his <hi>Sufferings</hi> to be <hi>properly Poenal,</hi> allowing 'em to be but <hi>Improperly,</hi> or <hi>Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gically</hi> a <hi>Puniſhment.</hi> That the ſufferings of Chriſt, as to the Reaſon of the thing, were a Natural Evil, endured for Sin, as ſin was the Occaſion, or remote Cauſe, and may be aptly enough called Puniſhment. But they would rather call them a <hi>Vicarious Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as they are <hi>Vice Poenae,</hi> in the <hi>Room,</hi> and <hi>Stead</hi> of a <hi>proper Puniſhment.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:31799:31"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Gerardus Voſſius,</hi> in a Letter to <hi>Grotius,</hi> is very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, that in this point <hi>Epiſcopius</hi> differed from him. For, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Tho' He owned that Chriſt's Sufferings had a reſpect unto God and not only, unto men; yet the Grand Queſtion is, ſaith He, <hi>what reſpect?</hi> As for the Opinion commonly Embraced, <hi>viz.</hi> that Chriſt bore that <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> which was due to us, he could by no means admit, becauſe then He thought Chriſt muſt have been plung'd into deſpair, and ſuffer the very Torments of Hell; and that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin would be made hereby Impoſſible — That his Notion of ſatisfaction was that as, in the <hi>Old Teſtament, ſins were</hi> Pardoned on <hi>the Offering of a Sacrifice without any ſuffering of a Puniſhment;</hi> even ſo, in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> on <hi>the Intervention of Chriſt's Sacrifice,</hi> which abundantly excels them under the <hi>Old,</hi> are all our ſins forgiven us: That herein, lay the Errour of <hi>Socinius,</hi> that He Denied Chriſt's Sacrifice to be properly <hi>Propitiatory.</hi> Epist. Praeſt. Viror. Ep.</hi> 278. Thus far <hi>Epiſcopius,</hi> who, in his publick Writing uſed more Caution, yet to his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Friend He thus freely opens himſelf, and <hi>Limborch</hi> thought it meet to acquaint the World with it, <hi>Curcellaeus,</hi> who ſucceeded him in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors Chair, declares freely, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That Chriſt did not <hi>Satisfie,</hi> as is commonly apprehended, by ſuffering all thoſe Puniſhments, which we had deſerved by our Sins. Firſt, becauſe ſuffering Puniſhment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to the Reaſon of a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> and hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Common with it. Sacrifices are not <hi>Debito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Solutiones,</hi> the Payment of Debts, as appears from the Legal Inſtitutions. Curcel. Relig. Chriſts Inſtit. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 19. § 14, 15.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lemborch</hi> holds the ſame Opinion, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">It may be in a certain ſenſe ſaid, that <hi>Chriſt was Puniſhed for us,</hi> as there was laid upon him a Vicarious Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that is Affliction, <hi>quae Poenae vicem ſuſtenuit,</hi>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:31799:32"/> in the place and ſtead of puniſhment. <hi>Limb. Theol. Chriſt. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 22. § 2.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Having thus ſtated the Controverſie between the Orthodox and the <hi>Socinians,</hi> together with <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepius</hi> and his Followers, I will conſider the Enquiry; What is the <hi>Nice Difference between Chriſts Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Obligations of the Violated Law of Works;</hi> and his Anſwering <hi>for our Violation of the Law of Works?</hi> And deſire my Brother to conſider, that a Man may ſubſcribe to this Aſſertion, <hi>That Chriſt anſwered for our Violation of the Law of Works,</hi> conſiſtently with his denying Chriſts Sufferings to be properly paenal: But <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eeing, the violated Law of Works <hi>obliged</hi> unto a <hi>proper puniſhment,</hi> Chriſt could not Anſwer for us the <hi>Obligations</hi> of this Violated Law any otherwiſe than by ſuffering a <hi>Proper Puniſhment</hi> for our ſins; So that, tho' an inſiſting on Chriſts Anſwering for our Violation of the Law of Works, ſecures not this Great Truth of Chriſts ſuffering a proper Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for our ſins; yet his Anſwering the <hi>Obligations of the Violated Law,</hi> doth it moſt effectually. But,</p>
                     <p n="5">5. My Brother aſſuring us, that no Terms or Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages were waved and paſſed by but ſuch as could not bear a ſound Senſe, and this word <hi>[Obligations]</hi> which eſtabliſhes Chriſts ſuffering a <hi>proper puniſhment</hi> being waved, is it not a plain Indication, that my Brother hath at leaſt a concern for them, who with the <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopians</hi> deny the Sufferings of Chriſt to be a proper Puniſhment, or Satisfactory to Gods Juſtice for our ſins, or hath in ignorance ſpoken all this?</p>
                     <p n="6">6. It's now time therfore, to gather up what my Brother hath ſaid to the ſhaking the Foundations of Chriſts Satisfaction; which is ſo very much, that an Engliſh <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian,</hi> in the way now eſteemed moſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to ſucceed, could do no more towards it.</p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:31799:32"/>
                     <p>If any one of them hath made it his Province to expoſe the Aſſertion of a <hi>Neceſſity of a Commutation, or Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us, hath rejected the Phraſes, of Christs ſustaining the Perſon of Sinners; of a Change of Perſons between Christ and us; of laying the guilt of our Iniquities upon Chriſt; of his Anſwering the Obligations of the violated Law of Works; of his bearing our ſins in his own body, as our Surety, and feeling the weight of Gods wrath in the puniſhment of our ſins tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd upon him,</hi> and expoſe them all as what <hi>can't bear a ſound Senſe,</hi> but are <hi>lyable to be Interpreted to a Senſe, and ſound of Malignity to the whole of the Goſpel; and Ridiculing ſome of them as Jargons of Art, of a very late Contrivance; fit to amaze, puzzle and confound mens <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings,</hi> affirming, that their ſenſe and meaning muſt be <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> and that the Phraſe of <hi>Christs ſuffering in our stead,</hi> cannot ſignifie more than <hi>for our good:</hi> Should, I ſay, an <hi>Engliſh Socinian</hi> ſtart up and write after this rate, would you not be apt to ſay he hath done his part to break down the Barriers of our holy Religion in the Article of Chriſts Satisfaction, he hath made many bold ſtroaks, and done his moſt to ſubvert this Glorious Doctrine. Why, theſe things are done by my Reverend Brother; who, I hope, was not aware of what he was adoing, when he wrote his Rebuke, but I'll not aggravate, I will only endeavour to Inculcate.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That the Rejecting ſo many ſound Terms and Phraſes, eſtabliſhed by a long Preſcription in the Church of God, as moſt apt to explain the Truth and and diſtinguiſh it from Error, may be juſtly eſteemed as a good Reaſon for ſuch an one, as obſerved thus much in a calm way and manner to do his moſt for the ſecuring the endangered Truths.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That the Rejecting them for the Reaſons menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the Rebuke may Juſtly Allarm the Orthodox amongſt us, and Juſtifie their inſiſting on a fuller ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:31799:33"/> for Truth than the third Paper Affords. But I ſhall have a fair Occaſion to preſs this Conſideration ſome what further, in my Anſwer to the following Enquiry.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>VI.</hi> Why ſo many Orthodox Terms, and Phraſes, which were in the Firſt Paper, are left out of the third?</head>
                  <p>Altho' I have already ſuggeſted what my Brother has ſaid of the Reaſon; yet, it being a Matter of great Importance, I will, in this place, be more full, in ſetting before you what he ſaith of the <hi>Mature Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration,</hi> and <hi>Just Reaſons,</hi> upon which they have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected thoſe Phraſes; and then ſhow who are herein imitated, and what are the moſt likely Conſequences of ſuch a Practice.</p>
                  <p>As to what my Brother ſaith of the Brethrens Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting theſe Phraſes, with deliberation and for juſt Reaſons, take his own Words.</p>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p n="5">
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">5. Thoſe Brethren, who had their <hi>Heads,</hi> their <hi>Hands,</hi> and <hi>Hearts</hi> too, in <hi>Drawing, Dreſſing,</hi> and <hi>ſigning</hi> the former Paper, when they had heard the <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Arguments</hi> of the <hi>whole Body;</hi> where all Matters were managed, not in a <hi>haſty</hi> and <hi>praecipitate</hi> way, but with the <hi>greateſt calmneſs, by ſlow paces,</hi> with great liberty and freedom of debate, and being <hi>now</hi> diſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbred from the Counterpoize of Oppoſitions, or Inſinuations; might, and did ſee <hi>Just</hi> Reaſons to <hi>alter the Phraſes,</hi> and new-model ſome Expreſſions.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">6. And hereof you may be <hi>fuller Aſſured,</hi> inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, as thoſe <hi>individual <hi>Nine</hi>
                           </hi> Brethren, who for, and in hopes of Peace, had ſigned <hi>the</hi> former <hi>Paper,</hi> had their <hi>Hands,</hi> and <hi>Heads,</hi> and <hi>Hearts</hi> too, in the <hi>Forming, Wording,</hi> and <hi>Aſſenting</hi> to this <hi>third:</hi> Nor did they herein alter their Judgments, or vary in the leaſt from <hi>their Zealous Deſires of Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> only they <hi>now</hi> ſaw this <hi>last</hi> Paper was in all things
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:31799:33"/> the ſame with the <hi>former,</hi> ſaving in ſome <hi>few <hi>Paſſages,</hi>
                           </hi> and <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> which carryed a <hi>Face</hi> of ſome <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Tendencies;</hi> which, however they might eſcape the Notice of <hi>Private</hi> Brethren, could not eſcape the <hi>Obſervation</hi> of the <hi>many Diſcerning</hi> Heads, who with <hi>utmost Application,</hi> ſet themſelves to prevent any Inconvenience, that might ariſe to the Truths of the Goſpel.— The Brethren did unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly agree to grant as much as the <hi>Sound Senſe could bear;</hi> and modeſtly <hi>to wave and paſs by the other,</hi> which was lyable to be Interpreted to a <hi>Senſe and Sound of Malignity</hi> to the whole of the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> pag. 29, 30.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p n="1">I. My Brother here gives a Character of ſuch as did Sign the <hi>firſt Paper;</hi> and of them, who Formed, Worded and Aſſented unto the <hi>Third:</hi> The former are <hi>Private Brethren,</hi> who, it's like, were ſo haſty in what they did, that ſome Paſſages of a dangerous Aſpect eſcaped their Notice: The <hi>other</hi> are the <hi>whole</hi> Body, many <hi>Diſcerning Heads,</hi> whoſe obſervation, the dangerous Paſſages could not Paſs; who gave ſuch <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Arguments</hi> to their <hi>Private</hi> Brethren, as convinced them, that there were <hi>Juſt Reaſons</hi> to <hi>Alter the Phraſes and new Model ſome Expreſſions.</hi> Now, that you may the more rightly Judge of this Matter, I will give you the <hi>Names</hi> of theſe <hi>Private</hi> Brethren; who were ſo <hi>Hasty</hi> and <hi>Inconſiderate,</hi> tho' when with the Body, ſo thoughtful as to receive much light from the ſtrong Reaſons of the <hi>many Diſcerning Heads:</hi> They were, Dr. <hi>Bates,</hi> Mr. <hi>Howe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stretton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Alſop,</hi> Mr. <hi>Shower,</hi> Mr. <hi>Burgeſs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Slauter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Quick,</hi> Mr. <hi>Evans,</hi> Mr. <hi>Veal,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> of <hi>Roterdam,</hi> Mr. <hi>Glaſcock,</hi> and three or four more. The <hi>Names</hi> of the <hi>many Diſcerning</hi> Heads, I need not give, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will leave the Reader to Pauſe a while on the Repreſentation my Brother hath given of this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:31799:34"/> and go on to conſider what he further ſaith of them.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. The <hi>Private <hi>Brethren,</hi>
                        </hi> ſuch as Dr. <hi>Bates,</hi> Mr. <hi>Howe,</hi> &amp;c. received ſo much light from the <hi>many Diſcerning</hi> Heads, that as they <hi>might,</hi> ſo they did ſee <hi>Juſt Reaſons</hi> to <hi>alter the Phraſes,</hi> and <hi>New Model</hi> ſome <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> ay, to <hi>wave,</hi> and <hi>paſs by</hi> ſome Phraſes, as what <hi>could not bear a <hi>ſound ſenſe,</hi>
                        </hi> but were <hi>liable</hi> to be Interpreted to a <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>ſound</hi> of <hi>Malignity</hi> to the Goſpel.</p>
                     <p>In this place 'twill be Expedient that we <hi>compare</hi> the <hi>Two Papers,</hi> and ſee what are the <hi>Waved,</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Paſſages.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>The <hi>Firſt</hi> Paper.</head>
                                 <p n="1">
                                    <hi>1. <hi>Bearing with One ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Infirmities,</hi> and <hi>Different Sentiments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout</hi>
                                    </hi> Logical, <hi>or</hi> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical Terms, <hi>or</hi> meerly Humane Forms of Speech, <hi>in</hi> matters of Leſſer weight.</p>
                              </div>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>The <hi>Third</hi> Paper.</head>
                                 <p n="1">
                                    <hi>1.</hi> Bearing with One ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Infirmities, and <hi>Different Sentiments</hi> in matters of Leſſer weight, <hi>not contending <hi>about</hi>
                                    </hi> Logical, or Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical <hi>Terms, or</hi> meer Humane Forms of Speech.</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>The <hi>Alteration</hi> in this place, how <hi>Inſignificant</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it may ſeem to ſome, is in a point, that Affects the <hi>very Vitals</hi> of our Holy Religion; For, by this <hi>Change,</hi> the words [in <hi>matters of leſſer weight,</hi>] being transferr'd <hi>[from Logical Terms]</hi> unto <hi>[different ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments]</hi> a matter of another kind, with an addition of [<hi>not Contending about Logical, or Philoſophical Terms,</hi> &amp;c.] without the Reſtriction <hi>[in matters of leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer weight]</hi> a <hi>Liberty</hi> to contend about theſe <hi>Terms</hi> in <hi>matters of greater weight,</hi> is denied, and the <hi>Aſſenters</hi> unto the <hi>Third</hi> Paper are brought under an Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſit ſtill, as ſilent Spectators, whilſt the <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copians,</hi>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:31799:34"/> and <hi>Socinians</hi> are Expoſing to the greateſt Reproach the <hi>Logical,</hi> and <hi>Philoſophical Terms</hi> and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Forms of Speech,</hi> pitch'd upon by the Church of God to <hi>Explain</hi> the Foundation Points both of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed</hi> and <hi>Natural</hi> Religion.</p>
                     <p>To clear thus much, I deſire to Inculcate theſe following Particulars. 1. That it's an Unexpreſſible Grievance unto all <hi>ſorts</hi> of <hi>Hereticks</hi> to obſerve in the Church of God a <hi>ſtrict Adherence</hi> to thoſe <hi>Logical,</hi> or <hi>Philoſophical Terms</hi> that have been choſen, and ſettled, as what do moſt aptly and clearly explain thoſe glorious <hi>Truths,</hi> diſcovered unto us by the <hi>Light of</hi> Nature, and <hi>Scripture Revelation;</hi> and clearly diſtinguiſh theſe moſt Important <hi>Truths</hi> from Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That it hath been the way of <hi>Heriticks</hi> to <hi>quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel</hi> with theſe <hi>Terms,</hi> becauſe not found in the <hi>Letter of Scripture.</hi> Tho' the Controverſie is about the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of Scripture, ay, about the ſenſe of every Text is there a Controverſie with one <hi>Heretick</hi> or other; yet, will they have us to confine our ſelves to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>phraſes,</hi> in Explaining Scripture <hi>phraſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Tho' it's undoubtedly True, that there is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way to Underſtand the genuine ſenſe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, than by comparing Scripture with Scripture, yet it's no leſs True, that it's not ſo eaſie to convey the True ſenſe unto others without the help of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Forms of Speech.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Amongſt many others it's well obſerved by the learned Mr. <hi>Norton</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> that the moſt <hi>Peſtilent Doctrines</hi> have often times been communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the <hi>Language of Scripture;</hi> which was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why St. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpeaking againſt the Hereſies of <hi>Ebion, Photinus, Marcion,</hi> and <hi>Baſilides,</hi> did ſay, <hi>Think not the</hi> Goſpel <hi>to be in the <hi>words</hi> of the Scripture, but in the ſenſe.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Norton</hi> adds, who is <hi>Ignorant,</hi>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:31799:35"/> that the <hi>Arians</hi> ſpeak Hereſie by that Text, <hi>The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is greater than I, Joh.</hi> 14.28.</p>
                     <p>But <hi>Biddles Scripture Catechiſm</hi> is an illuſtrious Evincement of this Truth, for there he hath in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture words,</hi> delivered very groſs Errours, for inſtance, that God hath a <hi>ſimilitude,</hi> or <hi>ſhape</hi> whoſe <hi>Eſſence</hi> is <hi>confined to the Heavens,</hi> and the like; as alſo, that <hi>God is not Omniſcient,</hi> for he knows not what will be hereafter; Whereas, <hi>in Truth,</hi> God is <hi>Omniſcient,</hi> and <hi>Incomprehenſible</hi> too. And though theſe <hi>Terms</hi> are not in the <hi>Letter</hi> of Scripture; yet the <hi>things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi> in theſe <hi>Terms</hi> and <hi>Phraſes,</hi> are <hi>Expreſly</hi> in the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> And as the learned Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> affirms. <hi rend="margSglQuotes">It is the <hi>Wiſer</hi> and <hi>Safer</hi> Courſe to keep in the <hi>ſame Way,</hi> which the Chriſtian Church hath uſed, ever ſince ſhe hath agreed to expreſs her ſenſe in ſuch <hi>Terms,</hi> which were thought moſt proper for the purpoſe. — And ſince no other can be found more ſignificant and proper for that End, it <hi>looks like yielding too <hi>Great Advantage</hi> to our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,</hi> to <hi>give up</hi> the <hi>Boundaries</hi> of <hi>our Faith. Pref. to the Vindie, of the Prin. p.</hi> 2, 3.</hi> But I do alſo Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That the firſt <hi>Attempts</hi> made by them, who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Faith, are on theſe <hi>Terms</hi> and <hi>Phraſes.</hi> Thus the <hi>Socinians,</hi> (as I have ſhewn in my <hi>Growth of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi>) did about the year 1562. labour to engage the Miniſters in ſome parts of <hi>Poland</hi> to <hi>Abſtain</hi> from the uſe of <hi>Philoſophical Terms, or Humane Forms of Speech,</hi> and as <hi>Stonius</hi> Obſerves, it was this year concluded in a <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>Pin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>zow,</hi> that the Miniſters ſhould not uſe any <hi>Philoſophical Modes</hi> of Speech, ſuch as the <hi>Trinity, Eſſence</hi> &amp;c. but that every one ſhould confine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the <hi>Terms</hi> uſed in the Writings of the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and in the <hi>Apoſtles Creed.</hi> p. 175.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Epiſcopius,</hi> and his Followers took the ſame Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, when they Attempted to ſubvert the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:31799:35"/> received Doctrine about Chriſt's Satisfaction. In a Letter to <hi>Schotlerus,</hi> he confeſſes, 'twas charged upon him, that he uſed other <hi>phraſes,</hi> than thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Church, and ſuch as ſeemed to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the <hi>Socinian</hi> Cauſe, and the Truth of the charge againſt him he does not deny. <hi>Curcellaeus</hi> doth the ſame, and has a <hi>Diſſertation</hi> againſt <hi>Mareſius,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he defends the laying by of ſundry <hi>phraſes,</hi> uſed by the Church of God, becauſe not found in the <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> but both <hi>Epiſcopius</hi> and <hi>Curcellaeus,</hi> did not content themſelves in the laying aſide the <hi>Uſe</hi> of theſe <hi>phraſes,</hi> but went on to oppoſe the Truths Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained by 'em, and at laſt lodged themſelves in the <hi>Socinian</hi> Tents, and are Juſtly, by <hi>Sandius,</hi> placed in the <hi>Anti-Trinitarian Bibliothec.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. As it has been the <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Hereticks</hi> to make their <hi>firſt</hi> Attempts on Orthodox <hi>phraſes,</hi> that they may the more effectually Introduce their Errour; in like manner, it has been the <hi>care</hi> of them, who are <hi>ſound</hi> in <hi>the Faith,</hi> to keep up thoſe <hi>Banks</hi> or Barriers, and to Defend theſe <hi>phraſes,</hi> as the <hi>Boundaries</hi> of the Truth. When <hi>Gregorius Pauli,</hi> and many others of the <hi>Socinian</hi> Faction ſtruggled for the <hi>Diſuſe</hi> of all <hi>phraſes,</hi> not expreſly delivered in Scripture, and <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicius</hi> with Divers others ſo earneſtly contended for their Uſe, as they did moſt clearly expreſs the <hi>Truth,</hi> and diſtinguiſh it from Errour, that <hi>Gregories</hi> party found it moſt Prudent to admit of their Uſe. And the <hi>Orthodox</hi> in all Ages, would by no means part with theſe phraſes.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. In <hi>Imitation</hi> of our Fore-fathers, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>conſtant Practice</hi> of the Church, before and ſince the Reformation, the <hi>Reverend Brethren,</hi> who ſent the <hi>firſt</hi> Paper unto the <hi>Congregational,</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Charge to be, that <hi>the Doctrine of Chriſt's Satisfaction was corrupted,</hi> did in the ſaid Paper, ſingle out, and pitch'd upon thoſe Terms, <hi>Expreſſions</hi> and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:31799:36"/> 
                        <hi>Phraſes,</hi> which have been Uſed by Proteſtants, to Explain this Doctrine. Such as a <hi>Change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us; Chriſts taking on him our Perſon;</hi> and <hi>coming into our <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> and Stead,</hi> to <hi>anſwer for us the <hi>Obligatio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi>
                        </hi> of the <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>red Law of Works;</hi> the <hi>laying the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> our iniquities on Chriſt;</hi> and that <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> as <hi>our Surety,</hi> did <hi>feel,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>ſure of God, and the Weight of his Wrath <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> as men found in the Faith, they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> matter of <hi>Offence</hi> to their <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Brethren But</p>
                     <p n="6">6. How <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> theſe <hi>phraſes</hi> are, how <hi>apt</hi> to explain the <hi>Truth,</hi> and how <hi>Neceſſary</hi> ſoever to diſtinguiſh it from Errour, it cannot be admitted by others, for the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and <hi>ſecret Influences</hi> of that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, who <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>quiſhed the <hi>commonly Received Doctrine of Protestants,</hi> in this Inſtance, are ſo powerful, that theſe <hi>phraſes</hi> muſt be rejected; and what cannot but aſtoniſh our Brethren in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, the Orthodox in the <hi>Church of England, Scotland</hi> and the Reformed abroad, they are rejected, as <hi>phraſes,</hi> that <hi>cannot <hi>be ſafely</hi> retain'd; that can't bear a ſound ſenſe;</hi> but are liable to be Interpreted to a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of <hi>Malignity</hi> to the <hi>whole</hi> of the Goſpel, which is ſuch a bold ſtroke, ſo deep a wound given the Doctrine commonly paſſing in regard to <hi>Christs Satisfaction,</hi> as hath not been given it by any but by ſuch as <hi>Epiſcopius, Socinus,</hi> and their Admirers; and it's carried on with ſo High a Hand, that whoever dares Appear to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect their Attempt, tho' with the greateſt ſoftneſs of Expreſſion, muſt be cried down as a <hi>Fire-brand</hi> and a <hi>Diſturber</hi> of our Peace, and the very Man, who once Pleaded for the Faith, is turn'd with much ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity againſt his Orthodox Brethren, and as if this had been the time to follow the Blow, and ſtrike at all, it is Inſerted as a <hi>Term</hi> of Peace, in the Paper, ſent from <hi>Little St. Hellens,</hi> that there muſt be,</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:31799:36"/>7. <hi>No Contending about Logical, or Philoſophical Terms;</hi> or <hi>meerly humane Forms of Speech; tho' about Matters of</hi> the greateſt <hi>Importance,</hi> as appears by their removing from this Place the <hi>limitation which in the first Paper,</hi> was <hi>[in matters of Leſſer Weight.]</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That I may, in this place, diſcharge my Conſcience with the greateſt Impartiality, I do declare, 1. That I Charge not the Brethren at <hi>Little St. Hellens,</hi> as a <hi>Body,</hi> for I am Perſwaded the greateſt Part of them are not aware of the <hi>Deſign,</hi> or <hi>Tendency</hi> of this <hi>Alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation;</hi> and that the <hi>Chief Contriver</hi> doth <hi>gaudere ſinu,</hi> to Obſerve, how he impoſes on them; and how he has Tooled my Rebuker, who, I would hope, has his Heart as yet untainted with the <hi>Errours,</hi> delivered in his <hi>Rebuke.</hi> However<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. It is moſt evident to me, that as they will An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it in the great Day of the Lord, they are under the ſtrongeſt Bonds of doing their utermoſt to put a Check to thoſe Invaſions made on the <hi>Truth</hi> by the Methods, uſed by the Contriver of the <hi>third Paper.</hi> I ſpeak of them, who are convinced of the <hi>truth of the Commonly received Doctrine of Proteſtants, for by Countenancing this Paper,</hi> they <hi>in Fact Renounce what they Believe to be True;</hi> and by approving of this <hi>Alteration,</hi> which will by no means allow of our <hi>contending about Logical or Philoſophical Phraſes,</hi> tho' in <hi>Matters of greateſt Weight,</hi> they open a gap for the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in all manner of errour; For</p>
                     <p n="8">8. They, by <hi>Aſſenting to this Paper,</hi> have put in a Bar againſt their contending for any Logical Phraſes, and when the <hi>Socinians</hi> ſhall expoſe to Contempt and Ridicule <hi>ſome Phraſes,</hi> which expreſs, what is Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to the Principles of <hi>Natural</hi> as well as of <hi>Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion,</hi> they muſt break their Promiſe, or be ſilent; ſuffering the very <hi>Deiſt</hi> to carry all before him.</p>
                     <p>To clear thus much 'twill be ſufficient to mention what <hi>Biddle</hi> ſays on this <hi>Topick;</hi> I'le give you his own
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:31799:37"/> Words, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Examine therefore the Expreſſions of God's being Infinite, and Incomprehenſible; of his being a ſimple Act; of his ſubſiſting in three Perſons; of a Divine Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuminceſſion; of an eternal Generation; of an eternal Proceſſion of an Incarnation; of an Hypoſtatical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, — of Original Sin; of Chriſts making ſatisfaction to God for our Sins, both past, preſent and to come; of Christs fulfilling the Law for us; of Chriſts being puniſhed of God for us; of Christs merits, his meritorious Obedience, both Active and Paſſive, — of Christs enduring the wrath of God for us,— of Apprehending and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying Christs Righteouſneſs to our ſelves by Faith; of Christs being a Surety; of Christs paying our Debts; of our Sins imputed unto Christ; of Chriſts dying to appeaſe the wrath of God— of infuſed Grace, — of irreſiſtible workings of the Spirit in bringing men to believe — of ſpiritual Deſertions, <hi>&amp;c. — And thou ſhalt find that as theſe <hi>Forms of Speech</hi> are not owned by the Scripture, ſo neither the things contained in them.</hi>
                        </hi> So far <hi>Biddle</hi> in his <hi>Preface to his Catechiſm.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That the things contained in theſe <hi>Forms of Speech</hi> are moſt plainly and expreſly revealed in Scripture, and that God is <hi>Infinite</hi> and <hi>Incomprehenſible,</hi> made known by the Light of Nature, is certain; But that the <hi>Phraſes</hi> themſelves are not <hi>Literally</hi> in the Scriptures muſt be acknowledged, and if we muſt not contend about the above-mentioned <hi>Phraſes,</hi> will not the Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of <hi>Biddle</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> Triumph over us? And ſhould this <hi>Paper</hi> paſs as the <hi>Senſe of the Diſſenters,</hi> would they not provoke unto it, to the great grief of many ſound and godly Divines in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as well as of our Country Brethren?</p>
                     <p>But, I will ſay it again, for I believe it to be true, that there are not five of the Brethren who meet at <hi>Little St. Hellens,</hi> who are aware of this and that, on a review, they will never bring themſelves under
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:31799:37"/> the <hi>Obligation</hi> of not contending for the above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Phraſes,</hi> tho' but humane Forms of Speech, ſuited to explain the neceſſary Articles of Religion, ſo far is my Brother from the Truth, when he ſaith, that the <hi>third</hi> Paper was with that deliberation, ſlow paces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Compoſed.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>The Firſt Paper.</head>
                                 <p n="2">
                                    <hi>2.</hi> Altho' Regeneration, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance towards God, Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and holy Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, are by Gods expreſs word manifestly neceſſary to the Salvation of a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, yet that none of theſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>The Third.</head>
                                 <p n="2">
                                    <hi>2.</hi> That altho' the expreſs word of God do Aſſert the neceſſity of Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to our entring into the Kingdom of God, and Requires Repentance, that our ſins may be blotted out, and Faith in Chriſt, that we may be juſtified, and holineſs of heart and life, without which we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee God; Yet that none of theſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>It will be expedient, that I do in this place ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That according to what my Brother de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares again and again, it muſt be ſuppoſed that this <hi>Paſſage</hi> in the firſt Paper can't be ſafely retained, that it can't bear a <hi>Sound Senſe,</hi> but is lyable to be interpreted to a <hi>Senſe and Sound of Malignity</hi> to the <hi>whole</hi> of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> and therefore upon <hi>mature deliber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi> waved, and another <hi>Paſſage</hi> put into its place; whereas, in my Opinion, no one, that is not of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſort of <hi>Antinomians,</hi> even a <hi>Libertine,</hi> who denys <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, Repentance towards God, Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and Holy Converſation, to be neceſſary to the Salvation of Sinners,</hi> dares ſay, <hi>that this Paſſage can't bear a Sound Senſe,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>therefore must be Altered.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:31799:38"/>
                     <p>That my Brother has out-run himſelf, and all his old avowed Principles, in this way of Writing, is enough to awaken us all to take heed, how we do in the leaſt Point, turn aſide from the Truth, nothing being more manifeſt than that <hi>uno abſurdo dato mille ſequuntur.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But tho' my Brothers <hi>Writings</hi> are in this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſo extravagantly Erroneous, I would willingly hope, 1. Better things of him, and in Charity will place this <hi>Miſtake</hi> amongſt his <hi>Incogitancies,</hi> concluding that when he ſaid, what alterations were made, were upon <hi>Juſt Reaſons,</hi> and what was <hi>waved</hi> could not <hi>Bear a Sound Senſe,</hi> he did not think on the <hi>paſſing by this Paſſage,</hi> it being very common for Men in a heat to forget themſelves.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. My Brother doth perhaps look on this <hi>Paſſage,</hi> in the <hi>firſt Paper,</hi> not to contain in it, ſo full a Teſtimony againſt <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> as he could wiſh, and thinks needful, which I ſhould have more firmly believed, in caſe he had not delivered himſelf ſo poſitively as above: However, I think it not amiſs to ſhow what fell under Conſideration, when this <hi>Point</hi> was to be <hi>ſtated.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. It was thought moſt conducive to the great end, to avoid as much as poſſible, a running into the Diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and Determination of Differences of <hi>leſſer mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which were agitated amongſt the godly Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox themſelves, and therefore to keep to thoſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which did more nearly concern the <hi>Eſſential Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. There being a Controverſie amongſt the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med themſelves about the order, between Faith and Repentance, as which hath the <hi>Antecedence</hi> and <hi>Priority;</hi> and whether Repentance was a neceſſary <hi>praerequiſite</hi> to pardon, the <hi>Compoſers</hi> of the <hi>Firſt</hi> Paper waved the determination thereof; which was no more than was done in the Compoſing the Seven <hi>Propoſitions</hi>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:31799:38"/> which were renounced to the end we might expreſs our abhorrence of <hi>Antinomian</hi> Errours; a brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of which will be needful, not only to detect my Brothers miſtakes touching matter of Fact in this one point, but to Inlighten others in this Affair.</p>
                     <p>It muſt then be carefully minded, 1. That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> of which my Brother ſpeaks, <hi>pag.</hi> 23. was drawn up by ſome Brethren of <hi>both Perſuaſions;</hi> of which number the very <hi>Perſon,</hi> my Brother takes to be the <hi>Reporter,</hi> was One, who faithfully tranſcribed the ſeven Propoſitions agreed unto, and by Direction carried 'em unto the B<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren at <hi>Little St. Hellens,</hi> where he Read them, and expreſſed his great ſatisfaction of the Renunciation, as ſeveral of them, who do now ordinarily meet there can Teſtifie.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That whereas Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> inſiſted on the Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the neceſſity of Repentance in order to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, about which the Orthodox have different Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, 'twas at laſt agreed to aſſert the <hi>neceſſity of Repentance,</hi> and leave this Controverſie undetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which was done by declaring againſt what was <hi>Oppoſite</hi> in this matter unto the Aſſembly, as you have it in the fourth <hi>Propoſition,</hi> where we renounce the Doctrine of them who hold <hi>[That any may expect Pardon without Repentance.]</hi> To return,</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The only difference that I can ſee between the <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Third</hi> Paper, in this particular, muſt be in theſe words, [<hi>That God requires Repentance that our ſins</hi> may be blotted out] which look as if the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining this Controverſie had been deſigned: The reaſon why I can ſee no other difference is, becauſe I know that the Congregational do hold, That <hi>the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Word of God</hi> doth Aſſert <hi>the neceſſity of Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to our entring into the Kingdom of God; and Faith in Chriſt that we may be Juſtified, and Holineſs of Heart and Life, without which we cannot ſee God,</hi> for theſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:31799:39"/> things are all included in what is in the <hi>firſt</hi> Paper. And in caſe my Brethren, who glory in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining themſelves unto <hi>Scripture Expreſſions,</hi> will take in the whole verſe, they refer unto, when they ſay <hi>[That God requires Repentance that our ſins may be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out,]</hi> which is <hi>[When the times of Refreſhing ſhall come from the Preſence of the Lord]</hi> I know not a Man among the Congregational, that will ſcruple to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs his Aſſent unto this Clear and Full Teſtimony againſt <hi>Antinomians</hi> in the Fundamental Article of <hi>Juſtification:</hi> And, if any of them do agree with <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanus,</hi> and many more ſound Proteſtants in this <hi>Unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided</hi> Controverſie, it cannot advantage the <hi>Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians,</hi> eſpecially ſeeing they hold, <hi>That none may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Pardon without Repentance.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>
                                    <hi>Firſt</hi> Paper.</head>
                                 <p n="3">
                                    <hi>3.</hi> Yet that none of theſe, or any work done by men, or wrought by the Spirit of God in them, is <hi>under the Notion of Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,</hi> or under any Denomination <hi>whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any</hi> Part of that Righteouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                              <div type="paper">
                                 <head>The <hi>Third.</hi>
                                 </head>
                                 <p n="3">
                                    <hi>3.</hi> Yet that none of theſe, or any work done by men, or wrought by the Spirit of God in them, is, under any <hi>Denomination whatſoever <hi>any Part of that Righteouſneſs,</hi>
                                    </hi> &amp;c.</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p n="1">1. In this place the words <hi>[Vnder the Notion of Subordination]</hi> is waved, and as my Brother will have us believe, upon the <hi>weightiest Reaſons,</hi> as what can't <hi>bear a ſound ſenſe.</hi> And yet,</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The following words which are left in <hi>[under any Denomination whatſoever]</hi> ſhould methinks be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive enough to take in under 'em <hi>[the Notion of Subordination]</hi> for a Subordinate Righteouſneſs falls within the circle <hi>[of any Denomination whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.]</hi> But,</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:31799:39"/>3. My Brother can't endure to ſwallow a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, which this muſt be, in caſe the phraſe <hi>[un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Notion of Subordination]</hi> cannot bear a ſound meaning, as it cannot in the Opinion of my Brother, becauſe it's waved; and yet is comprized under [any Denomination whatſoever] which muſt bear a ſound ſenſe becauſe not paſſed by, for which reaſon we muſt endeavour to ſave it from a Contradiction, which cannot be but by reſtraining this Univerſal Term <hi>[<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder any Denomination whatſoever]</hi> thus, <hi>[un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any Denomination whatſoever that can bear a ſound ſenſe,]</hi> but <hi>[the Notion of Subordination]</hi> not being able to bear a ſound ſenſe it's not to be taken within the verge of <hi>under any Denomination whatſoever.]</hi> Well then,</p>
                     <p n="4">4. If this phraſe <hi>[under the Notion of Subordination]</hi> can't bear a ſound ſenſe, it muſt be becauſe they hold a Subordinate Righteouſneſs in our Juſtification, where it muſt be noted, that here is the mention on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>one Iuſtification,</hi> which carrieth in it the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin,</hi> the <hi>accepting of ſinners,</hi> and an <hi>Entituling them to Eternal Life;</hi> and that this Juſtification is not <hi>only</hi> by <hi>Chriſts Righteouſneſs, but alſo</hi> by a <hi>Subordinate one,</hi> of our own, they both concurring to our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, the one <hi>Principally,</hi> the other <hi>Subordinately.</hi> This is the only way, that I can think on to fetch my Brother off from a Contradiction, and yet do I what I can I muſt at laſt lodge him under a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. For,</p>
                     <p n="5">5. This <hi>Third</hi> Paper doth expreſly declare, that we are <hi>Pardoned, Accepted,</hi> and <hi>Entituled to Eternal Life <hi>only</hi> by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed unto us, and received by Faith alone.</hi> But to be Pardoned, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and Entituled unto Eternal Life <hi>only</hi> by Chriſts Righteouſneſs, and yet to be Pardoned, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted or Entituled to Eternal Life by a <hi>Subordinate Righteouſneſs of our own</hi> is an Implication. Being thus
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:31799:40"/> neceſſitated to leave my Brother in theſe dark ſhades, I will return to the <hi>private Brethren,</hi> ſuch as Dr. <hi>Bates,</hi> Mr. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Mr. <hi>Alſop,</hi> and the reſt of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination, to ſee what Influence that light, which they received from the <hi>many diſcerning Heads</hi> hath had on them, which my Brother aſſures me was very great. For, he ſaith,</p>
                     <p n="3">III. <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Thoſe Individual nine Brethren, who for, and in hopes of Peace had <hi>ſigned</hi> the <hi>former Paper,</hi> had their <hi>Hands,</hi> their <hi>Heads,</hi> and their <hi>Hearts</hi> too, in the <hi>forming, wording,</hi> and <hi>aſſenting</hi> to this <hi>Third</hi>— For they <hi>now</hi> ſaw in the <hi>former</hi> ſome few <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>aſſages</hi> and <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> which carried a <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>e</hi> of ſome <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Tendencies;</hi> which, however they might eſcape the <hi>Notice</hi> of <hi>Private Brethren</hi> could not paſs the obſervation of <hi>many diſcerning</hi> Heads.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In Examining this Paſſage, it muſt be remark'd.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That theſe <hi>Private</hi> Brethren, every one of the <hi>Individual Nine,</hi> ſaw the Face of ſome <hi>dangerous Tendencies,</hi> in the <hi>Firſt</hi> Paper, which they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Subſcribed, and therefore muſt be now ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to Repent of <hi>that;</hi> but whether this be true or not, I appeal to their own <hi>Conſciences,</hi> for, till this Brother publiſhed his <hi>Rebuke,</hi> I could not hear one word to this purpoſe, ſome of 'em aſſuring me, that the <hi>Alterations</hi> between the two Papers were but <hi>very Minute,</hi> ſuch <hi>Tan<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>lla</hi> as were not worth a contending about, and not of ſuch things as were of <hi>dangerous Tendencies.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Several of the <hi>Nine</hi> have very lately declared their Approbation of the <hi>Firſt</hi> paper, and one of 'em in particular told me, that my Brother was guilty of a <hi>Notorious Falſhood</hi> in ſaying, that the <hi>Individual Nine</hi> had their <hi>Hands,</hi> their <hi>Heads,</hi> and <hi>Hearts</hi> in the form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wording and aſſenting to the Third Paper, for he had neither Hand, nor Head, nor Heart in it.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:31799:40"/>3. If the Individual <hi>Nine</hi> had a <hi>Hand,</hi> a <hi>Head</hi> and a <hi>Heart</hi> in compoſing the third, and in <hi>Waving</hi> the <hi>Phraſes,</hi> rejected, becauſe they could not bear a <hi>ſound ſenſe,</hi> then muſt Dr. <hi>Bates,</hi> who is one of the <hi>Nine Private</hi> Brethren. be for a waving the <hi>Phraſes,</hi> of <hi>Chriſts ſuſtaining the Perſon of ſinners;</hi> and <hi>ſuffering the wrath of God as our Surety,</hi> as what could not bear a <hi>ſound ſenſe,</hi> and if it be ſo, I do humbly <hi>conclude</hi> that 'tis his <hi>Duty</hi> to anſwer that part of his <hi>Harmony,</hi> where theſe <hi>Phraſes</hi> are uſed, and the Doctrine they expreſs is Aſſerted and Defended.</p>
                     <p>But ſure I am, that I have heard him ſay, that the <hi>Harmony</hi> was the fruit of <hi>Fervent Prayer</hi> of his cloſeſt ſtudies, and moſt Impartial Examination, not only of the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> but of their <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> and that, tho' twas his reſolution to follow light, and if he could meet with good reaſons to convince him, he was in an Errour, he would fall under it, yet hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he has met with no reaſons to move him to change his mind, and to this purpoſe he has ſpoke ſince the <hi>compoſure</hi> of the Third Paper.</p>
                     <p>To cloſe my Anſwer to this Enquiry, it's manifeſt to me that my Brother and his <hi>Teacher</hi> are for <hi>reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the above mentioned Orthodox <hi>Terms</hi> and <hi>Phraſes,</hi> becauſe they have forſaken the <hi>Proteſtant Doctrine, as ordinarily conceived by them.</hi> Tho' I have put my Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on the outmoſt ſtretch in favour of my <hi>Rebuking</hi> Brother, yet muſt I ſay, That, if he doth not ſee the <hi>Tendencies</hi> of a rejecting the aforeſaid <hi>Phraſes,</hi> upon the <hi>Reaſons</hi> he has aſſigned, to be deſtructive of the Proteſtant Faith in the Article of <hi>Chriſts Satisfaction,</hi> He is not the ſitteſt Man in the World to enter on a Controverſie of this kind; and yet I muſt at the ſame time acknowledge, that the more unmeet any one is to enter on this Controverſie, the more likely he is to be impoſed on by his more <hi>ſeeing</hi> guide,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:31799:41"/> who doth, in the inſtance before us, as the nature of the thing ſpeaks, leave the Reformed; and nothing ſhort of this can be the <hi>import</hi> of my Brothers argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in his <hi>Rebuke.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Aſſertion I do confeſs leads me to the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the <hi>ſeventh Enquiry,</hi> which is,</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>VII. In <hi>what Confeſſions</hi> are the <hi>Terms</hi> or <hi>Phraſes,</hi> ſo much contended for to be found?</head>
                  <p>My Brother is very confident, that the <hi>Phraſe</hi> of a <hi>Change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us,</hi> and his <hi>taking on him the Perſon of Sinners</hi> is not in any one <hi>Confeſſion of Faith.</hi> For, ſaith he,</p>
                  <div type="rebuke">
                     <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Obſerve further, That the Phraſe of a <hi>Change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us,</hi> and his <hi>taking upon him the Perſon of Sinners,</hi> are Terms wholly Unknown to thoſe <hi>Confeſſions</hi> and <hi>Articles,</hi> which were made the Teſt of <hi>ſoundneſs in the Faith,</hi> by the United Miniſters, nay, if you have the leiſure, ſearch the <hi>whole Body</hi> of <hi>Confeſſions</hi> of the Reformed Churches from <hi>Helvetia</hi> to <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> thence to <hi>America,</hi> and you ſhall not find theſe <hi>Terms, Phraſes,</hi> or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in any one of them. p. 17.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. This <hi>ſtrong Aſſurance</hi> of my Brother brings to my remembrance a paſſage I have met with in Mr. <hi>Baxters Catholick Theology</hi> of a <hi>Jocular Contemptuous Defendant;</hi> who, whilſt He pretended to have a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from all the <hi>Syſtematical Divines</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> was ſo <hi>Charitably Uncharitable</hi> as to ſay, <hi>That <hi>never a man</hi> in his Wits <hi>affirmed, That the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt was the</hi> Formal <hi>Cauſe of</hi> our Iuſtification. <hi>(Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. to the Praemun. par.</hi>
                        </hi> 2.) whereas, on the other hand, <hi>Davenant,</hi> who was far from being a <hi>Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> or from repreſenting the Proteſtants to be ſo,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:31799:41"/> doth aſſure us, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That it is the common ſenſe of all our Divines, that the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, imputed to us, is the <hi>Formal</hi> Cauſe of our Juſtification,</hi> and as to what pertains to the <hi>thing it ſelf,</hi> not one Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Divine has either ſpoke, or <hi>written otherwiſe.</hi>
                        </hi> Praelect. de Juſtit. hab. c. 22.</p>
                     <p>This Over-bold, Raſh, and Untrue Aſſertion of the <hi>Jocular Defendant,</hi> ran in my Mind as ſoon as I entred on the Examination of what the <hi>Rebuker</hi> here ſays, not only becauſe He has as little reaſon for what he ſays, but upon another account. For,</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Do we in good earneſt preſs for what hath not the countenance ſo much as of <hi>One <hi>Confeſſion of Faith?</hi>
                        </hi> This would really be hard, and Provocation ſufficient to ſtir up his Ange<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> againſt the offended Brethren. To whom, in Anſwer I do declare, that if I had not found theſe phraſes in ſome <hi>Publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions;</hi> nay, if I had not met with them in the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> I would have been ſilent and never have put Pen to Paper, on this occaſion. Miſtake me not, my meaning is, that the <hi>things ſignified</hi> by theſe <hi>Terms</hi> and <hi>Phraſes,</hi> are expreſly in our Confeſſions, and in the <hi>Holy Scriptures too;</hi> and perhaps it may appear that the phraſe moſt expoſed by him, will be found to be literally in <hi>one</hi> or <hi>other Confeſſion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. That I may ſet what I now <hi>declare</hi> in the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt light, I muſt obſerve unto you,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That the phraſes, of a <hi>Commutation, or Change of Perſons between Chriſt and us; of Chriſts ſuſtaining our Perſon;</hi> of his <hi>being Subſtituted into our room;</hi> and his <hi>Suffering in our Place and Stead,</hi> are ſo nearly Allied to each other, that they are as <hi>Hypocrates</hi> his <hi>Twins;</hi> they Live and Dye together. Grant one and all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily come in with it; oppoſe but any one of 'em in the genuine meaning, and you oppoſe all of'em.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Phraſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſts Dying in our Place and Stead,</hi> as it imports ſomewhat more than for <hi>our good,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:31799:42"/> 
                        <hi>a Subſtitution of Chriſt into our Place,</hi> which <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be without a change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us;</hi> or without <hi>Chriſts ſuſtaining</hi> our <hi>Perſon.</hi> If then any one of theſe phraſes be found in any one Confeſſion, there is an owning all the reſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Thoſe Scriptures, which ſpeak of Chriſts <hi>Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for us;</hi> of his being a <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> and of his being our <hi>Surety to ſatisfie the Law for us,</hi> do all import Chriſts <hi>Suffering in our ſtead,</hi> his <hi>being Subſtituted in our Place, a change of Perſons between him and us, and his ſuſtaining our Perſon</hi> in ſuffering.</p>
                     <p>What I here aſſert is ſo clear, that there is no doubt of it amongſt the Orthodox, who throughly underſtand this Controverſie. Yea further,</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Theſe controverted phraſes do expreſs what is eſſential unto a <hi>Real, Proper</hi> and <hi>Plenary ſatisfaction</hi> to Gods Juſtice for our ſins, and upon this account, in what confeſſion ſoever ſuch a ſatisfaction is aſſerted, there theſe phraſes are owned.</p>
                     <p>If then I can direct to the <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> where either a <hi>Proper Satisfaction</hi> is aſſerted; or, where 'tis decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that <hi>Chriſt as our <hi>Surety</hi> ſuffered for us;</hi> or, that <hi>Chriſt ſuffered in <hi>our Place</hi>
                        </hi> and <hi>Stead;</hi> or <hi>ſtood in our Perſon,</hi> when He Died, I hope it may ſatisfie any unprejudiced perſon, that the phraſes Contended for are in our Confeſſions; and if I ſhew that all theſe laſt mentioned are in ſome publick Confeſſions or Catechiſms, why may it not be enough to remove my Brother from his Faſtneſſes; and oblige him to conclude, that they who plead for their uſe are not ſo ſingular as he has Inſinuated?</p>
                     <p>Theſe things Praemiſed, our firſt Enquiry muſt be,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. In what <hi>Confeſſion</hi> is a <hi>proper Satisfaction</hi> owned? Go to the <hi>Aſſemblies, cap.</hi> 8. <hi>ſect.</hi> 8. and there you may read, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That the Lord Jeſus by his <hi>Perfect Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of himſelf, hath <hi>fully ſatisfied</hi> the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of his Father. And <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:31799:42"/> Chriſt by his <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> did make a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Real,</hi> and <hi>Full</hi> Satisfaction to his Fathers Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice on their behalf.</hi> The ſame is repeated in the <hi>larger Catechiſm</hi> in anſwer to the Queſtion, <hi>What is Juſtification?</hi> and to that which follows it.</p>
                     <p>If my Brother can't ſee in the aſſertion of [a <hi>Proper, Real and Full Satisfaction</hi> made for us by Chriſt to the <hi>Juſtice of God.</hi>] the <hi>Phraſe</hi> [of a <hi>Change of Perſons between Chriſt and Us,</hi>] it is not becauſe it's not there. For in a <hi>Proper Satisfaction,</hi> whatever is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential thereunto, as a <hi>Commutation, or Change of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons between Chriſt and Us is,</hi> is contained; and whoever underſtands the true nature of a proper Satisfaction, cannot but ſee it. However for the ſake of the leſs ſtudied, I will by a very plain inſtance Illuſtrate thus much; affirming, that all ſound Believers are <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from that Obligation to Puniſhment</hi> they lay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for their paſt ſins, that the <hi>Obligation unto Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> is in their caſe, diſſolv'd, that this is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine embraced by the Reformed. Now, if my Brother demands of me, in what Confeſſion of Faith is this phraſe [of <hi>Diſſolving the Obligation to Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>] to be found; In anſwer, I'll refer him to the Aſſemblies Confeſſion. cap. 11. ſect. 1. <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Thoſe whom God Effectually calleth, he alſo Freely Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth — by <hi>Pardoning their Sins.</hi>
                        </hi> If he ſaith, he can't in this place ſee the phraſe [of <hi>Diſſolving the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to Puniſhment.</hi>] I'll tell him, it is there, tho' he can't ſee it, for in the <hi>Pardon of ſin</hi> it is, it being <hi>Eſſential</hi> unto <hi>Pardon,</hi> that the <hi>Obligation unto Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be diſſolv'd,</hi> to talk of the Pardon of a ſinner whilſt he continues to lye under the Obligation unto Puniſhment, is to Trifle, and to ſay, that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving the Obligation to Puniſhment cannot be read, where the Pardon of ſin is expreſſed, is to talk after ſuch a manner as Modeſty wont give me leave to call by its moſt proper name.</p>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:31799:43"/>
                     <p>The ſame is true of Chriſts <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and a <hi>Commutation of Perſons between Chriſt and Us;</hi> for, a Commutation of Perſons between Chriſt and Us, is as eſſential unto a proper Satisfaction, as the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving the Obligation to Puniſhment is unto Pardon of ſin.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The <hi>phraſe</hi> [of Chriſts <hi>ſuffering <hi>in our place and ſtead,</hi>
                        </hi>] as it imports ſomewhat more than <hi>for our good,</hi> implies a <hi>Commutation of Perſons between Christ and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s;</hi> and ſignifieth the ſame with Chriſts <hi>ſuffering in our Perſon, as our Surety.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That it is thus underſtood by the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> I have already cleared, and to what hath been ſaid, I will add the Judgment of the <hi>Palatinate Divines,</hi> which they delivered into the <hi>Synod of Dort,</hi> which was, That one Errour, amongſt the many embraced by the <hi>Remonstrants,</hi> was [the ſame which my <hi>Brother</hi> has in his <hi>Rebuke,</hi> viz.] That <hi>to Die for ſinners must not be understood, as if Christ died <hi>Loco, aut vice ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum,</hi>
                        </hi> in their <hi>Place and Stead, <hi>ſed</hi> bono tantum,</hi> but <hi>only</hi> for <hi>their good.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This <hi>Errour</hi> theſe Divines, (in what they have ſaid on the <hi>ſecond</hi> of the <hi>five Articles</hi>) did confute, aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in oppoſition unto them, that <hi>Chriſt our Surety</hi> according to the Scriptures died <hi>Loco Peccatorum,</hi> in the place of ſinners, which in their <hi>Orthodox Antithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> they thus explain, <hi>partim <hi>Loco,</hi> partim <hi>bono</hi> ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> And it was Decreed by this <hi>Synod,</hi> 
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That whereas we were unable of our ſelves to ſatisfie Gods Juſtice, and deliver our ſelves from his Wrath, God of his <hi>Immenſe</hi> Mercy, gave his <hi>only begotten Son</hi> to be a <hi>Surety</hi> for us; who, that he <hi>might make <hi>Satisfaction</hi>
                           </hi> for us, was <hi>made Sin,</hi> and a Curſe on the Croſs <hi>for us,</hi> or <hi>vice nostra,</hi> or in <hi>our ſtead.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Decree was about the year 1623. received by the Reformed in <hi>France</hi> in the Synod of <hi>Charen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi>
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:31799:43"/> and ſubſcribed by the Paſtors and Elders of the ſaid Synod, with a <hi>Proteſtation</hi> in the <hi>Preſence of God,</hi> that through his grace, they would never depart from it; decreeing that it ſhould be inviolably obſerved by all the Churches, and Univerſities in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
                     <p>And, in the <hi>Aſſemblies Confeſſion,</hi> Cap. 11. Sect. 3. it is expreſs, <hi>That Chriſts Obedience and Satisfaction was accepted in <hi>their ſtead;</hi>
                        </hi> and why <hi>accepted in <hi>their ſtead?</hi>
                        </hi> but becauſe Chriſt obeyed and ſatisfied in <hi>their ſtead?</hi> which, as I have ſhown, is as much as to ſay, Chriſt <hi>obeyed and ſatisfied in our Perſon.</hi> But of this more immediately under the next Head.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The <hi>Term <hi>[Surety]</hi>
                        </hi> when applyed to Chriſt, as ſuffering for <hi>our ſins,</hi> denotes to us a <hi>Change of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons between him and us,</hi> and his ſuſtaining our <hi>Perſon, in his ſufferings.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus much is ſo evident, that they who have any tollerable Acquaintance with this Controverſie, and oppoſe the Phraſes of a <hi>Change of Perſons between Christ and us, and of Chriſts ſuſtaining our Perſon,</hi> do alſo deny that <hi>Chriſt ſuffered as our Surety.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> himſelf therefore Rejects Chriſts being under the Law of Works, as our <hi>Surety,</hi> upon the old <hi>Socinian</hi> Bottom, as ſaid to be inconſiſtent with the Free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of Sin. <hi>Man made Right.</hi> p. 92, 96. And my Brothers <hi>many diſcerning Heads</hi> do not only Reject Chriſts <hi>taking on him the Perſon of Sinners,</hi> as a Phraſe that can't bear a <hi>Sound Senſe,</hi> but they alſo Reject this other Phraſe <hi>[of Chriſts being conſidered in Relation to us, <hi>as our Surety, bearing our ſins in his own Body]</hi>
                        </hi> and leaſt thus much ſhould have been inferr'd from that other <hi>Phraſe</hi> of <hi>[Chriſts feeling and bearing <hi>the Weight of Gods Wrath]</hi>
                        </hi> it is alſo Rejected as what is lyable to a <hi>Senſe and Sound of Malignity to the whole of the Goſpel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:31799:44"/>
                     <p>Now, if I muſt believe, as my Brother ſuggeſts, that theſe alterations and the Rejecting of theſe Phraſes is upon the aſſigned Reaſons is the deliberate Act of the whole Body, compoſed of <hi>many diſcerning Heads,</hi> that ſtill profeſs a Zeal for all the Doctrines contained in the <hi>Aſſemblies Confeſſion; Larger and ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Catechiſm.</hi> I muſt declare, God knows, with a ſincere deſire, it may be with brokenneſs of Heart, and the deepeſt Humiliation, that our Caſe, in this regard, is more deplorable than I am willing to ſuggeſt, tho' I can't but reflect on the Calamitous Condition, into which our Brethren in <hi>France</hi> have fallen, ſince they omitted to witneſs ſo fully as they ſhould have done againſt <hi>Armyraldian</hi> Incroachments made on the Common Faith of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> eſpecially ſeeing they are now out done, by <hi>ſome amongſt our ſelves.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If Chriſt was not as our <hi>Surety,</hi> made under the Law; If he did not endure the moſt <hi>grievous Torments, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately in his Soul,</hi> and moſt <hi>painful Sufferings in his Body, as <hi>feeling and bearing the Weight of Gods Wrath</hi> due to us for our ſins,</hi> how ſhall we be able to ſtand before the Bar of God in the great day? <hi>Will the Lord be pleaſed with thouſands of Rams, or with ten thouſands of Rivers of Oyl? Shall I give my Firſt-born for my Tranſgreſſion, the Fruit of my Body for the Sin of my Soul?</hi> Theſe things can't ſatisfie Gods Juſtice, nor appeaſe his Wrath, nor make an <hi>Attonement</hi> for our Sin. It muſt be Chriſts Suffering in our <hi>ſtead, his bearing our ſins in his Body, as our Surety, and feeling, and bearing the Weight of Gods Wrath for our Sins,</hi> that alone can ſave us.</p>
                     <p>But theſe <hi>Phraſes,</hi> tho' they were in the <hi>Firſt Paper,</hi> are <hi>waved,</hi> and left out of the <hi>Third,</hi> becauſe, as my Brother ſays, they can't <hi>bear a ſound Senſe,</hi> &amp;c. whilſt a Zeal is pretended for the <hi>Aſſemblies Confeſſion and Catechiſm,</hi> in which the rejected Doctrines are <hi>literally</hi> aſſerted. In the <hi>Confeſſion, Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3, 'tis expreſs,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:31799:44"/> 
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That the Father called the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> to the Office of a <hi>Mediator,</hi> and <hi>Surety:</hi> And in <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. this Office the Lord Chriſt did moſt willingly undertake, which that he might <hi>diſcharge,</hi> he was <hi>made under the Law,</hi> and did perfectly fulfil it, endured moſt <hi>grievous Torments <hi>in his Soul,</hi>
                           </hi> and moſt <hi>painful Sufferings <hi>in his Body.</hi>
                           </hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe things the Lord Chriſt endured as <hi>our Surety;</hi> which is more fully delivered in Anſwer to that Queſtion, <hi>How is Juſtification an Act of Gods Free Grace?</hi> In which you will ſee Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> his Objection againſt Chriſts <hi>being under the Bonds of the Law,</hi> as <hi>our Surety,</hi> taken from a ſuppoſed inconſiſtency be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween it and the forgiveneſs of our Sins fully remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, in that it's there declared, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Altho' Chriſt, by his <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> did make a <hi>Proper, Real</hi> and <hi>Full Satisfaction</hi> to Gods Juſtice; yet in as much as God accepteth <hi>the Satisfaction</hi> from <hi>a Surety,</hi> which he might have demanded of <hi>them,</hi> did provide this <hi>Surety,</hi> his own only Son, imputing his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs to them, and requiring nothing of them for <hi>their Juſtification</hi> but <hi>Faith,</hi> which alſo is his gift, their <hi>Justification is to them,</hi> of <hi>Free-Grace.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But if Chriſt, as <hi>our Surety,</hi> doth ſo, will it not follow, <hi>that he paid our Debts?</hi> Yes, it will; And ſo, ſaith the <hi>Aſſembly, Confeſ. Cap.</hi> 11. § 3. <hi rend="margSglQuotes">
                           <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by his <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Death, <hi>did fully diſcharge the Debt</hi>
                           </hi> of all thoſe that are thus Juſtified, and did make a <hi>proper, real,</hi> and <hi>full Satisfaction.</hi>
                        </hi> Did he not then <hi>feel and bear the Weight of Gods Wrath?</hi> Ay, he did ſo: And thus much is affirmed by the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> in the ſame Words, it is rejected by the <hi>many diſcerning Heads;</hi> For, in Anſwer to this Queſtion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>How did Chriſt humble himſelf in his Death?</hi> It is in the <hi>Larger Catechiſm,</hi> thus, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">Chriſt humbled himſelf in that, having been betrayed by <hi>Judas</hi>—and having alſo <hi>conflicted with the Terrors of Death,</hi> and the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:31799:45"/> 
                           <hi>powers of Darkneſs, <hi>felt and bore the weight of Gods Wrath;</hi>
                           </hi> he <hi>laid down his Life an Offering for ſin.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whether a Rejecting the Phraſes of Chriſts bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Sins in his Body, <hi>as <hi>our Surety,</hi>
                        </hi> and <hi>his feeling and bearing the weight of Gods Wrath,</hi> be not a <hi>Contravening</hi> a <hi>Doctrinal Article,</hi> eſtabliſhed by the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter?</hi> and whether this Brother who doth ſo, ought not to be Cenſured by the Body of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Miniſters,</hi> if we may be ever ſo bleſſed, as to ſee ſuch a Meeting <hi>once more.</hi> I ſubmit to more diſcerning Heads; and ſure I am, that, however this Matter may iſſue, it's plain enough to me, that the Controverted <hi>Phraſes</hi> are owned by the Synod of <hi>Dort<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> eſtabliſhed in the Reformed Churches in <hi>France,</hi> as well as by the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of Learned, Judicious, Godly and Orthodox Divines at <hi>Westminſter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Well, but tho' I had leiſure to look into all the Confeſſions at home; or ſearch the whole Body of Confeſſions of the Reformed Churches from <hi>Helvetia</hi> to <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> thence to <hi>America,</hi> can I find, in any one of them, the leaſt Countenance given to theſe Terms, Phraſes, or Expreſſions? Or is it poſſible to Obſerve in any one of them, ſo much as a ſmile on that Phraſe of Chriſts ſuffering in our <hi>Perſon?</hi> I anſwer,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. What, tho' I can't? Is it not enough that I have ſhown, that the Controverted <hi>Phraſes</hi> are included in the Acknowledgment of Chriſts making a <hi>proper Satisfaction to Gods Iuſtice for us?</hi> And that they are all virtually owned, which in ſundry Confeſſions and Synods, which have openly Received the Phraſe of <hi>Chriſts ſuffering in our Stead,</hi> as it ſignifyeth more than <hi>for our good,</hi> and is of the ſame Import with <hi>Chriſts ſuffering in our Perſon,</hi> but the owning that Chriſt as our <hi>Surety,</hi> felt and bore the <hi>weight of Gods Wrath,</hi> ſhould, methinks, be ſufficient. However,</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That my Brother may ſee, that without going
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:31799:45"/> ſo far as <hi>Helvetia, Tranſylvania</hi> or <hi>America,</hi> we may find enough nearer home to convince him, that he has very little, or no Reaſon for his aſſuming way of Writing, I will only take a turn into <hi>Scotland,</hi> where we ſhall find this very <hi>Phraſe</hi> of <hi>Christs dying in our Perſon,</hi> inſerted in their <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> 
                        <hi rend="margSglQuotes">It became the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and <hi>Redeemer</hi> to be <hi>True God,</hi> and True Man, becauſe he was to ſuffer the <hi>Puniſhments</hi> due for our ſins, and to appear, [quaſi in <hi>Perſona noſtrâ,</hi> coram Judicio Patris pro noſtrâ tranſgreſſione, &amp; in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiâ pati, morte, mortis authorem ſuperare]</hi> in <hi>our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> before the Judgment Seat of the Father to ſuffer for our Tranſgreſſions, and by death to deſtroy him that had power over Death. Vid. <hi>Carp. Confeſ. Ed. an.</hi> 1612. <hi>pag.</hi> 142.</p>
                     <p>Here you ſee that the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> above a hundred years ago, uſed this very <hi>Phraſe,</hi> which, my Brother aſſured us, could not be found in any one Confeſſion: and which, he ſays, doth make a <hi>Blaſphemous Repreſentation</hi> of Gods Love in the Redemption of falen Man, but I hope, when he ſhall be ſo far reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered as to be able to entertain ſome <hi>free Thoughts,</hi> on this Subject, he will do his part, to repair the <hi>Breaches</hi> he has, by his <hi>Rebuke,</hi> made on one of the Chief Articles of our Holy Religion, and do what in him lyeth, to clear the Orthodox from thoſe unjuſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches he has covered them with, by making them to hold and defend Blaſphemous Opinions in their uſe and defence of the Controverted <hi>Phraſes;</hi> And that it may be thus, it ſhall be my Prayer, and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it may be alſo the Prayer of all them who love the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity.</p>
                     <p>There is one thing more needful to be ſpoken unto, before I cloſe my <hi>Reply:</hi> It is the Third and Laſt <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Head,</hi> I have propoſed to be conſidered.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:31799:46"/>
               <head>III. The <hi>Charge</hi> of <hi>Antinomianiſm.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. MY <hi>Brother,</hi> that he may put the fairer Gloſs, upon the <hi>New Notions,</hi> he has undertaken the Defence of, applyeth himſelf to the ſame <hi>Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> by which the <hi>Socinian<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> of old, uſed to Propagate their Hereſies, which was to expoſe the <hi>Ref<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed,</hi> as Men of <hi>Antinomian Principles,</hi> Men of a very bad <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,</hi> and ill <hi>Deſigns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That he has, without any provocation given him, thus <hi>Aſperſed</hi> his <hi>Congregational Brethren,</hi> in the Bulk, without a <hi>Salvo</hi> to the Reputation of any one of them, I will particularly evince.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Charge of Antinomianiſm;</hi> He layes in thus, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">The <hi>True Reaſon of their</hi> (the <hi>Congregational Brethrens) ſevere displeaſure</hi> conceived againſt the <hi>Third Paper</hi> is, that it has ſo <hi>clearly</hi> and <hi>fully</hi> born its <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt the <hi>Antinomians in the Fundamental Article of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> Reb. p. 56. A little before this, 'I wiſh (ſaith he) you could inform me, Whether they, [<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Congregational</hi>] have received any <hi>New Revelations,</hi> or made any <hi>New Diſcoveries</hi> of theſe <hi>great Secrets,</hi> and <hi>Indi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>penſible Neceſſity</hi> of theſe <hi>New Notions?</hi> [that is, if the <hi>Terms, Phraſes,</hi> and <hi>Doctrines,</hi> long ago open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly embraced by the Reformed] 'Whether they [the <hi>Congregational</hi> ſtill] are become <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>Adepts,</hi> in the <hi>Roſacrucian Myſteries,</hi> or have found out the Philoſophers Stone to turn all <hi>Antinomianiſm</hi> into pure Gold. <hi>pag.</hi> 50.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will here, only tell you, that theſe <hi>Roſacrucians</hi> are a People, who hold, that by the help of a Spirit which <hi>Penetrates</hi> the Univerſe, they are adorn'd with ſuch <hi>Angelical</hi> Wiſdom, as excels the Knowledge, convey'd to us by the Holy Scriptures, by which they may underſtand whatever is done, or can be known in the World— They are a ſort of <hi>Chimists,</hi> who, in their <hi>Laboratories</hi> deſired Inſtruction, either from the <hi>Stars,</hi> or after the manner of <hi>Enthuſiaſts,</hi> expect <hi>ſecret
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:31799:46"/> Inſpirations</hi> and <hi>Revelations;</hi> as alſo <hi>Converſes</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences</hi> with Spirits, and great Aſſiſtances from them; whereupon many have been ſtrangely deluded by the Devil, who transforms himſelf into an Angel of <hi>Light.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>Roſacrucians,</hi> my Brother ſpeaks of, and as one in doubt, wiſhes to be informed, whether the <hi>Congregational,</hi> are not <hi>Adepts,</hi> great Proficients in their <hi>Helliſh Myſteries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Character he further gives of them is, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That they are <hi>Pettyfoggers,</hi> whoſe work it is to ſow the Seeds of Strife, <hi>pag.</hi> 31. whoſe <hi>deſultory Humours</hi> (or giddy Brains) can no more be fixed than <hi>Proteus</hi> can be bound. <hi>pag.</hi> 33. who are no longer of an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion than till the next Crotchet comes into their Heads to invent another. <hi>pag.</hi> 33. <hi>Great Intreaguers, <hi>p.</hi>
                     </hi> 29. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable Men, Malitious Slanderers,</hi> Guilty of a more heinous Sin, in that they Uſurp the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of God to Judge the <hi>Heart.</hi> p. 34. whoſe <hi>Grief,</hi> to obſerve how much the Doctrine of <hi>Christs Satisfaction</hi> is in danger, may remember you of what you Read in ſome <hi>Naturalists,</hi> That the <hi>Crocodile</hi> weeps over his Pre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and then devours it; whoſe Tears are all Mockery. <hi>p.</hi> 54. who lye Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> to the Stake to be Baited, (by their <hi>Party,</hi> that is, (by the Engliſh <hi>Moloſſi,</hi> or <hi>Maſtiff-Dogs,</hi> and every <hi>Whaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing Welp,</hi> that could bark, tho' not bite, <hi>Vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Cruel,</hi> putting ſuch Terms upon Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> as are not ſo <hi>Merciful,</hi> as thoſe put upon the Men of <hi>Jabeſh Gilead</hi> by <hi>Nahaſh,</hi> 1 Sam. 11.2. who would only thruſt out their <hi>Right Eyes,</hi> but theſe [<hi>viz</hi> The <hi>Congregational</hi>] would <hi>cut off his Right Hand too.</hi> p. 58. whoſe <hi>Terms</hi> favour too much of <hi>Empire</hi> over <hi>Souls,</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> over the <hi>Conſciences</hi> and <hi>Faith of Men.</hi> p. 59 Who, when they promiſe not to make further Publick Conteſts, yet will then be for <hi>Private Whiſperings, Evil Surmiſes, Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Slanders,</hi> and <hi>Clandeſtine Reproaches,</hi> whilſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:31799:47"/> Mr. <hi>W.</hi> is <hi>alive,</hi> and 'tis to be feared will <hi>feed</hi> upon <hi>his Carcaſs,</hi> and Survive his Duſt and Aſhes. That theſe Bigots will never forgive them, who have join'd with the Brethren of a more <hi>Benign Temper</hi> in the <hi>Third Paper.</hi> p. 60.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the way he takes to Treat a whole Party of Brethren in this City, who are known to be Men of <hi>Integrity, ſoundneſs in the Faith,</hi> and <hi>ſucceſsful Labourers</hi> in the <hi>Vineyard of our Lord;</hi> But I will make no other Return than to aſſure him, it's my prayer, he may ſee, and conſider what he has done, and that the Lord will ſoften his heart, and forgive him. As for what he ſaith of the <hi>Reporter,</hi> I will not repeat one word of it, only I will accquaint you with what little Reaſon my Brother had to Inſinuate, as if the <hi>Reporter</hi> had been a favourer of Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s <hi>Errors,</hi> and what Obligations he lyeth under to clear himſelf fom the ſuſpition of <hi>Antinomianiſm;</hi> for ſuch indeed is the Nature of <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> that how diſtant ſoever ſome Hereſies are, in their appearances from each other, they frequently center in one and the ſame Point.</p>
               <p>To evince what I have here ſuggeſted, 'twill be ſufficient to propoſe what my Brother ſaith of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters Zeal</hi> for Dr. <hi>Crisps,</hi> and make my Reply.</p>
               <div type="rebuke">
                  <head>Faithful Rebuke.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="margSglQuotes">The <hi>Propoſal</hi> of a full <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt <hi>Antinomia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm,</hi> is the unpardonable Sin againſt Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> which ſhall never be forgiven by the <hi>Reporter.</hi> p. 57.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. That my Anſwer may be the more clearly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, it muſt be noted, that I ſpeak of the <hi>Perſon,</hi> who is by my Brother taken for the <hi>Reporter,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be Right, or not, in his Conjecture; and by the <hi>Rebuker,</hi> I mean the Man that is <hi>Famed</hi> to be ſo. This premiſed, I affirm,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That there is not the leaſt pretence for his inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating, that the <hi>Reporter</hi> is a favourer of Dr. <hi>Criſps</hi>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:31799:47"/> Notions; but there are divers reaſons for my inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on it, that my Rebuker is not free from the ſuſpition, if not liable to a charge of giving Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to them, and ſo ſtands bound to clear himſelf.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It's well known unto me, That when the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter</hi> did, about ſeventeen years ago, write againſt <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> with a particular Reference unto ſome aſſertions of Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> my Brother gave him ſufficient encouragement to expect his Mid-wiſing it into the World by a <hi>Praefatory Epiſtle,</hi> which upon ſome noiſe made on the mention of the Doctors Name, he declin'd to do. When my Brother ſhall call to mind what he wrote in a <hi>Letter</hi> to Φ Χ, He can't, I preſume, but remember that what I here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, tho' ſo long ago, is very true.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. When a <hi>New</hi> Impreſſion of the Doctors <hi>Works,</hi> with an addition of ſome <hi>Sermons</hi> came into the World about ſeven or eight years ſince, the <hi>Reporter</hi> was deſired to ſet his <hi>Name</hi> to the <hi>Atteſtation</hi> before it; but He, apprehending it would be taken for granted, at leaſt by the Common People, that His <hi>Name</hi> would ſtand there as an approval of all the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in that Book, and enſnare many to a cloſure with the very Errours my Brother now ſeems to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt, <hi>Refuſed</hi> to ſet his <hi>Name</hi> unto <hi>it:</hi> And yet he himſelf, notwithſtanding the <hi>Antinomian He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, Horrid Opinions, and Abominable Doctrines</hi> that He chargeth his <hi>Congregational</hi> Brethren with in his One and twenty Poſitions, pag. 25, 26. did ſet his <hi>Hand</hi> unto the Atteſtation before Dr. <hi>Criſps</hi> Book. And there it ſtill remains without a publick recalling it. And I think he can't eaſily forget, <hi>when,</hi> and where he was charged with it, and call'd upon to give ſatisfaction, but was ſo Inflexible, that no other could be obtain'd, than that the Charge was <hi>Rude</hi> and <hi>Ignorant,</hi> and ſo braved it out.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>Reporter</hi> is one never like to make any <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies</hi>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:31799:48"/> for the Doctors Notions, as differing from the common Belief of Proteſtants; But, this Brothers Hand is ſet to a <hi>Plea</hi> for them.</p>
                  <p>In a <hi>Preface,</hi> before Mr. <hi>Flavels blow at the Root,</hi> Subſcribed by the <hi>Rebuker,</hi> we have the following defence of thoſe very points, wherein Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> forſook the <hi>Orthodox.</hi> For, it is there declared.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That the <hi>Difference</hi> between Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> and other <hi>good Men,</hi> ſeems to lye, <hi>not ſo much</hi> in the <hi>Things,</hi>
                     </hi> which the one, or the other of them <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> as about their <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Reference <hi>to one another</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is one paſſage, that my Brother has <hi>Subſcribed:</hi> which clears it, That, if He did it with conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſincerity, He could not look on Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> to hold either <hi>Antinomian Hereſies,</hi> or any other <hi>horrid Opinions,</hi> but that as to the <hi>things</hi> themſelves, the <hi>Doctor</hi> is of the <hi>ſame Faith</hi> with my <hi>Rebuker,</hi> which thing once granted, makes it evident, that there could be no ſuch powerful reaſons to influence Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> to write againſt the Doctor as my Brother ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts, <hi>p.</hi> 16. for, when <hi>Differences</hi> are only about the <hi>Order,</hi> and <hi>Reference</hi> of one thing to another, where, as to the <hi>Things <hi>themſelves,</hi>
                     </hi> there is an <hi>Agreement,</hi> then it becomes the Duty of thoſe Brethren, who, in theſe leſſer matters, differ from each other, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe <hi>mutual forbearance;</hi> and, it muſt be, in Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> and thoſe zealous Brethren, who did ſet him on this Work, a Violation of the <hi>Rule</hi> of Chriſtian <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Forbearance,</hi> to make this <hi>Strife;</hi> whence it muſt unavoidably follow, that 'twas Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> who made the <hi>Firſt breach</hi> on the Union, and that my Rebuker, ſo long as his <hi>Name</hi> abides to <hi>this Preface,</hi> can never clear him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. You will ſay, There may be <hi>Agreement</hi> as to the <hi>things themſelves,</hi> and yet about their <hi>Order,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to one another, very material difference. I grant it may be ſo. Tho' for my own <hi>part,</hi> I do
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:31799:48"/> look on the <hi>difference</hi> between the <hi>Orthodox</hi> and Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> to be much greater than this ſort of <hi>Palliating Preface</hi> will allow it to be, and that whilſt my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Name</hi> continues (without a <hi>Retractation</hi>) to be before the Doctors Book, and under this Preface, 'twill be a <hi>Snare</hi> to multitudes; eſpecially, ſeeing He adds his further ſenſe in theſe words.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. But we reckon, that notwithſtanding what is <hi rend="margSglQuotes">
                        <hi>more Controverſible,</hi> in Dr. <hi>Criſps Writings,</hi> there are <hi>much more Material Things, <hi>wherein they cannot but</hi> Agree,</hi> and would have come <hi>much nearer</hi> each other, even in <hi>theſe things,</hi> if they did take ſome <hi>Words</hi> or <hi>Terms</hi> in the <hi>ſame</hi> ſenſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What can be ſaid <hi>more fully,</hi> in <hi>Favour</hi> of Dr. <hi>Criſps</hi> Notions? Did ever the <hi>Reporter</hi> talk thus? I'll go further, if there be any thing dangerous in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors Writings, as I believe there is, what can be ſaid <hi>more</hi> to enſnare poor People to receive that as <hi>Sound</hi> and <hi>True?</hi> Did Dr. <hi>Chauncey</hi> ever ſay more? Shew me where he has at any time ſaid ſo much. 'Tis true, he brings in the <hi>Antinomian,</hi> ſaying as much as he can in his own defence; but he alſo, if I mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake not, tells you, that you are not to look for his Judgment there, but where he brings in <hi>Calvin</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derating between <hi>Neonomian</hi> and <hi>Antinomian. Once more,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whereas my Brother doth, in his <hi>Rebuke,</hi> p. 25, 26. inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, as if the <hi>Cataing<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> of <hi>Artino<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ian Hereſies, horrid Opinions,</hi> and <hi>abominable Doctrines,</hi> had been offered to the <hi>Congregational,</hi> that they might give ſatisfaction to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Brethren,</hi> but would not, (tho' to this day, did I never hear, 'twas tendred to the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> for their <hi>Purgation</hi>) there is reckoned amongſt theſe <hi>Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> this, as the eleventh. <hi>A believer is to work from life, &amp; not for life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And what thinks my Brother of this? <hi rend="margSglQuotes">There is (ſaith he) an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion</hi> in <hi>Vol</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 46. <hi>That Salvation is not the end of any good work we do;</hi> which is like that of another, <hi>We are to Act from Life, not for Life.</hi> Neither of which are (ſaith he) to be rigidly taken as 'tis likely, <hi>they were never meant,</hi> in the ſtrict Senſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the <hi>Plea</hi> my Brother makes for <hi>Criſpian</hi> Notions, in which, if he was <hi>not ſincere,</hi> He ought to be as <hi>publick</hi> in taking the ſhame of it, as the ſetting his Name hath been; If he was <hi>ſincere,</hi> and has received <hi>convincing</hi> Light from his <hi>Maſter</hi> Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> let him
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:31799:49"/> own it to the World, and recal his <hi>Hand</hi> from the <hi>Atteſtation</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Doctors Writings, and from this <hi>Preface.</hi> But if he did <hi>ſincerely</hi> ſet his hand, and is ſtill of the ſame mind, let him conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what it is that hath put him upon this <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>elf-contradicting Province,</hi> which brings him the more under the Reprehenſion and Juſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his being a Favourer of that <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> which is in Dr. <hi>Criſps</hi> Books.</p>
                  <p>Thus I have, ſo far as the <hi>Paper</hi> allotted me would give leave, Examined the <hi>Faithful Rebuke</hi> of my Brother, which I call <hi>[Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful]</hi> not becauſe I can ſee ſo much as one grain of <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> in it, but becauſe 'tis the <hi>Name</hi> He has given it. And what I have don<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> has been with <hi>Impartiality;</hi> For, I thank God, that I having <hi>Felt</hi> the <hi>Diſpleaſure</hi> of ſome of my <hi>Congregational</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, becauſe a Conviction of Truth hath neceſſitated me in ſome inſtances, relating to the <hi>True Way</hi> to Peace, to differ from them both, I am the leſs concern'd tho' I pleaſe neither, ſo long as I am enabled to diſcharge a good Conſcience towards God and All Men. And as I have been <hi>Impartial,</hi> ſo it hath been my care to write according to the Unforeſeen advice, which the Learned and Grave Mr. <hi>Humfrey</hi> hath given me in his <hi>Friendly Interpoſer</hi> (for which I thank him) in that I have been, not only <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmoved</hi> in my ſelf; but have made it my endeavour, that nothing might fall from my <hi>Pen,</hi> expreſſive of undue reſentments. It is <hi>Truth</hi> I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, and glad ſhall I be to ſee more of <hi>that,</hi> whether conveyed to my <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> in the angry way, in which my <hi>Rebuking</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delivers his ſenſe; or in a more <hi>clear, diſtinct</hi> and <hi>calm</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto I muſt acknowledge, that the commonly <hi>Received Doctrine of Proteſtants,</hi> is in my Conſcience moſt agreeable to the Word of God in Scripture; But if at any time, whether in reading what Mr. <hi>Humfrey</hi> has delivered in the ſeveral <hi>Tracts</hi> he has Publiſhed on this Occaſion, in which there is <hi>another</hi> Spirit, and other Matter, and more <hi>Mature</hi> Thoughts than in my <hi>Rebuker,</hi> or otherwiſe from any <hi>Letters</hi> he ſpeaks of hereafter; or in reading any Books written on this Subject by any others, <hi>I ſhall be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,</hi> I am in a <hi>miſtake,</hi> I will not be afraid to own it, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, that the <hi>Truths</hi> of God need neither Mens <hi>Lies,</hi> nor their <hi>Hypocritical Methods</hi> to ſupport them. And I muſt confeſs it, I am the better pleaſed with Mr. <hi>Humfrey,</hi> in that I do ſee by this <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſition,</hi> that the <hi>halting,</hi> the offenſive halting of Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> which I have formerly obſerved, and in theſe Papers my ſelf reprehended, is, in the Point of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> made ſo <hi>Judiciouſly,</hi> and <hi>Fully</hi> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, in this Piece, upon his own <hi>Repugnant</hi> Principles, that if he will be a <hi>Follower</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> as much as a <hi>Leader of the People,</hi> he muſt go quite over to Mr. <hi>H.</hi> (as I have already noted) or come back to the <hi>Received Doctrine,</hi> which he makes <hi>now</hi> to ſerve him only for a Gloſs, but <hi>Recedes</hi> from it. Whether he be <hi>ſincere,</hi> or no, he muſt now ſhow it.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:31799:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
